. >> GOOD AFTERNOON WELCOME TO
THE JANUARY 13TH 2026 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN FRANCISCO
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESIDENT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN PRESENT RANDLEMAN PRESENT SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER
PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL PRESENCE SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR HUANG WONG
PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE RAMAKRISHNA ALONI WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA.
AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE
WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAMAKRISHNA LONI HAVE NEVER
CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY.
AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING
ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOME LAND. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAW
MATERIAL IN THE COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR
SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG
OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH
IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD, INDIVISIBLE WITH LIBERTY
AND JUSTICE FOR ALL. >> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I
WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV TODAY THAT IS
ESPECIALLY KALEENA MENDOZA. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ON LINE. AND WITH THAT MADAME CLERK
LET'S GO TO OUR 2 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER.
>> YES, THE 2 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER IS THE APPEARANCE BY THE
HONORABLE MAYOR DANIEL LURIE TO DISCUSS THE ELIGIBLE TOPICS
SUBMITTED FROM DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR SUPERVISOR CHEN.
THE MAYOR MAY ADDRESS THE BOARD INITIALLY FOR UP TO FIVE
MINUTES. >> THANK YOU.
WELCOME MR. MAYOR. >> MAYOR LURIE, DO YOU HAVE ANY
OPENING REMARKS? I DO.
GOOD AFTERNOON. BOARD PRESIDENT AND MEMBERS OF
THE BOARD. >> FIRST, HAPPY NEW YEAR AND I
LOOK FORWARD TO ANOTHER YEAR OF CONTINUED PARTNERSHIP WITH ALL
OF YOU. TODAY IS AN IMPORTANT MOMENT
FOR SAN FRANCISCO. JUST A FEW HOURS AGO SUPERVISOR
MATT DORSEY AND I ANNOUNCED THAT VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY, ONE
OF THE WORLD'S LEADING RESEARCH UNIVERSITIES HAS SELECTED SAN
FRANCISCO AS THE HOME FOR A FULL TIME ACADEMIC CANCER
CAMPUS BEGINNING IN 2027, VANDERBILT WILL BRING STUDENTS
,FACULTY AND RESEARCH ACTIVITY INTO THE HEART OF OUR CITY.
STRENGTHENING DOWNTOWN, SUPPORTING SMALL BUSINESSES
AND REINFORCING SAN FRANCISCO'S ROLE AS A GLOBAL CENTER OF
INNOVATION. WHEN I TOOK OFFICE I SAID
RESTORING CONFIDENCE IN SAN FRANCISCO REQUIRED BOTH PUBLIC
SAFETY AND LONG TERM INVESTMENT.
THIS DECISION REFLECTS THAT WORK.
MY TEAM ENGAGED MULTIPLE INSTITUTIONS AND VANDERBILT
STOOD OUT AS A PARTNER ALIGNED WITH OUR VALUES.
OUR AMBITIONS AND OUR FUTURE. VANDERBILT'S CHOICE SENDS A
CLEAR MESSAGE. SAN FRANCISCO REMAINS A WORLD
CLASS PLACE TO LIVE LEARN AND INNOVATE.
IT REINFORCES OUR VISION OF A CITY WHERE PEOPLE CAN LIVE,
WORK, PLAY AND LEARN. AND WHERE OUR CITY CORE IS
ACTIVE WELL BEYOND THE 9 TO 5 WORKDAY.
I ALSO WANT TO TAKE A MOMENT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT THIS
ANNOUNCEMENT COMES DURING A TRANSITION FOR THE CALIFORNIA
COLLEGE OF THE ARTS COMMUNITY. CCE HAS BEEN PART OF SAN
FRANCISCO'S CREATIVE AND CULTURAL FABRIC FOR MORE
THAN A CENTURY. THAT LEGACY MATTERS.
I APPRECIATE VANDERBILT'S COMMITMENT TO PRESERVING CCA'S
ARCHIVES SUPPORTING ALUMNI AND CONTINUING THE WAGGA
INSTITUTE OF CONTEMPORARY ARTS THROUGH A NEW INSTITUTE AT
VANDERBILT. VANDERBILT'S PRESENCE WILL
BRING NEW ENERGY, NEW TALENT AND LONG TERM ECONOMIC BENEFIT
TO OUR CITY HELPING TRAIN THE NEXT GENERATION OF LEADERS MANY
OF WHOM WILL CHOOSE TO REMAIN AND STAY HERE THEIR ENTIRE
LIVES. I WANT TO THANK THE CHANCELLOR
DEAR MEYER AND THE VANDERBILT TEAM, THE COMMUNITY AND CITY
STAFF FOR THEIR WORK TO MAKE THIS POSSIBLE.
THIS IS THE KIND OF LONG TERM INVESTMENT SAN FRANCISCO NEEDS
AND IT SHOWS THAT WHAT WE CAN ACHIEVE WHEN WE STAY FOCUSED ON
RESULTS. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU AND CONGRATULATIONS MAYOR LARRY
. >> MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU
PLEASE CALL THE TOPIC FOR DISTRICT 11?
YES. THE TOPICS SUBMITTED BY THE
DISTRICT 11 MEMBER SUPERVISOR CHEN IS STRATEGIES AND FUNDING
COMMITMENTS TO ADDRESS AND PREVENT HUMAN TRAFFICKING
ESPECIALLY DURING MAJOR LARGE SCALE SPORTING EVENTS.
>> SUPERVISOR CHEN PLEASE ASK YOUR OPENING QUESTION.
>> THANK YOU YOUR PERSON AND THANK YOU FOR JOINING US.
MR. MAYOR TODAY. SAN FRANCISCO HAS LONG BEEN A
LEADER ON ISSUES IMPACTING SOME OF THE MOST VULNERABLE
POPULATIONS PARTICULARLY WOMEN AND IMMIGRANTS.
>> WHILE WE ARE EXCITED TO HOST TO BE A HOST CITY FOR THE NFL'S
SUPER BOWL 60 AND FIFA WORLD CLUB THIS YEAR I'M HEARING
GROWING CONCERNS ABOUT POTENTIAL INCREASES IN HUMAN
TRAFFICKING BOTH LABOR AND SEX TRAFFICKING.
BETWEEN 2024 AND 2025 HUMAN TRAFFICKING IN SAN FRANCISCO
INCREASED BY 163%. >> IN RECOGNITION OF HUMAN
TRAFFICKING PREVENTION MONTH AND IN LIGHT OF THIS MAJOR
LARGE SCALE EVENTS COMING TO TOWN.
MY QUESTION TO YOU IS HOW ARE WE ENSURING THAT WE HAVE A
ROBUST INFRASTRUCTURE TO ADDRESS AND PREVENT HUMAN
TRAFFICKING BEFORE AND AFTER THE SUPER BOWL AND WORLD CLUB
BUT ALSO INCREASING CAPACITY TO BE RESPONSIVE DURING THIS EVENT
? SUPERVISOR THANK YOU.
I SAW YOU AT THE PRESS CONFERENCE.
I SAW SUPERVISOR CHAN AS WELL. I REALLY APPRECIATE THE
OPPORTUNITY TO TALK ABOUT THIS BECAUSE IS ABSOLUTELY CRITICAL.
HUMAN TRAFFICKING IS A VIOLATION OF SOMEONE'S
FUNDAMENTAL HUMAN RIGHTS. CHILDREN, WOMEN AND MEN ARE
TRAFFICKED OF ALL AGES. IT CAN AND IT DOES HAPPEN YEAR
ROUND IN EVERY INDUSTRY. IT DOESN'T JUST HAPPEN WHEN
LARGE SCALE SPORTING EVENTS HAPPEN BUT IT DOES TEND TO
INCREASE WHICH IS WHY OUR STRATEGIES CANNOT BE LIMITED TO
JUST WHEN THESE EVENTS OCCUR. NOW I WAS CHAIR OF THE SUPER
BOWL 50 HOST COMMITTEE TEN YEARS AGO.
I KNOW VERY WELL THE AMAZING OPPORTUNITY THAT THESE UPCOMING
EVENTS BRING TO OUR CITY AND OUR REGION.
AND WE WANT THIS TO BE A SUCCESS FOR EVERYONE.
AS I'VE SAID REPEATEDLY KEEPING SAN FRANCISCO AND OUR RESIDENTS
AND VISITORS SAFE IS MY NUMBER ONE PRIORITY.
THIS PRIORITY IS REFLECTED IN MY DIRECTION TO HAVE A WHOLE
OF CITY APPROACH TO PREVENT TRAFFICKING AND SUPPORTING
VICTIMS AND SURVIVORS. SAN FRANCISCO HAS TAKEN A
COMPREHENSIVE SURVIVOR CENTERED APPROACH TO COMBATING HUMAN
TRAFFICKING BY ENGAGING THE PUBLIC.
STRENGTHENING SERVICES AND IMPROVING COORDINATION
ACROSS AGENCIES IN PARTNERSHIP WITH THE BAY AREA HOST
COMMITTEE, NONPROFIT PARTNERS AND S.F. MTA.
WE ARE LAUNCHING A PUBLIC AWARENESS CAMPAIGN INCLUDING
MESSAGING ON TRANSIT TO HELP PEOPLE RECOGNIZE THE SIGNS OF
TRACK TRAFFICKING AND KNOW HOW TO REPORT IT.
AND AS WE LEARNED LAST A FEW DAYS AGO, THE THEME OF THAT IS
IF YOU SEE SOMETHING, SAY SOMETHING.
AT THE SAME TIME THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF VICTIMS RIGHTS IS
PROVIDING YEAR ROUND TRAINING FOR FRONTLINE CITY STAFF
AND KEY INDUSTRY WORKERS WITH SEVERAL THOUSAND BEING TRAINED
FOR FEBRUARY AND FOR SUPER BOWL.
WE ARE ALSO CONTINUING TO FUND TRUSTED MULTI-LANE COMMUNITY
BASED ORGANIZATIONS THAT PROVIDE LEGAL AND SOCIAL
SERVICES NOT ONLY FOR TRAFFICKING RELIEF BUT ALSO FOR
RELATED HARMS SUCH AS EVICTION, DOMESTIC VIOLENCE AND SEXUAL
ASSAULT. THESE ARE CONCRETE ONGOING
ACTIONS TO COMBAT HUMAN TRAFFICKING AND MY
ADMINISTRATION LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING ENGAGEMENT WITH YOUR
OFFICE ON THIS WORK. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, MAYOR, FOR THE RESPONSE AND THE COMMITMENT.
AND LAST YEAR MANY CBOS WHO CONDUCTED WORK IN THE IN THIS
AREA THEY ALL HAD TO FIGURE OUT HOW TO CONTINUE TO MEET THE
NEEDS OF OUR COMMUNITY DESPITE A BUDGET CRISIS.
BUT THIS YEAR GIVEN OUR BUDGET FORECASTS, ARE WE PREPARED TO
FUND THE SERVICES AND PROGRAM TO MEET BOTH THE EXISTING
AND INCREASE THE CAPACITY? AND IF NOT, WHY STRATEGY DO YOU
HAVE BY EMPLOYING TO DO SO? >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHAN WITH THE BOARD'S SUPPORT THE CITY HAS
FULLY MAINTAINED FUNDING FOR OUR GENDER BASED VIOLENCE
SERVICES AND INCREASE THE INVESTMENT BY AN ADDITIONAL
$902,000 OVER PRIOR YEARS. THIS SUSTAINED AND EXPANDED
$9.37 MILLION INVESTMENT IN GENDER BASED VIOLENCE
SERVICES ALLOWS US TO FUND TRUSTED COMMUNITY BASED
ORGANIZATIONS THAT DELIVER ESSENTIAL PREVENTION
AND INTERVENTION SERVICES FOR ADULTS AND YOUTH WHO ARE
SURVIVORS OF DOMESTIC VIOLENCE, SEXUAL ASSAULT, STALKING
AND HUMAN TRAFFICKING. WE FUND MULTIPLE 24 SEVEN
CRISIS LINES STAFFED BY TRAINED ADVOCATES WHICH CAN ABSORB
INCREASED CALL VOLUME AND PROVIDE IMMEDIATE SAFETY
PLANNING REFERRALS AND CONFIDENTIAL SUPPORT.
THIS INFRASTRUCTURE IS GOING TO BE ESPECIALLY CRITICAL AS WE
PREPARE TO HOST SUPER BOWL AND WORLD CUP.
THIS WILL HELP ENSURE THAT SURVIVORS OF TRAFFICKING
AND RELATED VIOLENCE CAN ACCESS IMMEDIATE TRUSTED SUPPORT
BEFORE, DURING AND IMPORTANTLY ALSO AFTER THESE GLOBAL EVENTS.
ADDITIONALLY, WITH THE BOARD'S PARTNERSHIP, THE CITY HAS
INVESTED IN A FULL HOUSING CONTINUUM FOR SURVIVORS FROM
EMERGENCY AND TRANSITIONAL OPTIONS OPTIONS TO THE $30
MILLION IN PROP A CAPITAL FUNDING FOR LONG TERM STABLE
HOUSING. LAST MONTH I INTRODUCED A $3.5
MILLION BUDGET SUPPLEMENTAL TO ENSURE HEIGHTENED OPERATION
EASE DURING A NUMBER OF LARGE EVENTS THIS SPRING INCLUDING
SUPER BOWL. THAT ORDINANCE EXPLICITLY
INCLUDES FUNDING FOR CBOS TO COMBAT HUMAN TRAFFICKING.
I REALLY APPRECIATE YOUR ADVOCACY ON THESE ISSUES.
SUPERVISOR AND AS SAN FRANCISCO PERFECT PREPARES TO HOST SUPER
BOWL AND WORLD CUP, I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH YOU
AND ALL OF YOUR COLLEAGUES TO ENSURE OUR CITY IS SAFE
AND WELCOMING TO OUR VISITORS FROM AROUND THE WORLD.
>> THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, MAYOR LURIE. YOU MAY NOW ASK QUESTION TO
SUPERVISOR CHEN OR TO ANY OTHER SUPERVISOR IN ATTENDANCE
PERTAINING TO THE SAME TOPIC BUT NOT NECESSARILY RELATED TO
THE PREVIOUS QUESTION. I'M GOOD.
THANK YOU. ALL RIGHT.
WELL THEN THANK YOU FOR JOINING US TODAY.
>> APPRECIATE IT. GOOD TO SEE.
>> ALL RIGHT. >> THAT CONCLUDES THE DISTRICT
11 TOPIC DISCUSSION. THE MATTER'S BEEN DISCUSSED
AND WILL BE FILED AFTER GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT.
AND MADAM CLERK, I THINK THAT TAKES US BACK TO COMMUNICATIONS
. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOUR
PRESENCE HERE IN ITS LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER.
ROOM 250 WHEN YOU CANNOT BE HERE.
THESE PROCEEDINGS ARE AIRING LIVE ON S.F. GOP TV'S CHANNEL
26. OR YOU CAN VIEW THE LIVE STREAM
AT W W W DOT S.F. G O V T V.ORG.
IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO SUBMIT YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT YOU MAY DO
SO IN WRITING. YOU CAN SEND AN EMAIL TO BOSSIE
AT S.F. GOV DAWG OR USE THE POSTAL SERVICE JUST ADDRESS THE
ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS THE NUMBER
ONE DR. CARLTON B GOOD PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN
FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94102 IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A REASONABLE
ACCOMMODATION FOR A FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS
WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE,
CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS
IN ADVANCE BY CALLING (415) 554-5184.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR MEETING MINUTES.
APPROVAL OF THE NOVEMBER 18TH 2025 DECEMBER 2ND, 2025
DECEMBER 9TH, 2025 REGULAR BOARD MEETING MINUTES AND THE
NOVEMBER 17TH 2025 SPECIAL MEETING MINUTES AT THE LAND USE
TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE MEETING WHICH CONSTITUTED A
QUORUM OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
>> COLLEAGUES CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES
AS PRESENTED MOVED BY CHERYL. IS THERE A SECOND?
SECOND BY WALTON. MADAM CLERK WE PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED.
>> SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
MANAGEMENT I AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I THERE ARE 11
EYES. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT AS PRESENTED
AND I BELIEVE THIS IS THE POINT AT WHICH I CAN SPEAK ABOUT SOME
AGENDA CHANGES ANTICIPO PATED FOR FOLKS WHO ARE INTERESTED
IN ITEMS 24 TO 27 WE ANTICIPATE THAT THERE WILL BE A MOTION TO
CONTINUE THOSE TO FEBRUARY 3RD. SO IF YOU'RE HERE FOR THAT JUST
LETTING YOU KNOW AND WITH THAT MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR
CONSENT AGENDA PLEASE CALL ITEMS TWO AND THREE TOGETHER
ITEMS TO AND THREE TOGETHER FALL UNDER THE REGULAR AGENDA
UNDER UNFINISHED BUSINESS ITEM TWO MR. PRESIDENT, I SHOULD
READ THE TITLES. YEAH.
ITEM TWO IS AN ORDINANCE TO ORDER THE VACATION OF PORTIONS
OF HAWES AND GRIFFITH STREET BANCROFT AVENUE FOR THE
DEVELOPMENT OF THE SAN FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT
TRAINING FACILITY AT 1236 CARROLL AVENUE TO RESERVE
PUBLIC UTILITY AND ACCESS RIGHTS IN FAVOR OF THE CITY
AND EASEMENT RIGHTS FOR EXISTING ANY OVERHEAD
ELECTRICAL FACILITIES TO APPROVE THE INTERDEPARTMENTAL
TRANSFER OF THE STREET VACATION AREA FROM PUBLIC WORKS TO THE
FIRE DEPARTMENT TO AUTHORIZE OTHER OFFICIAL ACTS TO AFFIRM
THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS
FOR ITEM THREE THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE ZONING MAP OF THE
PLANNING CODE TO CHANGE THE ZONING USE DISTRICTS
DESIGNATION OF ASSESSOR'S PARCEL BLOCKS NUMBER 4877 LOT
NUMBERS 001 THROUGH 004 AND ASSESSOR'S PARCEL BLOCK
NUMBERS 4852 LOT NUMBERS 002 THROUGH ZERO TWO TO THE FULL
WIDTH OF BANCROFT AVENUE BETWEEN GRIFFITH AND HAWES
STREETS AND THE FULL WIDTH OF GRIFFITH AND HALL STREETS
BETWEEN CARROLL AVENUE AND ARMSTRONG AVENUE
COLLECTIVELY KNOWN AS 1236 CARROLL AVENUE FROM PDR TO
PRODUCTION DISTRIBUTION AND REPAIR DISTRICT TWO
AND £0.02 PUBLIC TO CHANGE THE HEIGHT AND BULK DISTRICT
DESIGNATION OF THE AFOREMENTIONED PARCELS
AND ASSESSOR'S PARCEL BLOCK NUMBERS 4852 LOT NUMBER 001
FROM 4-X TO 90 DASH X AND TO AFFIRM THE SEGMENT
DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS TWO AND THREE SUPERVISORS SAUTER
SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN
EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANAGEMENT I AND SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR EITHER R.A. LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
FOR ITEM FOUR IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO
DEFINE A FAMILY AS A HOUSEHOLD TO ELIMINATE NUMERIC LIMITS ON
UNRELATED FAMILY MEMBERS AND REQUIREMENTS THAT FAMILY
MEMBERS SHARE MEALS CLASSIFY RESIDENTIAL CARE FACILITIES
THAT SERVE SIX OR FEWER PERSONS AS RESIDENTIAL USES TO INCLUDE
CERTAIN GROUPS OF SIX OR FEWER PEOPLE AND ASSOCIATED OPERATORS
AS A HOUSEHOLD TO CLARIFY THE ZONING ADMINISTRATORS
ENFORCEMENT AND AUTHORITY TO ADMINISTRATIVELY SUBPOENA
DOCUMENTS TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE
APPROPRIATE FINDINGS. COLLEAGUES, I THINK WE CAN TAKE
THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL .
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO NEW BUSINESS.
>> PLEASE CALL ITEMS FIVE AND SIX TOGETHER ITEMS FIVE
AND SIX ARE TWO RESOLUTIONS THAT RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE
THE DEPARTMENT OF THE ENVIRONMENT TO ACCEPT
AND EXPEND GRANT PRIZES FROM THE UNITED STATES DEPARTMENT OF
ENERGY'S OFFICE OF ENERGY EFFICIENCY AND RENEWABLE
ENERGY. ITEM FIVE AUTHORIZES THE
ACCEPTANCE AND EXPENDITURE OF A $400,000 PRIZE CONFIRMED AS
RECEIVED BY THE DEPARTMENT OF THE ENVIRONMENT DECEMBER 12TH,
2023 TO DEVELOP A PILOT IMPLEMENTATION PLAN TO UPGRADE
TO 200 SAN FRANCISCO HOMES WITH ELECTRIC HEAT PUMPS, WATER
HEATERS AND ENERGY EFFICIENT MEASURES AND TO EXECUTE THE
CONTRACTS BETWEEN THE CITY AND THE CO APPLICANTS PURSUANT
TO THE PURPOSE OF THE AWARDED PRIZE FOR ITEM SIX THIS
AUTHORIZES THE ACCEPTANCE AND EXPENDITURE OF A $400,000
PRIZE CONFIRMED AS RECEIVED BY THE DEPARTMENT OF THE
ENVIRONMENT ON MARCH 17TH, 2025 TO IMPLEMENT A PILOT PROGRAM TO
UPGRADE 20 SAN FRANCISCO HOMES WITH ELECTRIC HEAT PUMP WATER
HEATERS AND ENERGY EFFICIENT MEASURES AND AGAIN LET'S TAKE
THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
SEVEN ITEM SEVEN RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE FOOD AND BEVERAGE
MINIMUM ANNUAL GUARANTEE AND PRE SECURITY RENT REDUCTION
PROGRAM FOR FOOD AND BEVERAGE CONCESSION TENANTS ALLOWING THE
SAN FRANCISCO INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT TO ENTER INTO LEASE
AMENDMENTS TO LOWER THE MINIMUM ANNUAL GUARANTEES FOR 18 OF 69
FOOD AND BEVERAGE LEASES TO LOWER THE PERCENTAGE RENT
STRUCTURE FOR SEVEN PRICE SECURITY LEASES AND ALTER THE
ANNUAL MINIMUM ANNUAL GUARANTEE ADJUSTMENT METHODOLOGY FOR ALL
FOOD AND BEVERAGE LEASES. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEMS EIGHT AND NINE TOGETHER ITEMS
EIGHT AND NINE COMPRISE TWO RESOLUTIONS THAT AUTHORIZE THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND TWO GRANTS.
ITEM EIGHT AUTHORIZES AS AN APPROXIMATE $6.75 MILLION GRANT
FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO GENERAL HOSPITAL FOUNDATION TO
PARTICIPATE IN A PROGRAM ENTITLED Z PC Q I ROUND THREE
OPTIMIZING EPIC TO DRIVE TRUE NORTH AND DEVELOPING OUR PEOPLE
THE Z S F G WAY FOR A TERM JANUARY 1ST 2026 THROUGH JUNE
30TH 2029 AND TO APPROVE THE NOTICE OF THE AWARD AGREEMENT
AND FOR ITEM NINE THIS RESOLUTION AUTHORIZES
AND APPROXIMATE $1.1 MILLION GRANT FROM THE CALIFORNIA
DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH FOR PARTICIPATION IN A PROGRAM
ENTITLED DISEASE INTERVENTION SPECIALIST WORKFORCE
DEVELOPMENT GRANT JULY 1ST, 2025 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2026
AND TO APPROVE THE GRANT AGREEMENT.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. MADAME CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS
TEN AND 11 TOGETHER. >> ITEMS TEN AND 11 ARE TWO
RESOLUTIONS THAT AUTHORIZE, ACCEPT AND EXPEND GRANTS FOR
THE HUMAN SERVICES AGENCY. ITEM TEN AUTHORIZES THE
ACCEPTANCE AND EXPENDITURE OF A $268,000 GRANT FROM BLUE CROSS
OF CALIFORNIA PARTNERSHIP PLAN INC TO PARTICIPATE IN A PROGRAM
ENTITLED HOUSING AND HOMELESSNESS INCENTIVE
PROGRAM FUNDING FOR SAN FRANCISCO APRIL 1ST, 2026
THROUGH MARCH 31ST, 2030 AND ITEM 11 THIS EXCEPTS
AND EXPENDS AN APPROXIMATE $1 MILLION GRANT FROM THE SAN
FRANCISCO HEALTH PLAN TO PARTICIPATE IN A PROGRAM
ENTITLED HOUSING AND HOMELESSNESS INCENTIVE
PROGRAM FUNDING SAN FRANCISCO APRIL FIRST, 2026 THROUGH MARCH
31ST 2030. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEMS 12 AND 13 TOGETHER.
ITEMS 12 AND 13 ARE TWO RESOLUTIONS THAT AUTHORIZE THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH TO ENTER INTO A GRANT AGREEMENT
FOR TERMS COMMENCING ON THE EXECUTION OF THE GRANT THROUGH
JUNE 30TH 2030 BETWEEN THE CITY AND THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT
OF HEALTH CARE SERVICES AND ITS THIRD PARTY ADMINISTRATOR
ADVOCATES FOR HUMAN POTENTIAL INC ITEM 12 THIS IS A $21.3
MILLION ANTICIPATED REVENUE TO INCLUDE PROVISIONS ALLOWING FOR
THE RECAPTURE OF ALLOWABLE PROJECT EXPENSES INCURRED
RETROACTIVE TO MAY 6TH 2025 TO INCLUDE A PERMITTED
AND RESTRICTED USE AT 887 POTRERO AVENUE TO AUTHORIZE
RETROACTIVELY PUBLIC HEALTH TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND GRANT FUNDS
FOR THE PERIOD OF MAY 6TH, 2025 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2030.
AND ITEM 13 THIS AUTHORIZATION HAS ANTICIPATED REVENUE OF
APPROXIMATELY 6.3 MILLION TO INCLUDE A PROVISION ALLOWING
FOR THE RECAPTURE OF ALLOWABLE PROJECT EXPENSES INCURRED
RETROACTIVE TO MAY 6TH, 2025 TO INCLUDE A PERMITTED
AND STRICTLY USE AT 333 SEVENTH STREET RETROACTIVELY
AUTHORIZING THE PUBLIC HEALTH TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND THESE
GRANT FUNDS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> PLEASE CALL ITEM 14. ITEM 14 RESOLUTION TO
RETROACTIVELY APPROVE AND AUTHORIZE THE MAYOR AND THE
DIRECTOR OF THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT TO EXECUTE A GRANT AGREEMENT WITH RSU ASSOCIATES
L.P. IN AN AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 15.3 MILLION FOR
A 20 YEAR TERM TO PROVIDE OPERATING SUBSIDIES FOR 100%
AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT HOUSING FOR LOW INCOME
AND FORMERLY HOMELESS HOUSEHOLDS TO INCLUDE
TRANSITION AGE YOUTH LOCATED AT 78 HAIGHT STREET AND 120
OCTAVIUS STREET TO APPROVE THE FORM AND AUTHORIZING THE
EXECUTION OF THE GRANT AGREEMENT WITH A RETROACTIVE
COMMENCEMENT DATE OF OCTOBER FIRST, 2025 SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 1516 AND 18 TOGETHER
ITEMS 15, 16 AND 18 ARE THREE RESOLUTIONS THAT PERTAIN TO 967
MISSION FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING ITEM 15 AUTHORIZES THE
EXECUTION AND DELIVERY OF A MULTIFAMILY HOUSING REVENUE
NOTE IN A PRINCIPAL AMOUNT OF 21.7 MILLION AND A MULTIFAMILY
HOUSING REVENUE NOTE IN AN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL AMOUNT OF
20 MILLION FOR A TOTAL AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 41.7 MILLION
TO PROVIDE FINANCING FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF A 95 UNIT
MULTIFAMILY RENTAL HOUSING DEVELOPMENT KNOWN AS 967
MISSION AND ITEM 16 APPROVES AND AUTHORIZES THE DIRECTOR OF
PROPERTY AND THE DIRECTOR OF THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING
AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO ENTER INTO A GROUND LEASE FOR
REAL PROPERTY OWNED BY THE CITY LOCATED AT 967 MISSION STREET
WITH 967 MISSION LP A 75 YEAR LEASE TERM AND A 124 YEAR
OPTION TO EXTEND AN ANNUAL BASE RENT OF 15,000 TO CONSTRUCTING
100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING RENTAL HOUSING DEVELOPMENT CONSISTING
OF 95 UNITS FOR SENIOR HOUSEHOLDS KNOWN AS 967 MISSION
TO INCLUDE INCLUDE 40 SENIOR OPERATING SUBSIDY UNITS 24
LOCAL OPERATING SUBSIDY PROGRAM UNITS RESERVED FOR HOMELESS
SENIORS AND SENIORS AT RISK OF HOMELESSNESS AND FIVE UNITS FOR
REFERRALS FROM THE CITY PLUS HOUSING LIST TO APPROVE AN
AUTHORIZED AN AMENDED RESTATED AND CONSOLIDATED LOAN AGREEMENT
FOR 44.3 MILLION AND A 57 YEAR LOAN TERM WITH 967 MISSION LP
TO FINANCE THE DEVELOPMENT AND CONSTRUCTION OF THE PROJECT
. AND FOR ITEM 18 THIS RESOLUTION
APPROVES AND AUTHORIZES THE MAYOR AND THE DIRECTOR OF THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO
EXECUTE A GRANT AGREEMENT WITH 967 MISSION LP FOR 10.5 MILLION
A 15 YEAR TERM TO PROVIDE OPERATING SUBSIDIES FOR A 95
UNIT 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT WITH 40 UNITS OF
HOUSING FOR EXTREMELY LOW INCOME SENIORS.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED. >> AND MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO
OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER. >> OKAY?
YES, IT IS NOW TIME FOR THE RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS
FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO SUPERVISOR DISTRICT THREE SUPERVISOR SAUTER YOU GET
TO START. >> THANK YOU.
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN TODAY I HAVE THE HONOR OF RECOGNIZING DENISE
FIELDER WHO IS AN ACCLAIMED SAN FRANCISCO ARTIST WHOSE RETAIL
STUDIO IS LOCATED IN DISTRICT THREE IS RUSSIAN HILL DENISE,
WOULD YOU COME ON UP AND JOIN US PLEASE?
>> OVER THE PAST FEW MONTHS DENISE'S ARTWORK HAS BEEN SEEN
AROUND THE WORLD MILLIONS AND MILLIONS OF TIMES IN A ONE
INCH BY ONE INCH SQUARE. >> THAT IS BECAUSE HER ARTWORK
HAS GRACED MILLIONS OF POSTAGE STAMPS AS SHE WAS.
THIS YEAR'S FEATURED ARTIST FOR THE HOLIDAY CHEER SERIES.
HOLD IT UP RIGHT HERE FOR EVERYONE TO SEE THIS SERIES OF
FOUR BEAUTIFUL DESIGNS HAS BROUGHT ENDLESS HOLIDAY CHEER
THIS SEASON TO MANY THE STAMP DESIGNS INCLUDE.
AND I HOPE YOU'LL TELL US MORE ABOUT THEM AND THEIR
INSPIRATION A BEAUTIFUL WREATH, A GRACEFUL CARDINAL, AN
ARRANGEMENT OF PEARS, POMEGRANATES AND CITRUS AND A
CHEERFUL HOLIDAY FLOWER BOUQUET AS I IMMATURE STAMP COLLECTOR
FROM MY DAYS GROWING UP I KNOW THAT STAMPS HAVE A BIG IMPACT
DESPITE THEIR SMALL SIZE THEY TELL STORIES.
THEY ARE MARKERS OF HISTORY THAT WILL BE FOUND IN DRAWERS
DECADES OR CENTURIES LATER AND THEY ARE A PHYSICAL SIGN OF
HUMAN CONNECTION WHICH IS SOMETHING WE ALL NEED IN THIS
DIGITAL AGE. >> DENISE WAS FIRST TRAINED AS
AN INTERIOR DESIGNER AND THEN EXPERIMENTED WITH COLLAGE
AND STARTING IN THE 1990S AS SHE WAS WORKING IN THE TEXTILE
INDUSTRY AND SHE ESTABLISHED HER STUDIO PASTE IN 2009.
HER DREAM COMMISSION. AND MAYBE WE CAN WORK TO MAKE
THIS POSSIBLE. HER DREAM COMMISSION IS
SOMETHING FOR A PUBLIC SPACE TO BE SEEN BY ALL.
AND CONTINUING HER GOOD TASTE HER FAVORITE RESTAURANT IS ZUNI
CAFE. >> SHE NOTES THAT HER
INSPIRATION COMES FROM HER EXPERIENCE BEING IN THE NATURAL
WORLD PARTICULARLY PLANTS AND ANIMALS STROLLING IN THE
BEAUTIFUL HILLS OF SAN FRANCISCO.
CUT OUTS OF MATISSE AND 18TH CENTURY ENGLISH ARTISTS
PARTICULARLY FLORAL PAPER MOSAICS.
>> DENISE THANK YOU FOR YOUR DECADES OF ART CREATIVITY
AND CRAFT. THANK YOU FOR REPRESENTING
DISTRICT THREE SO WELL AND FOR ALWAYS FOSTERING SAN
FRANCISCO'S CREATIVE SOUL. >> AND THE FLOOR IS YOURS TO
SAY ANY REMARKS. >> THANK YOU.
I'M SO, SO HONORED TO BE HERE TODAY AND I JUST WANT TO SAY AS
AN ARTIST YOUR ENVIRONMENT SHAPES YOU AND MOLDS YOU AND IT
INSPIRES YOU. AND I HAVE TO SAY THERE'S NO
OTHER PLACE I'D RATHER BE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
IT JUST OFFERS ENDLESS CREATIVE INSPIRATION AND THE STAMPS ARE
ACTUALLY INSPIRED BY THE FARMERS MARKETS HERE.
SO THANK YOU AGAIN. I'M SO SO HONORED.
>> THANK YOU
. DISTRICT FIVE SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD COLLEAGUES TODAY IT IS MY HONOR TO RECOGNIZE OLIVIA
SCANLON FOR HER MORE THAN TWO DECADES OF EXTRAORDINARY PUBLIC
SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> WELCOME, OLIVIA. OLIVIA BEGAN HER CAREER WITH
THE CITY IN 2003 AS A LEGISLATIVE AIDE AT THE BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS WHERE SHE SERVED DISTRICT SEVEN RESIDENTS FOR A
DECADE UNDER THREE SUPERVISORS PROVIDING RARE INSTITUTIONAL
CONTINUITY THAT DEEPLY BENEFITED CONSTITUENTS,
COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS AND POLICYMAKERS ALIKE.
>> DURING HER TIME AT THE BOARD, OLIVIA DISTINGUISHED
HERSELF AS A TRUSTED POLICY LEADER AND A FIERCE ADVOCATE
FOR IMMIGRANT AND UNDOCUMENTED COMMUNITIES CHAMPIONING THE
REVIVAL OF THE IMMIGRANT FLAG RAISING CEREMONY IN 2006.
>> WHAT BEGAN AS A SINGLE RESTORED TRADITION HAS SINCE
GROWN INTO A BROADER PRACTICE OF HONORING THE MANY CULTURES
THAT MAKE SAN FRANCISCO HOME. >> AFTER MASTERING THE ART OF
LEGISLATIVE LEADERSHIP, OLIVIA TOOK ON A NEW CHALLENGE
IN PUBLIC SAFETY SERVING AS CHIEF OF STAFF AT THE SAN
FRANCISCO FIRE DEPARTMENT FROM 2015 TO 2023.
THERE SHE WAS THE RIGHT HAND TO TWO FIRE CHIEFS JOANNE HAYES
WHITE AND JANINE NICHOLSON OVERSEEING GOVERNMENT
RELATIONS, COMMUNICATIONS, BUDGET AND POLICY DURING SOME
OF THE MOST DEMANDING PERIODS IN THE DEPARTMENT'S HISTORY.
>> AND WHILE ANY CHAPTER OF OLIVIA'S CAREER COULD MERIT
RECOGNITION, IT IS HER LEADERSHIP.
>> OVER THE PAST TWO AND A HALF YEARS OF CHIEF OF STAFF AT THE
DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT THAT DESERVES
SPECIAL ACKNOWLEDGMENT TODAY OLIVIA STEPPED INTO THE TEAM AT
A MOMENT OF ENORMOUS TRANSITION AND DESPITE HAVING THE SMALLEST
BUDGET AMONG MAJOR PUBLIC SAFETY AGENCIES, THE
DEPARTMENT'S RESPONSIBILITY IS EXPANDED DRAMATICALLY.
IN ADDITION TO NINE OVER ONE DISPATCH EMERGENCY SERVICES,
EMS REGULATION, FEDERAL GRANTS AND ENCAMPMENT RESOLUTIONS THE
TEAM WAS TASKED WITH LEADING STREET RESPONSE COORDINATING
LARGE SCALE EVENTS AND HELPING CONFRONT SAN FRANCISCO'S MOST
COMPLEX PUBLIC SAFETY CHALLENGES INCLUDING THE DRUG
MARKETS. THROUGH IT ALL, OLIVIA HAS BEEN
A LEADER AMONG LEADERS. SHE BRINGS CLARITY AND AN
ABILITY TO CUT THROUGH THEOCRACY TO GET THINGS DONE.
SHE WORKS ACROSS EVERY DIVISION OF TEAM AND WITH COUNTLESS
DEPARTMENTS TO SOLVE OPERATIONAL PROBLEMS, NAVIGATE
COMPLEX POLICY ISSUES AND KEEP THE CITY MOVING FORWARD DURING
MOMENTS OF CRISIS SOMETHING I KNOW ALL OF US IN THIS ROOM
HAVE BENEFITED FROM AS WELL FROM ADDRESSING THE 911
DISPATCHERS STAFFING CRISIS TO HELPING CREATE THE DRUG MARKET
AGENCY COORDINATION CENTER. OLIVIA HAS BEEN A STEADY FORCE
HOLDING TOGETHER OUR PUBLIC SAFETY SYSTEM.
>> SHE IS ON DUTY EVERY DAY OF THE YEAR RESPONDING TO FIRES,
POWER OUTAGES, STORMS AND ARMY THREATS AND MAJOR EMERGENCIES
ENSURING ELECTED LEADERS AND THE PUBLIC RECEIVE TIMELY,
ACCURATE INFORMATION WHEN IT MATTERS MOST.
>> AS WE ALL KNOW MOST RECENTLY OLIVIA WORKED DAY AND NIGHT TO
SUPPORT THE CITY'S RESPONSE TO THE CITYWIDE DECEMBER BLACKOUT.
>> COORDINATING RAPID RESPONSE STANDING UP POWER OUTAGE
CENTERS AND COMMUNICATING UPDATES WITH ELECTED OFFICIALS
AND RESIDENTS ALIKE. >> OLIVIA DOES THIS WORK NOT
FOR RECOGNITION BUT BECAUSE SHE UNDERSTANDS THAT IN MOMENTS OF
EMERGENCY THE GOVERNMENT MUST FUNCTION AT ITS VERY BEST.
>> SHE IS EMBLEMATIC OF THE BEHIND THE SCENES PUBLIC
SERVANTS WHO MAKE SAN FRANCISCO WORK AND BEYOND HER
PROFESSIONAL CONTRIBUTION EARNS OLIVIA ALSO CARRIES ANOTHER
FULL TIME ROLE AS A DEVOTED PARENT TO HER THREE CHILDREN
ANDREW KIEFER AND CILLIAN. >> ANYONE WHO KNOWS OLIVIA
KNOWS THAT HER FAMILY IS HER FOUNDATION AND THAT HER SERVICE
TO THE CITY IS DEEPLY ROOTED IN HER CARE FOR FUTURE
GENERATIONS. OLIVIA THANK YOU FOR YOUR
LEADERSHIP, YOUR DEDICATION TO VULNERABLE COMMUNITIES AND YOUR
UNWAVERING COMMITMENT TO SAN FRANCISCO.
OUR CITY IS SAFER, STRONGER AND MORE RESILIENT BECAUSE OF
YOUR WORK. THANK YOU.
I THINK MY COLLEAGUES HAVE SOME REMARKS AS WELL.
>> THERE ARE THOSE HONOREES WHO YOU KNOW ARE GOING TO TRIGGER A
A LIST IN THE QUEUE AND THIS IS ONE OF THEM.
SO SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MAILMAN AND THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR MAHMUD FOR OUR HONORING OLIVIA.
I HAVE TO HAVE TO LOOK AT YOU WELL SAY NICE THINGS ABOUT YOU
FIRST ON BEHALF OF THE DISTRICT SEVEN OFFICE AND THE ENTIRETY
OF DISTRICT SEVEN THANK YOU FOR BEING THE WONDERFUL HUMAN BEING
THAT YOU ARE. ASIDE FROM ALL THE PROFESSIONAL
QUALIFICATIONS THAT SUPERVISOR MAHMUD I JUST LISTED AS A FIRST
RESPONDER SUPPORTING OUR FIRE DEPARTMENT AND NOW OFFICE OF
EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT YOU'RE ALWAYS ON TOP OF IT.
YOU'RE A FANTASTIC COMMUNICATOR .
SURE YOU KNOW EXACTLY WHAT TO SAY, WHEN TO SAY IT, WHEN TO
COMMUNICATE WHAT INFORMATION TO CONVEY.
ALL OF THOSE THINGS ARE TRUE. YOU'RE SO COMPETENT.
>> BUT IN ADDITION TO ALL OF THAT YOU ARE A WARM, WONDERFUL
OUTSTANDING HUMAN BEING AND I AM SO GRATEFUL TO ALSO BE YOUR
FRIEND. YOU HAVE ADDED SO MUCH TO ALL
OF OUR LIVES PROFESSIONALLY BUT ALSO AS A HUMAN.
YOU ARE OUTSTANDING AS A MOM WHENEVER I SEE YOU OUT IN THE
WILD I'M ALWAYS SO THRILLED THAT YOU ALWAYS HAVE KIDS
IN TOW AND YOU ARE SO CONNECTED TO THE COMMUNITY THE IMMIGRANT
COMMUNITY, IRISH COMMUNITY AND THE DISTRICT SEVEN
COMMUNITY. SO THANK YOU FOR THIS
RECOGNITION OF OUR FRIEND OLIVIA.
SHE IS AMAZING AND IT IS WELL WELL DESERVED SUPERVISOR SÖDER
THANK YOU PRESIDENT AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MAHMUD FOR
SHARING THIS HONOR WITH OLIVIA. OLIVIA IT'S BEEN A PLEASURE TO
WORK WITH YOU AND IN THIS FIRST PAST YEAR IT'S BEEN A BUSY
ACTIVE YEAR. AND YOU KNOW, I THINK PROBABLY
THE PUBLIC KNOWS OF THE DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY
MANAGEMENT AROUND SOME OF THOSE HIGH INCIDENTS OR HIGH PROFILE
INCIDENTS. BUT THERE'S SO MANY OTHERS THAT
THANKFULLY NEVER REACH THE PUBLIC'S AWARENESS BECAUSE
PRECISELY BECAUSE OF THE WORK THAT YOU DO AND YOUR DEPARTMENT
DOES IN PREPARING AND THERE ARE ALSO SO MANY MOMENTS WHERE WE
ARE INUNDATED BY CONCERNS AND QUESTIONS AND REQUESTS FROM
OUR RESIDENTS AND OUR CONSTITUENTS.
AND SURPRISE, SURPRISE, SOMETIMES WE DON'T KNOW THOSE
ANSWERS AND IT'S USUALLY YOU WHO WE TURN TO AND YOU'RE
ALWAYS TIMELY AND RESPONSIVE AND COMPREHENSIVE WITH YOUR
ANSWERS AND YOUR SUPPORT. SO THANK YOU AND I HOPE WE
DON'T HAVE TO LEAN ON YOU TOO MUCH THIS YEAR BUT AS IT GOES
WE PROBABLY WILL. SO THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY
I THINK EVERYTHING THAT I WOULD SAY IS BEEN REPEATED AND WILL
BE REPEATED BY OTHERS BUT I JUST KNOW HOW MUCH THAT I
AND MY STAFF APPRECIATE YOU ESPECIALLY WHEN IT COMES TO
EVENTS OR EMERGENCIES THAT ARE PLAYING OUT AND JUST HAVING A
SENSE OF BEING ABLE TO HAVE OUR FINGER ON THE PULSE OF THINGS
THAT ARE PLAYING OUT FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY
MANAGEMENT YOU'RE THAT CONNECTION TO US AND IT HELPS
US DO A BETTER JOB. SO I APPRECIATE YOU.
I APPRECIATE MARY ELLEN CAROL AND THE ENTIRE STAFF OF TEAM
BUT THANK YOU SO MUCH. >> SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU
OLIVIA I JUST WANT TO SAY THANK YOU EVEN THOUGH I ALWAYS WHEN I
SEE YOU ON MY PHONE I'M LIKE OH WHAT HAPPENED OR WHAT IS
HAPPENING? I KNOW THAT IT'S NEVER GOOD
NEWS BUT YOU DELIVER BAD NEWS VERY WELL AND SO WE APPRECIATE
YOU. I APPRECIATE YOU AND OUR
CONSTITUENTS ALSO APPRECIATE YOU BECAUSE OF YOU THAT WE GET
TO BE ABLE TO COMMUNICATE IN REAL TIME AND IT IS AMAZING
YOU ARE AN AMAZING LIKE NOT JUST A CITY LIKE PUBLIC
SERVANTS AND BUT ALSO A MOM AND AND JUST THANK YOU YOU ALSO
BEEN A GREAT COLLEAGUE TO ME ON A BOTH PROFESSIONAL
AND PERSONAL LEVEL SO FOR THAT I REALLY AM GRATEFUL.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU FOR DOING THIS
PRESENT AMENDMENT. >> I AM NOT GOING TO BE LONG.
>> I DEFINITELY WANT TO ECHO THE COMMENTS OF MY COLLEAGUES
BUT I ALSO JUST WANT TO SAY THANK YOU FOR WORKING WHEN
EVERYBODY ELSE IS NOT. AS YOU KNOW WE HAD A LOT OF
STORMS AND A LOT OF BAD WEATHER OVER THE HOLIDAYS AND YOU KEPT
EVERYBODY INFORMED OF WHAT WAS GOING ON AND I KNOW IT HAD TO
TAKE TIME AWAY FROM FAMILY AND YOUR COMMITMENT TO THIS
CITY IS EVIDENT AND I JUST WANT TO SAY THANK YOU SUPERVISOR
CHEN I ALSO DON'T WANT TO BE ALONE BUT I ECHO EVERYTHING
EVERYONE EVERYONE'S SHARE AND I ALSO APPRECIATE THE ATTENTION
BECAUSE OF OVER THE HOLIDAY THAT WAS A STORM THAT WAS
FLOODING POTENTIALLY IN MY NEIGHBORHOOD.
SO I WANT TO THANK EVERYTHING THAT YOU AND YOUR DEPARTMENT
HAS DONE AND KEEP DOING. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THE
WAY. THANK YOU FOR MYSELF.
>> I WILL I WILL ADD I THINK IT IS NOTE NOTABLE THAT
SUPERVISORS WHO MAY NOT ALWAYS AGREE ABOUT EVERYTHING AGREE
ABOUT THE EXCELLENCE OF THE DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY
MANAGEMENT AND ABOUT THE ELECT THE EXCELLENCE OF OLIVIA
SCANLON. I HEARD AT LEAST ONE OF MY
COLLEAGUES WHEN THEY SAW THIS COMMENDATION POPPING UP ON ON
OUR AGENDA EXPRESSING ANXIETY THAT YOU MIGHT BE RETIRING
AND THAT'S NOT ALLOWED. SO THAT THAT WOULD BE AN
UNACCEPTABLE ANNOUNCEMENT AND WE WOULD NOT BE HAPPY.
YOUR DEPARTMENT IS A LITTLE BIT LIKE I THINK I MAY HAVE SAID
THIS BEFORE A LITTLE BIT LIKE A SWISS ARMY KNIFE FOR SAN
FRANCISCO. WE TEND TO MAKE YOU RESPOND TO
ALL OF THE CITY'S MOST PRESSING CHALLENGES AND YOU ARE A LITTLE
BIT THE SWISS ARMY KNIFE OF CITY HALL STAFFERS WHO HAVE
COME INTO SO MANY DIFFERENT PRETTY TOUGH JOBS AND DONE THEM
ALL EXTRAORDINARILY. I PERSONALLY ENJOY YOU.
YOU HAVE BEEN A YOU'VE INTRODUCED ME TO SO MANY PARTS
OF MY OWN DISTRICT. YOUR CONNECTIONS IN THE CITY
ARE SO DEEP. BUT IF YOU'RE ALSO JUST A
TREMENDOUS RESOURCE TO EVERYBODY ON THIS BOARD AND THE
THE CLEAR AND REGULAR COMMUNICATION THAT YOU PROVIDE
TO US ABOUT WHAT IS GOING ON AND WHAT WE NEED TO KNOW HELPS
US ALL DO OUR JOB BETTER. SO THANK YOU OLIVIA AND THANK
YOU SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD FOR FOR RECOGNIZING THIS EXTRAORDINARY
PUBLIC SERVANT AND THE QUEUE IS UP SO IT'S YOUR TURN.
OLIVIA SCANLON OR MARY ELLEN CARROLL ACTUALLY THE DIRECTOR
OF THE DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT GETS TO GO FIRST.
>> COME ON. MUCH TO HER DISMAY, I HAVE
SOMETHING TO SAY. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
I THINK IT SAYS SOMETHING EVERY TIME YOU HONOR SOMEONE IN OUR
DEPARTMENT THEY ARE SO UNCOMFORTABLE AND BECAUSE
THEY'RE UNCOMFORTABLE I THINK WITH JUST THE ATTENTION AND ARE
VERY MUCH BEHIND THE SCENES FOLKS YOU KNOW OLIVIA IS MY
RIGHT HAND WOMAN. SHE HAS AN AND WITH EVERYTHING
THAT WE DO I COULD NOT DO THE JOB I DO WITHOUT THE PEOPLE
THAT WORK WITH ME EVERY DAY AND OLIVIA IS ONE OF THOSE MOST
IMPORTANT PEOPLE. YOU KNOW OLIVIA SOMETIMES AS I
HAVE BEEN WITH THE CITY OVER 20 YEARS AS HAS OLIVIA YOU DON'T
ALWAYS END UP IN PLACES THAT APPRECIATE YOU IN THE WAY THAT
YOU DESERVE TO BE. AND I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT
EVERY DAY. I APPRECIATE THAT OLIVIA IS
HERE, THAT SHE'S SUPPORTING ME, OUR DEPARTMENT AND REALLY THE
ENTIRE CITY AND OF COURSE ALL OF YOU WHICH I THINK IS WHY YOU
ASKED HER TO BE HERE BEING A WOMAN IN LEADERSHIP, BEING A
WOMAN IN THIS CITY IS NOT ALWAYS EASY.
BEING A MOTHER I AM MY KIDS HAVE FLOWN THE COOP SO MY LIFE
FEELS A LOT EASIER. BUT QIFA AND ANDREW ARE HERE.
I THINK KILLIAN IS AT SCHOOL. ABSOLUTELY THERE IS A SACRIFICE
TO FAMILY AND I KNOW THESE TWO KIDS FEEL IT OVER THE HOLIDAYS.
INDEED WE ALL WORKED FROM SATURDAY BEFORE CHRISTMAS
THROUGH CHRISTMAS DAY SO THAT WAS TOOK AWAY ALL THE
PREPARATIONS THAT ONE HAS TO DO THE SHOPPING THE HOLIDAY SHE
SHE WAS WORKING BECAUSE SHE WAS WORKING WITH ME AND THAT'S THE
KIND OF SACRIFICE THAT THESE JOBS TAKE.
SO I AM VERY GRATEFUL THAT YOU HAVE ASKED THAT YOU'VE BROUGHT
HER IN HERE. SHE IS NOT THRILLED ABOUT IT.
>> I MEAN I'M SURE SHE APPRECIATES THAT THIS IS A
DEEPLY UNCOMFORTABLE FOR HER. >> BUT I JUST WANTED TO SAY
THAT ANY TIME THAT WE HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO HONOR ANYONE
IN THE CITY ESPECIALLY WOMEN WHO HAVE DEDICATED THEIR LIVES
AND MAKE THE SACRIFICE THAT THEY DO EVERY DAY TO SERVE THE
CITY AND IT IS WORTH UNDERSCORING.
AND SO I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU APPRECIATION TO ALL OF THE
WORKING MOMS OUT THERE AND ESPECIALLY WOMEN IN PUBLIC
SAFETY. IT'S A KIND OF UNIQUE LITTLE
PLACE THAT SPACE THAT WE INHABIT AND IT'S NOT ALWAYS
EASY. SO I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU
AND I WANT TO THANK YOU OLIVIA AND I WANT TO THANK YOU ANDREW
AND KIEFER AND ALSO KILIAN FOR THE SACRIFICE.
I AM SO GRATEFUL FOR YOU TO BE WHERE YOU ARE WITH US AT THE
THANKS SUPERVISOR MAHMUD AS PRESIDENT MANDOLIN
AND SUPERVISORS I AM MORTIFIED THIS MY COMFORT ZONE.
>> ANYBODY THAT KNOWS ME KNOWS I LIKE BEING BEHIND THE SCENES.
I LIKE DOING THE WORK. I LIKE BEING A STAFFER.
>> THAT'S WHO I AM AND THANK YOU MARY ELLEN AND I WALKED
INTO THIS BUILDING 23 YEARS AGO AND I'M AN IMMIGRANT AND I
DIDN'T KNOW A LOT ABOUT WHAT WAS GOING ON.
I LOOK AT ANGELA THERE BECAUSE SHE WAS A FELLOW AIDE AND I
JUST PUT MY HEAD DOWN AND I ASKED QUESTIONS AND I LEARNED
EVERY DAY AND I STILL DO THAT TODAY AND IT'S A PRIVILEGE TO
BE A PUBLIC SERVANT. I LOVE SOLVING PROBLEMS.
I LOVE RESPONDING. I LOVE HELPING PEOPLE.
IT'S WHAT I GET JOY FROM MY CHILDREN HAVE GROWN UP IN THIS
BUILDING PRETTY MUCH AND I DRIVE AROUND DISTRICT SEVEN
SPECIFICALLY AND I SHOW THEM PROJECTS THAT I WORKED ON
AND I'M VERY PROUD OF THAT STILL AND I HOPE THAT IT
INSTILLED IN THEM A SENSE OF GIVING BACK AND PUBLIC SERVICE
DREAM HAS BEEN JUST A PRIVILEGE TO WORK IN THE LAST FEW YEARS
AND I FEEL LIKE I REALLY, REALLY FOUND MY HOME.
THERE WERE A SMALL BUT MIGHTY TEAM AND UNDER THE DIRECTION OF
MARY ELLEN I JUST FEEL SO BLESSED TO HAVE HER AS SOMEBODY
THAT I LOOK UP TO AND I LEARN FROM EVERY DAY AS WELL.
AND I JUST WANT YOU TO KNOW I'M STILL HERE.
I'M NOT GOING ANYWHERE AND I FEEL LIKE I'M STILL YOUNG
ENOUGH THAT I'VE GOT A FEW YEARS LEFT IN ME YET BUT I WILL
ALWAYS BE HERE FROM EACH AND EVERY ONE OF YOU AND YOUR
STAFF AND ONCE AN AIDE, ALWAYS AN AIDE I SAY THAT TO ALL THE
AIDES AND YOU'RE NEVER TOO SEASONED TO ASK QUESTIONS
AND BE CURIOUS. SO THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THIS.
IT MEANS AN AWFUL LOT TO ME AND TO THE DEPARTMENT.
>> SO THANK YOU. YEAH, JUST RIGHT AND WE WILL
CONCLUDE WITH DISTRICT EIGHT'S MOSES CORRECT WHERE IS MOSES?
>> COME ON UP. >> COLLEAGUES MOSES CARETTE
RETIRED EARLIER THIS MONTH AFTER 26 YEARS OF SERVICE AS AN
EMPLOYEE OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PLANNING DEPARTMENT AND THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS, HE EARNED HIS BACHELOR'S DEGREE IN ART
HISTORY AND PHILOSOPHY AT THE UNIVERSITY OF VERMONT AND LATER
EARNED HIS MASTER'S DEGREE IN HISTORIC PRESERVATION AT THE
UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA. MOSES JOINED THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT IN 1999 AS AN INTERN FOR ONE OF THE FIRST PROJECTS
WITH WHICH HE WAS TASKED WAS THE DESIGN OF A SURVEY OF
BUILDINGS TO DETERMINE WHICH ARE HISTORIC AND WHICH ARE NOT
. IN 2000 HE WAS BROUGHT ON FULL
TIME AS A PRESERVATION PLANNER. MOSES PARTICIPATED IN THE
DEVELOPMENT OF PRESERVATION SURVEYS AND POLICIES FOR AREA
PLANS INCLUDING MARKET AND OCTAVIA CENTRAL WATERFRONT
EASTERN SOMA AND SHOWPLACE SQUARE.
>> HE AUTHORED SEVERAL LANDMARK REPORTS ON BUILDINGS INCLUDING
THE JAMES LICK BATHS AND PEOPLE'S LAUNDRY BUILDING
ON 10TH STREET. BUT HIS MAIN FOCUS HAS BEEN ON
THE DOCUMENTATION OF SAN FRANCISCO'S HISTORY.
HE AUTHORED LANDMARK DESIGNATION LEGISLATION FOR THE
TWIN PEAKS TAVERN, THE FIRST LGBTQ BAR WITH WINDOWS OPEN TO
THE STREETS FOR WHICH HE WON A COVETED COVETED GOVERNOR'S
AWARD IN HISTORIC PRESERVATION AS WELL AS SPECIAL RECOGNITION
BY THE NATIONAL TRUST FOR HISTORIC PRESERVATION.
HE RESEARCHED AND PREPARED THE DOCUMENTATION FOR THE
LANDMARKING OF THE SITE OF THE COMPTON'S CAFETERIA A RIOT OF
1966 AND GILBERT BAKER'S RAINBOW FLAG INSTALLATION AT
HARVEY MILK PLAZA. HIS LAST LANDMARK DESIGNATION
WAS THE MINT MINT MALL AND HALL BUILDING A COLLABORATION WITH
SELMA PILIPINAS MOSES HAS DOCUMENTED HISTORIC DISTRICTS
IN THE GLEN IN LOW SORRY IT'S MY OWN DISTRICT.
MOSES HAS DOCUMENTED HISTORIC DISTRICTS IN GLENN PARK AND THE
CASTRO. AND UP UNTIL LAST MONTH HE WAS
CONTINUING HIS WORK ON S.F. SURVEY EVALUATIONS ALONG
LOMBARD STREET IN THE MARINA OVER THE YEARS TENS OF
THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE HAVE VISITED MOSES AT THE PLANNING
PERMIT COUNTER SEEKING HIS HELP WITH APPROVALS FOR THEIR
PROJECTS. IN ALL, HE'S REVIEWED MORE THAN
10,000 APPLICATIONS WITH AN AGGREGATED ESTIMATED PERMIT
VALUE OF MORE THAN 800 AND $55 MILLION FOR SIX MONTHS IN 2018
MOSES STEPPED IN AS A LEGISLATIVE AIDE TO FORMER
SUPERVISOR JANE KIM IN HER OFFICE.
HE WORKED ON THE CENTRAL SELMA AREA PLAN ADVISED ON SIX
APPEALS, HOUSING AND LABOR ISSUES AND WORKED CLOSELY WITH
THE COMPTON'S TRANSGENDER TRANSGENDER CULTURAL DISTRICT.
NOW THE TRANSGENDER DISTRICT, SELMA PILIPINAS CULTURAL
DISTRICT AND LEATHER AND LGBTQ PLUS CULTURAL DISTRICT.
>> BEYOND HIS PROFESSIONAL RESPONSIBILITIES, MOSES HAS
BEEN HEAVILY INVOLVED IN THE LABOR MOVEMENT GOING BACK AS
FAR AS 1997 WHEN HE JOINED JOBS WITH JUSTICE AS A STEERING
COMMITTEE MEMBER. HE SERVED ON IFP TO LOCAL 20
ONE'S POLITICAL ACTION COMMITTEE BEFORE BECOMING
TREASURER OF THE ORGANIZATION AND HE REORGANIZED THE UNIONS
BUDGET WHICH ALLOWED THEM TO PURCHASE THEIR OWN HEADQUARTERS
AND HE SAT ON SEVERAL BARGAINING COMMITTEES TO
NEGOTIATE LABOR CONTRACTS BETWEEN THE CITY AND THE UNION.
MOSES HAS BEEN A DELEGATE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO LABOR COUNCIL
FOR MORE THAN A DECADE, INCLUDING HIS TIME SERVING ON
THEIR PUBLIC EMPLOYEE COMMITTEE .
HE ALSO SERVED TWO TERMS ON THE OCI OVERSIGHT BOARD.
>> THANK YOU MOSES FOR YOUR DECADES OF SERVICE TO THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. AND AGAIN WE HAVE SOME OF MY
COLLEAGUES WHO WANT TO ADD ON SO I WILL INVITE SUPERVISOR
MELGAR TO SPEAK. >> THANK YOU PRESIDENT
RANDLEMAN AT MOSES. I'M GOING TO MISS YOU IN THE
MIX HERE. SO I HAVE HAD THE PLEASURE
AND HONOR OF WATCHING YOUR CAREER FROM THE TIME THAT YOU
KNOW I WAS ON THE PLANNING COMMISSION WHEN YOU ALSO DID
YOUR STINT IN THEN SUPERVISOR KIM'S OFFICE AND YOUR WORK
IN THE CENTRAL SOMA PLAN AND YOUR YOUR AMAZING WISDOM
AND VAST KNOWLEDGE ABOUT THE CODE BUT ALSO LIKE YOUR HUMAN
DECENCY AND DEALING WITH PEOPLE AT THE COUNTER WHO SOMETIMES
DIDN'T QUITE GET IT WHY WE HAD TO INTERPRET THINGS A CERTAIN
WAY AND IT IS WHAT IT IS. AND SO I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU
FOR YOUR LONG LEADERSHIP AT BOTH IN TERMS OF PLANNING BUT
ALSO IN OUR CITY AND OUR POLITICAL LIFE AND THE
LEADERSHIP THAT YOU HAVE EXHIBITED IN ALL AREAS.
SO I'M GOING TO MISS YOU AND THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING
YOU'VE DONE FOR OUR CITY SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MANDELA AND MOSES, I JUST WANTED TO CONGRATULATE YOU
ON A WELL-DESERVED RETIREMENT AFTER A LONG CAREER IN THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT YOU'VE BEEN A PART OF PRESERVING SOME OF
OUR CITY'S MOST BELOVED HISTORIC RESOURCES AS PRESIDENT
MANDELA MENTIONED. AND YOU STILL HAVE A LOT OF
FANS IN THE DISTRICT SIX OFFICE, MYSELF INCLUDED AS
PRESIDENT MANDELA MENTIONED, THE MINT MALL WAS AMONG YOUR
FINAL PROJECTS AND I WILL JUST SAY THAT THAT IS A BELOVED
CULTURAL HOME FOR OUR FILIPINO COMMUNITY.
IT'S ALSO IMPORTANT TO ME AS A AS A NEIGHBOR AND A PLACE WHERE
I GO FOR LUNCH AND GET MY HAIRCUT AND THAT KIND OF THING
AND IT'S IMPORTANT TO THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
I JUST APPRECIATE YOUR WORK ON THAT AND EVERYTHING THAT YOU
HAVE DONE FOR OUR CITY. SO THANK MOSES CARETTE THE
FLOOR IS YOURS. I HAVE COME TO REALIZE AND I'M
GLAD I'M REMEMBERING THIS THAT THESE COMMENDATIONS ARE
ESSENTIALLY LIFETIME ACHIEVEMENT AWARDS FOR CIVIL
SERVANTS AND I APPRECIATE THAT SO MUCH THAT THESE HAPPEN THAT
WE GET RECOGNIZED. I WOULD LIKE TO ALSO THANK THE
OTHER PEOPLE WHO WERE RECOGNIZED EARLIER TODAY
AND THE PEOPLE WHO WILL BE COMING AFTER IT HAS BEEN AN
HONOR AND A PLEASURE TO SERVE THE THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO
FOR MORE THAN A QUARTER OF A CENTURY.
THIS HAS BEEN MY MY ONLY JOB IN MY CAREER AND I AM PROUD
THAT I WAS ABLE TO ACCOMPLISHED SO MUCH AND TO LEAVE AT A TIME
WHEN I HAVE FOUND SUCCESSORS WHO ARE ALSO DOING GOOD THINGS
AND BOTH ON THE LABOR SIDE AND ON THE DEPARTMENT SIDE
TEACHING THE CODE IS NOT EASY BUT MENTORING A CIVIL SERVANT
WHO MIGHT OTHERWISE BE A BUREAUCRAT IS IS KEY AND TO
ALWAYS KEEP IN MIND THAT CEMETERIES ARE FULL OF
INDISPENSABLE PEOPLE. SO SPREAD YOUR KNOWLEDGE
AND LIVE AN HONORABLE LIFE. THANK YOU
. ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, LET'S
GO TO OUR FIRST 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER PLEASE CALL ITEMS 20
THROUGH 23 TOGETHER ITEMS 20 THROUGH 23 COMPRISE THE PUBLIC
HEARING OF PERSONS INTERESTED IN THE STATUTORY EXEMPTION
UNDER THE CALIFORNIA ENVIRONMENTAL QUALITY ACT
ISSUED BY THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT ON OCTOBER 31ST,
2025 FOR THE PROPOSED PROJECT TO DISSEMBLE AND REMOVE ARMAAN
VALEN COURTS EMBARCADERO FOUNTAIN TWO STORAGE LOCATED ON
ASSESSOR'S PARCEL BLOCK NUMBER ZERO 233 LOT NUMBER 035
PROPOSED BY THE SAN FRANCISCO RECREATION AND PARK DEPARTMENT
TO ADDRESS SIGNIFICANT PUBLIC SAFETY HAZARD AT EMBARCADERO
PLAZA. ITEM 21 THIS MOTION AFFIRMS THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S DETERMINATION THAT THE PROPOSED
PROJECT IS NATURAL STATUTORY STATUTORY EXEMPT FROM
ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW ITEM 22 THIS MOTION CONDITIONALLY
REVERSES THE DETERMINATION THAT THE PROPOSED PROJECT IS
STATUTORILY EXEMPT FROM ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW SUBJECT TO
THE ADOPTION OF WRITTEN FINDINGS BY THE BOARD
IN SUPPORT OF THE DETERMINATION AND ITEM 23 IS THE MOTION TO
DIRECT THE PREPARATION OF FINDINGS.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES, WE HAVE BEFORE US
ON APPEAL OF THE DETERMINATION OF EXEMPTION FROM ENVIRONMENTAL
REVIEW FOR VAILLANCOURT FOUNTAIN.
AFTER THE HEARING THE BOARD WILL VOTE ON WHETHER TO AFFIRM
OR CONDITIONALLY REVERSE THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S
DETERMINATION. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION.
I WOULD PROPOSE WE PROCEED AS FOLLOWS WITH UP TO TEN MINUTES
FOR THE APPELLANTS THEN WE'LL HAVE PUBLIC COMMENT IN SUPPORT
OF THE APPEAL TWO MINUTES PER SPEAKER.
THEN WE'LL HAVE A PRESENTATION OF UP TO TEN MINUTES FROM THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT. THEN WE WILL GIVE THE PROJECT
SPONSOR UP TO TEN MINUTES. AT THAT POINT WE WILL TAKE
PUBLIC COMMENT FROM AN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL.
AGAIN, TWO MINUTES PER SPEAKER. AND THEN FINALLY WE'LL GIVE THE
APPELLANTS THREE MINUTES FOR REBUTTAL.
DOES ANYONE OBJECT TO GOING FORWARD IN THAT WAY?
THEN SEEING NO OBJECTIONS, THE PUBLIC HEARING WILL PROCEED AS
INDICATED AND IS NOW OPEN. >> AND WITH THAT I WOULD ASK
THE APPELLANT TO COME FORWARD AND PRESENT THEIR CASE AND THEN
I HAVE SOME SLIDES I DON'T KNOW WHERE WE CAN PRESENT THOSE.
>> I'M SORRY CAN YOU SEE SLIDES TO PRESENT AS WELL?
>> OKAY. >> I'M JUST WONDERING HOW WE
SHOULD PROCEED. HAVE YOU PROVIDED THOSE SLIDES
TO THE CLERK'S OFFICE IN ADVANCE?
OKAY, GREAT. GREAT.
>> AND MAYBE RESET THAT CLOCK TO TEN I BELIEVE YOU WERE
DIRECTED TO HAVE THEM ON A USB SO THAT YOU CAN PLUG IT RIGHT
INTO THE LAPTOP RIGHT TO YOUR LEFT.
PERFECT. I CAN DO THAT.
YOU'RE WELCOME. I HAVE
LET US KNOW WHEN YOU'RE READY TO GO AND WE'LL SET THE TIME.
ALL RIGHT. I'M READY.
GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS JACK MCCARTHY
AND I'M JOINED BY SUSAN BRANT HOLLEY REPRESENTING DOCOMO,
NORTHERN CALIFORNIA IN SUPPORT OF THIS APPEAL.
DOCOMO MONACA IS A NONPROFIT ADVOCACY AND EDUCATION GROUP
DEDICATED TO MODERN DESIGN THAT HAS BEEN ACTIVE IN SAN
FRANCISCO FOR 30 YEARS. WE REPRESENT A BROAD COALITION
OF STAKEHOLDERS THAT INCLUDE STATE NATIONAL
AND INTERNATIONAL GROUPS SHOWN HERE IN ADDITION TO THE FAMILY
OF LAWRENCE HALPRIN AND THE FOUNDERS CREATOR ARMAND VINH
CORE AND HIS FAMILY. OPENED IN 1971.
THE VINE CORE FOUNTAIN IS THE CENTERPIECE OF RENOWNED
LANDSCAPE ARCHITECT LAWRENCE HALPERN'S EMBARCADERO PLAZA.
>> FOR OVER 50 YEARS THE PLAZA AND FOUNTAIN HAVE SERVED AS ONE
OF THE CITY'S MOST SIGNIFICANT GATHERING SPACES.
IT IS AN ICON OF PUBLIC ASSEMBLY, FREE SPEECH
AND ARTISTIC EXPRESSION. THIS SINGLE PIECE OF ART IS AN
INTERNATIONALLY KNOWN HISTORIC RESOURCE.
NO ONE DISPUTES THAT FACT. THE MATTER TODAY IS WHETHER THE
CITY CAN BYPASS SECURE UNDER THE PREMISE OF AN EMERGENCY.
THE EVIDENCE SHOWS NO EMERGENCY ONLY THAT THE FOUNDERS
CONDITION IS A PREDICTABLE RESULT OF THE CITY'S OWN LONG
TERM DEFERRED MAINTENANCE. WE ASK YOU TO OVERTURN THE
DECISION TO REMOVE THE VINE COURT FOUNTAIN.
INSTEAD REQUIRE CITY STAFF TO ENGAGE IN THE FULL PUBLIC
PROCESS MANDATED BY SEQUOIA THAT THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE WHO
VALUE THIS SPACE FOR ITS HISTORY OF PROTEST, ART
AND RECREATION DESERVE A GOOD FAITH CONVERSATION.
BEFORE THIS HISTORIC RESOURCE IS LOST.
>> THANK YOU, JACK. >> HELLO.
I'M NOT SURE HOW TO WORK THIS THOUGH.
ONE MOMENT. SURE.
>> SHE HAD TO GO TO THE NEXT SLIDE.
OKAY. HELLO, I'M SUSAN BRANDT HOLLEY
AND I'M A LAWYER WHO DOES? PEOPLE WE'RE PROTECTING
HISTORIC RESOURCES AROUND THE STATE.
PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
I'M HERE TO URGE YOU TO SET ASIDE THE OF THE STATUTORY
EMERGENCY EXEMPTION IN THIS CASE SECRET FROM THE IT'S
ADOPTION IN 1970 HAS PROTECTED HISTORIC RESOURCES OF THE BUILT
ENVIRONMENT TO THE SAME LEVEL AS NATURAL RESOURCES THAT WE'RE
USED TO TALKING ABOUT AND SO THE STATUTORY EXEMPTION BEFORE
YOU IS TO BE VERY NARROWLY CONSTRUED BECAUSE SECRET IS THE
WAY TO INVOLVE THE PUBLIC IN LOOKING AT ALTERNATIVES
AND WAYS TO AVOID SIGNIFICANT IMPACTS TO HISTORIC RESOURCES.
THIS BOARD IS THAT WELL THE CITY IS THE TRUSTEE OF ITS
HISTORIC RESOURCES AND HERE THE VAILLANCOURT FOUNTAIN IS A
HISTORIC RESOURCE. AS THE SLIDE SAID, THE ISSUE
BEFORE YOU IS NOT POLITICAL. WE UNDERSTAND THAT THE BOARD
OVER THE YEARS HAS STRONG FEELINGS ABOUT THE FOUNTAIN
AND WHAT SHOULD HAPPEN NEXT. BUT THAT'S NOT BEFORE YOU TODAY
IT'S NOT THE TIME TO FIGURE OUT WHAT HAPPENS TO THE FOUNTAIN.
THE ONLY ISSUE IS RELATING TO THE RELOCATION OF THE OF THE
FOUNTAIN AT THIS TIME THE WHILE THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT HAS
FRAMED THIS AS A SEPARATE PROJECT, IT IS NOT IN SECRET
PARLANCE WHEN YOU HAVE ELEMENTS OF A PROJECT AND HERE IT'S THE
RENOVATION OF EMBARCADERO PLAZA AND THE SUE BEERMAN PARK THE
FOUNTAIN SMACK IN THE MIDDLE AS YOU ALL KNOW.
AND WHAT HAPPENS TO THE FOUNTAIN HAS A GREAT IMPACT ON
WHAT YOU'RE GOING TO DO WITH THIS RENOVATION PROJECT
AND SECRET DOES NOT ALLOW SEGMENTATION OF PARTS OF A
PROJECT INTO LITTLE PIECES TO MAKE EACH PIECE POSSIBLY SEEM
NOT IMPORTANT. SO HERE YOU CAN SEE IN THE 2024
PLAN AND THE 2025 PLAN THAT THE OBVIOUSLY THE FOUNTAIN IS
IN THE MIDDLE OF IT AND THE RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT
HAS PROPOSED REMOVAL OF THE FOUNTAIN AS PART OF THE
EMBARCADERO PLAZA PROJECT. >> ALL OF THE INFORMATION ON
THE SLIDES ALSO WILL BE BEFORE YOU.
IT ALREADY IS IN THE RECORD IN IN PACKAGE THAT THAT HAVE
BEEN SUBMITTED. SO THE REVIEW SCOPE SAYS THAT
REMOVAL OF THE FOUNTAIN IS PART OF THE PROJECT AND PROJECT
MATERIALS WERE PROVIDED BY STAFF IN THE PROJECT MATERIALS
IT'S SURELY WE SHOULD BE VERY STRAIGHTFORWARD ABOUT WHAT'S
HAPPENING HERE AND FOR THE CITY TO HAVE A PRETEXT TO FIND A WAY
TO REMOVE THE FOUNTAIN FROM THE PLAZA IN ORDER TO MAKE THE
PROJECT LESS COMPLEX AS A PART OF A SEQUEL REVIEW THAT IS
DISALLOWED BY LAW. WHAT'S IN HAND-IN-HAND WITH THE
PROBLEM WITH THIS EXEMPTION IS THE CITY'S PRE COMMITMENT TO
THIS PROJECT BY ITS ACTIONS. I REPRESENTED A GROUP INVOLVING
THE GEORGE WASHINGTON HIGH SCHOOL MURALS A FEW YEARS BACK
AGAINST THE CITY SUCCESSFULLY WHERE WITHOUT A FORMAL APPROVAL
THEY TOOK ACTIONS THAT CLEARLY SHOWED A PRE COMMITMENT TO THE
PROJECT WITHOUT DOING ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW TO LOOK AT
IT TO ANALYZE IMPACTS, LOOK AT ALTERNATIVES AND LOOK AT
MITIGATION. WE HAVE A LOT OF PROJECT
COMMENTERS AND INCLUDING THE PROJECT'S SPONSORS ADMITTING
REMOVAL AS PART OF THE PROJECT SUPERVISOR SAUTER HAS EXPLAINED
THAT HE DOESN'T SEE A PATH TO KEEPING THE FOUNTAIN AND WHILE
AGAIN WHILE THERE MAY BE OPINIONS ABOUT THIS IT'S TOO
EARLY TO ACTUALLY MOVE FORWARD IN A WAY THAT DOESN'T ALLOW
FAIR CONSIDERATION OF ALTERNATIVES.
>> I'M TRYING TO FIGURE OUT IF THERE'S A WAY TO SEE HOW MUCH
TIME I HAVE. IS THERE A NUMBER SOMEWHERE OR
DO I NEED THAT? WHAT?
PARDON? FOUR MINUTES LEFT.
OKAY, I'M GOING TO GO FAST THEN NONE OF THE EXPERT BEFORE YOU
REPORTS BEFORE YOU HAVE RECOMMENDED APPROVAL THERE'S A
COST ESTIMATE OF OVER 4 MILLION WITH NO FUNDING FOR REMOVAL.
THE PURPOSE IS TO EXPEDITE THE PLAZA PROJECT AND THERE ARE
WAYS TO LOOK AT ABATEMENT OF THE ANY KIND OF RISK THAT THERE
IS THAT HAS TO BUILT. THERE'S NOTHING NEW THAT'S
HAPPENED. IT'S NOT A SUDDEN EMERGENCY
AND UNEXPECTED OCCURRENCE BASICALLY IT'S JUST THE
CONTINUED FAILURE OF THE CITY TO MAINTAIN THE FOUNTAIN THAT
HAS LED TO ITS CONDITION THAT THE THE FENCING WAS UNRELATED
TO THE ANYTHING ABOUT AN EMERGENCY.
IF YOU LOOK AT THE EXPERTS YOU HAVE THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT
AND OUR OPINION THEN YOU HAVE THE ENGINEER REPORT.
THE PAGE IN TURN WILL REPORT THE DBA LETTER NONE OF THEM
RECOMMEND REMOVAL FOR ANY REASON INCLUDING AN EMERGENCY
WHILE THERE'S LEAD IN AS BEST AND STRUCTURAL ISSUES THAT THE
SAME IS TRUE OF HUNDREDS OF BUILDINGS THROUGHOUT THE CITY
AND THE CITY DOES NOT THEN REQUIRE THEIR IMMEDIATE REMOVAL
UNLESS THERE IS SOMETHING MORE SIGNIFICANT GOING ON AND THAT'S
NOT GOING ON HERE. ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW NEEDS TO
LOOK AT THE WHOLE OF THE ACTION AND THE EVIDENCE BEFORE YOU BY
REMARKS FROM STAFF AND SUPERVISORS AND THOSE
PROJECT SPONSORS ARE THAT THIS HAS BEEN PLANNED AS PART OF THE
PROJECT. >> SO WHAT NEEDS TO HAPPEN
RESPECTFULLY IS THAT THIS BOARD SET ASIDE THE STATUTORY
EXEMPTION AND PROCEED WITH SEEK REVIEW OF THE ENTIRE PROJECT
OTHERWISE IT'S IT'S A RESPECTFULLY A BLATANT
VIOLATION OF SECURE THAT DOESN'T SERVE THE PUBLIC
AND CERTAINLY IS NOT TO THE BENEFIT OF THE CITY AND ITS
HISTORIC RESOURCES. I THINK I'M PROBABLY OUT OF
TIME. I'M JUST GUESSING 45 LEFT.
>> IT'S OKAY. THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT. IF THAT IS THE CONCLUSION OF
THE APPELLANT'S PRESENTATION, WE WILL NOW OPEN UP PUBLIC
COMMENT FOR SPEAKERS IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL.
>> >> THANK YOU. >> HOW MUCH TIME IS ALLOWED?
WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES AND THERE IS A TIMER ON
THE LARGER TALLER PODIUM. OKAY.
BUT FOR EACH PRESENTER WELL I WILL TWO MINUTES BE BRIEF THE
SAN FRANCISCO BRAND IS NOT A CARNIVAL DISPLAY OF VICTORIAN
RICK GRECH ON THE FRONT OF BUILDINGS.
IT'S THE FOOTPRINT LEFT IN THE CITY IN EVERY EPOCH BY THE
PEOPLE WHO HAVE CONTRIBUTED TO IT AND THIS BOARD IS FACED WITH
THE OPPORTUNE CITY TO MATCH THE COURAGE OF ITS PREDECESSORS WHO
HAVE PRESERVED AND ADVANCED THE SAN FRANCISCO BRAND.
30 YEARS AFTER THE FIRST AUTO BUS RAN ON MUNI, THE CABLE CARS
HAD FALLEN TO WRACK AND RUIN BY NEGLECT.
BUT YOUR PREDECESSORS HAD THE COURAGE TO INVEST WHAT WAS
NECESSARY TO BRING THE CABLE CAR SYSTEM BACK AND PRESERVE IT
AS PART OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BRAND 50 YEARS AFTER THE
PAN-AMERICAN EXPOSITION, THE PALACE OF FINE ARTS HAD FALLEN
INTO DISREPAIR BECAUSE OF ITS TEMPORARY STRUCTURE.
BUT YOUR PREDECESSORS AGAIN HAD THE COURAGE TO INVEST WHAT WAS
NECESSARY TO BRING IT BACK AND PRESERVE IT AS PART OF THE
SAN FRANCISCO BRAND THIS VERY BUILDING WAS CHALLENGED 80
YEARS AFTER CONSTRUCTION BY THE LOMA PRIETA QUAKE.
BUT YOUR PREDECESSORS HAD THE COURAGE TO REBUILD IT BETTER
COMPLETE WITH EARTHQUAKE BUMPERS IN THE BASEMENT TO
MAINTAIN IT AS PART OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BRAND.
AND I ASK THAT THIS BOARD ADOPT A LONG TERM VIEW SO THAT THIS
PUBLIC PARK WILL BE AVAILABLE 30 AND 50 YEARS FROM NOW WHEN
IT IS SEEN BY FRESH EYES WHO WILL APPRECIATE THE COURAGE OF
THE SHAMELESS OF SKILLED GOVERNMENT IN PRESERVING THEIR
DEDICATION TO ART AND PUBLIC SPACES.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS,
MADAM CLERK. BEFORE I BEGIN I JUST WANT TO
BE CLEAR WE ARE AT THE POINT IN THE HEARING WHERE ANYONE
FROM THE PUBLIC CAN SPEAK IN SUPPORT.
THAT'S RIGHT. OKAY.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. VERY WELCOME.
GOOD AFTERNOON. PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT
AND SUPERVISORS OF THE BOARD. MY NAME IS KATHRYN PETRIE
AND I'M SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF SAN FRANCISCO HERITAGE.
WE ARE A 54 YEAR OLD SAN FRANCISCO BASED NONPROFIT WITH
A MISSION TO PRESERVE AND ENHANCE OUR CITY'S
ARCHITECTURAL AND CULTURAL HERITAGE.
>> WE STRONGLY SUPPORT THIS APPEAL WHILE FUNDRAISING FOR A
NEW PARK. THE RECREATION AND PARKS
DEPARTMENT AGGRESSIVELY PUSHED FOR THE REMOVAL OF THE
EMBARCADERO FOUNTAIN A YEAR AHEAD OF ANY CONDITION
ASSESSMENTS, INSPECTION OR PUBLIC PROCESS.
UNDER LAW THIS IS CONSIDERED PRE-COMMITMENT AND IT IS
ILLEGAL. >> A DECISION TO REMOVE THE
FOUNTAIN WAS MADE AND PUBLICIZED BEFORE COMMUNITY
OUTREACH MEETINGS WERE CONDUCTED AND OTHER INDEPENDENT
INPUT FINALIZED. >> LATER THE CONSULTANTS
ASSESSMENT DID NOT FIND DID NOT FIND AN IMMEDIATE OR SUDDEN
DANGER TO THE PUBLIC. >> YET ARE QUICKLY DECLARED AN
EMERGENCY AND ERECTED FENCING TO SUPPORT THAT PRETEXT.
>> ALTERNATIVES TO REMOVAL OF THE FOUNTAIN A HISTORIC WORK OF
PUBLIC ART HAVE NOT BEEN ADEQUATELY INVESTIGATED AND A
TRUE PUBLIC PROCESS EXPLORING PRESERVATION ALTERNATIVES IS
IMPERATIVE. SAN FRANCISCO HERITAGE STANDS
WITH A MAMO IN SUPPORT OF RETAINING AND CELEBRATE ING THE
VAILLANCOURT FOUNTAIN AND WE ASK YOU TO UPHOLD THIS APPEAL.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. >> THANK YOU CATHERINE PERRON
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER IN SUPPORT OF THE
APPELLANT. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS CURT GESSLER AND I LIVE ACROSS THE BAY
IN RICHMOND, CALIFORNIA. I FIRST SAW THE VAN COURT
FOUNTAIN IN 1971. IT WAS AWESOME.
THE NEXT YEAR I TRAVELED THEN SETTLED IN EUROPE FOR FIVE
YEARS SEEING MANY DIFFERENT FOUNTAINS AND MANY IN MAJOR
EUROPEAN CITIES BUT NONE WERE AS EXCITING AS THE VIENNA
COURT. HOW COULD SAN FRANCISCO ALLOW
IT TO FALL INTO SUCH DISREPAIR WHEN IT SHOULD BE A WORLD
HERITAGE SITE? IF YOU WANT TO REMOVE UGLY
PUBLIC ART PLEASE LOOK AT THE TWO SQUARE VOTE AT THE LEGION
OF HONOR PARKING LOT. HAVE YOU CONSIDERED A BALLOT
INITIATIVE? >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> NEXT SPEAKER IN SUPPORT OF
THE APPELLANT. MY NAME IS OTTO DUFFY.
>> I LIVE HERE IN THE CITY. YOU KNOW, A THOUSAND YEARS AGO
AT THE TURN OF THE LAST MILLENNIUM THERE WAS A GREAT
DEAL OF MILLENNIAL ISM. THERE WAS A BELIEF THAT THE
WORLD WAS ENDING THE SAVIOR WAS GOING TO COME AND IT CREATED A
LOT OF INSTABILITY AND IT WAS AT THAT TIME THAT THE CITIES OF
OF EUROPE THEY STARTED TO START IN ON THE GREAT THE GREAT
CATHEDRALS, THESE CATHEDRALS TO IN EXCESS OF A CENTURY TO
BUILD. AND IT STARTED TO GIVE PEOPLE A
SENSE THAT THE CULTURE WAS GOING TO BE AROUND FOR A WHILE
. AND I THINK THAT THAT'S
SOMETHING THAT'S HORRIBLY MISSING HORRIBLY MISSING IN OUR
CULTURE TODAY THAT WE SHOULD BE BUILDING FOR A HUNDRED YEARS OR
200 YEARS. AND THE MEN DID A REALLY NICE
PUBLIC COMMENT BUT HE ONLY MENTIONED 50 YEARS.
AND WE NEED TO HAVE THOSE KIND OF PROJECTS.
>> THANK YOU ORO DUFFY FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER IN SUPPORT OF THE APPELLANT PLEASE.
>> HELLO, MY NAME IS LINDSEY WHITE.
>> I'VE LIVED AND WORKED AS AN ARTIST IN SAN FRANCISCO SINCE
2005 AND FOR OVER A DECADE I SERVED AS AN ASSOCIATE
PROFESSOR AND FOR PHOTOGRAPHY DEPARTMENT CHAIR AT THE SAN
FRANCISCO ART INSTITUTE. I SUPPORT THE APPEAL FOR THE
VAILLANCOURT FOUNTAIN AS HAVE PARKS AND CITY OFFICIALS INVOKE
THE EMERGENCY EXEMPTION NOT TO MITIGATE AN IMMINENT RISK BUT
TO AVOID THE CUMBERSOME CALIFORNIA ENVIRONMENTAL
QUALITY ACT PROCESS. THIS IS A FAILURE BY OFFICIALS
TO GO THROUGH THE PROPER CHANNELS TO TAKE CARE OF A
HISTORICAL MONUMENT. DID ANY OF YOU MEET OUR MON
VALLEY COURT? THE 96 YEAR OLD ARTIST WHO CAME
TO TOWN TO SAVE HIS WORK. I DID ARTIST POUR THEIR HEART
AND VISION INTO PUBLIC SCULPTURES.
FOR WHAT? FOR THE CITY TO NEGLECT IT
AND THEN MISMANAGED THE SITUATION SO THAT THEY CAN
BUILD A PICKLEBALL COURT AND GARDENS OVER HISTORY.
THE CITY KEEPS MISSING THE MARK ON TAKING CARE OF THE ARTS
AND THIS SITUATION AS A REFLECTION OF A DEEPER PROBLEM
CITYWIDE. YOU CAN'T JUST GET RID OF A
HISTORICAL LANDMARK AN ICONIC PIECE OF ARCHITECTURE AND ART.
AS A CITY IT IS YOUR DUTY TO TAKE CARE OF OUR HISTORICAL
MONUMENTS. WE MUST TAKE PRIDE IN THE
VARIETY OF ARTISTIC APPROACHES FROM ALL DECADES.
IT MAKES THE CITY MORE WELL-ROUNDED.
I WILL SAY THAT THIS IS A SAD MOMENT FOR THE ARTS IN SAN
FRANCISCO FOR A MULTITUDE OF REASONS BUT ESPECIALLY ON A DAY
WHERE THE CITY TRIES TO PUT A POSITIVE SPIN ON THE CALIFORNIA
OF THE ARTS CLOSURE. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU LINDSEY WHITE FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER IN SUPPORT OF THE APPELLANT PLEASE ALICE ROGOFF
THE VIOLENT COURT FOUND AND WAS AN INSPIRATION FOR A FICTIONAL
STORY I WROTE ABOUT IT AND THIS IS AN EXCERPT.
IN 1971 A FOUNTAIN WAS ERECTED IN SAN FRANCISCO SO IT WAS THE
BEGINNING OF MANY NEW BUILDINGS BUT LYLE DIDN'T KNOW IT YET A
FOUNTAIN SPEAKS IN A CONSTANT TONGUE WITH ITS PEAKS
AND VALLEYS, LULLS AND STREAMS A FOUNTAIN AS ETERNAL AN
ARCHITECT NATURE AND AS AN IDEA.
AND SO HE WALKED BACK HOME FROM THE VALLEY AND CAUSED FOUNTAIN
CORAL WORKED AS A TEMPORARY DOWNTOWN.
LYLE INTRODUCED HER TO THE VAILLANCOURT FOUNTAIN MANY
PEOPLE DISLIKED AND WANTED TO TEAR IT DOWN BUT IT BECAME HER
RIVER, HER STREAM, HER BROOK IN THE CITY.
SHE ALWAYS LIKED IT. I WOULD LIKE TO KEEP THE
VAILLANCOURT FOUNTAIN. THANK YOU ALICE RUDOLF FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
IN SUPPORT OF THE APPELLANT SUPERVISOR WAS MY NAME IS
ROBERT HERMAN I'VE BEEN AN ARCHITECT PRACTICE THING HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR OVER 60 YEARS.
>> I BEG YOU FOR A FEW EXTRA SECONDS NEARLY 92 I DON'T KNOW
HOW LONG I'M GOING TO BE HERE. >> I WITNESSED THE DEDICATION
OF ALMOND VINE COURTS FOUNTAIN BACK IN 1972.
IT INSTILLED PRIDE THE PRIDE OF BELONGING TO A TOWN PROGRESS OF
ENOUGH TO CHOOSE A UNIQUE INTERNATIONAL DESIGN
COMPETITION WINNER AT ITS UNVEILING, THOMAS HOVING,
DIRECTOR OF NEW YORK'S METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART
DELIVERED THE KEYNOTE ADDRESS PRAISING SAN FRANCISCO FOR ITS
BROAD MINDED CULTURAL ARTS PROGRAM.
>> HOVING LOOKED AND COULD SEE BEYOND THE FOUNTAIN'S
PROVOCATIVE SHAPE. HE SAW IT AS A REFERENCE TO SAN
FRANCISCO'S 34 YEAR FREEWAY BATTLE TO SAVE ITS WATERFRONT.
>> NOW 50 YEARS LATER RECKON PARK LOOKED THE COULD ONLY SEE
THE NEGLECTED FOUNTAIN RATHER THAN THE ONE THAT HAD ONCE
JOYFULLY RIDICULED A JOYLESS, UNIVERSALLY DESPISED 40 FOOT
HIGH DOUBLE DECKER FREEWAY THAT WALLED OFF THE CITY FROM ITS
GORGEOUS NORTHERN WATER FRUIT VIE IN COURT HAD MADE AN
ASTOUNDING CONCEPTUAL DESIGN LEAP REIMAGINING THE FREEWAYS
ELEPHANTINE PILLARS OF HOLLOW PRECAST CONCRETE BEADS STRUNG
TOGETHER TO SPOUT RAMPS, ANXIOUS BURSTS OF WATER INTO A
SHALLOW POOL. I'VE PRACTICED ARCHITECTURE
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO FOR 50 YEARS AND TAUGHT ARCHITECTURE
DESIGN AT BERKELEY FOR 20 YEARS.
>> THAT'S THE PERSPECTIVE I BRING TO THE TOPIC.
>> I KNOW THAT THE KEY TO AFFORDING ANY CONSTRUCTION
BUDGET IS ATTITUDE WHEN THERE'S A WILL TO GET A PROJECT.
>> THANK YOU SIR. >> THE PROD THE BUDGET CAN BE
PUSHED AND PULLED UNTIL IT WORKS.
IF THERE'S NO WILL THE FUNDS WILL FOREVER BE OUT OF REACH
FOR BIG. >> YEAH.
>> ALL RIGHT. WHAT?
THANK YOU, SIR. >> BRING TO THE TABLE A LOT OF
THEM. I HOW WAS THAT ATTITUDE
CONVEYED TO THE CONSULTANT? THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
SIR. WE ARE HAPPY TO TAKE YOUR
COMMENTS AND WE CAN PLACE IT INTO THE RECORD.
>> OKAY. NEXT SPEAKER ON BEHALF OF THE
APPELLANT WE JUST ASK THAT YOU HOLD YOUR APPLAUSE EVERYONE
THERE IS A BOARD RULE NO AUDIBLE SOUNDS OF A OF ANY SORT
APPROVAL OR AGAINST. >> WELCOME, MA'AM.
YEAH, THANK YOU. MY NAME IS BRIDGET BOYLAN.
I LIVED 20 YEARS IN THE GOLDEN GATEWAY APARTMENTS SO I'M OVER
AT THE VAILLANCOURT FOUNTAIN QUITE A BIT.
IT'S I LOVE THAT FOUNTAIN. I REALLY URGE YOU TO PUT THE
BRAKES ON THIS OVERLY FAST RETCHING PARKS DEPARTMENT
DECISION TO JUST IT'S IT'S DANGEROUS BUT ON A MORE
PERSONAL LEVEL I THOUGHT I WOULD JUST BRING TO YOUR
ATTENTION WHAT WHAT I THINK OF WHEN I SEE THAT FOUNTAIN SO ONE
OF THE FIRST THINGS I SEE IS OCTOPUS ARMS ALSO I WAS OVER AT
THE PIER SEVEN THIS MORNING LOOKING DOWN AT THE WATER
AND THERE WERE THE PIERS COVERED IN BARNACLES SQUARE
PIERS COVERED IN BARNACLES. I THOUGHT THIS LOOKS LIKE
VAILLANCOURT FOUNTAIN. >> IT LOOKS LIKE LEGO.
IT JUST IT'S GOT A LOT OF IT'S IT'S IT'S A PIECE OF ART THAT
HAS A LOT OF A LOT OF PEOPLE CAN LOOK AT IT AND SEE VERY
DIFFERENT THINGS I THINK IT SHOULD REMAIN THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER MY
NAME IS DAVID MICHELLE. I'VE BEEN A RESIDENT OF SAN
FRANCISCO SINCE 1970 AND I TOO WAS AT THE DEDICATION OF THE
FOUNTAIN IN 72. >> I'M NOT HERE TO SPEAK ABOUT
ITS VALIDITY OR WHY IT SHOULD REMAIN BECAUSE AS I UNDERSTAND
IT, WHAT YOU ARE BEING ASKED TO DECIDE IS WHETHER I WILL EVER
GET A CHANCE TO SPEAK IN FAVOR OF THE FOUNTAIN AND ITS VALUE.
>> THIS IS ABOUT THE NEGLECT WHICH THE PARK HAS COMMITTED ON
THIS FOUNTAIN OVER THE DECADES WHEN IT'S NO LONGER ASSESSABLE
AND CERTAINLY IT'S NO MORE FUN TO ENJOY AND FEEL AND GET
INSIDE AND THEN THEY WANT TO MAKE THIS NEGLECT BE AN
EMERGENCY THAT REQUIRES THEM TO SKIP AN OPPORTUNITY TO HEAR HOW
THE PUBLIC ACTUALLY FEELS ABOUT THEIR DECISION.
SO I REALLY URGE YOU TO APPROVE THIS MEASURE SO THAT THE PUBLIC
WILL IN FACT HAVE A CHANCE UNDER THE ORDERLY PROCESS OF
MAKING THESE DECISIONS THE PUBLIC WILL HAVE ITS CHANCE TO
SPEAK AND I WILL BE HAPPY TO RETURN AT THAT TIME AND EXPLAIN
TO YOU WHY I THINK THE FOUNTAIN SHOULD INDEED BE PRESERVED.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, DAVID MICHELLE FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HELLO. GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS KEVIN DOMINGUEZ AND IN 2008 TO 2021 I WAS THE
GENERAL MANAGER AT HOTEL THE DIAGEO WHICH WAS A GREAT HONOR
TO BE A PART OF THAT HISTORIC BUILDING AND PEOPLE REALLY
ENJOYED WHAT THE HISTORIC VALUE WAS THAT IT BROUGHT AT THAT
TIME. >> IT WAS A PLEASURE TO ALSO
TELL PEOPLE ABOUT ALL THE DIVERSE ARTWORK IN THE CITY
AND THIS IS WHAT I LOVED ABOUT SAN FRANCISCO IS THAT THE
PEOPLE CARE ABOUT THEIR ARTWORK.
>> THEY CARE ABOUT THEIR CITY, THEY CARE ABOUT THE EXPERIENCE.
I REALLY HOPE THAT YOU RECONSIDER THIS IDEA OF ERASING
HISTORY. AS YOU CAN SEE THERE'S MANY,
MANY AGES IN THIS ROOM AND TAKING AWAY SOMETHING.
THIS MEANS THAT THE THREAT OF POSSIBLY TAKING AWAY FROM
SOMEBODY ELSE'S GENERATION AS WELL LOOKING SORRY IT'S A FEW
THINGS BECAUSE OF THE FIRST TIME I DID THIS BEFORE I JUST
HOPE THAT THIS IMPORTANT PUBLIC ART IS NOT ERASED FROM SAN
FRANCISCO'S HISTORY AND AS THE CODE OF ARMED SHOWS FOR SAN
FRANCISCO I REALLY HOPE IT RISES FROM AS LIKE THE PHENIX
WHICH IS A GREAT SYMBOL FOR THE CITY.
IT MEANS THAT THERE'S HOPE AND THERE'S CARE INVOLVED.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU KEVIN DOMINGUEZ FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
OUR NEXT SPEAKER ON BEHALF OF THE APPELLANT HI SUPERVISORS MY
NAME IS MATT JOSEPH. I'M A RESIDENT OF POTRERO HILL
AS ONE OF THE OTHER PUBLIC COMMENTERS SAID, THERE'S
IMMENSE DISCUSSION HERE TO BE HAD ABOUT ART BUT TODAY IS NOT
ABOUT ART. IT'S ABOUT A SO CALLED
EMERGENCY AND IT'S SOMETHING THAT I DO IN MY JOB SOMETHING
THAT MY FATHER DID BEFORE ME AND SOMETHING THAT MANY
PROFESSIONALS IN THE INDUSTRY DO IS EVALUATE RISK.
OKAY? AND OFTEN WHEN YOU EVALUATE
RISK YOU DO IT IN TWO DIMENSIONS.
YOU EVALUATE IT IN TERMS OF LIKELIHOOD OF THAT RISK AND YOU
EVALUATE IT IN TERMS OF THE IMPACT OF THAT RISK.
THAT'S WHAT PROFESSIONALS DO. THEY DON'T PUT UP A BUNCH OF
SCARY TECHNICAL JARGON. THEY DON'T PUT UP A BUNCH OF
THINGS THAT SAY THE ARM IS GOING TO COLLAPSE.
THEY DON'T GIVE YOU A BUNCH OF TECHNICAL DETAILS.
THEY SYNTHESIZE IT INTO SOMETHING MEANINGFUL AND THAT'S
LIKELIHOOD AND IMPACT. SO WHAT IS LIKELIHOOD HERE?
THE LIKELIHOOD BEFORE US TODAY IS DEFINED IN PROJECT SPONSORS
WHERE IT IS ME OR POTENTIAL OR APPEARS OR COULD OR MIGHT.
>> THE REALITY IS THAT NO ONE IN THE AUDIENCE HERE CAN
PREDICT THAT PREDICT THE NEXT EARTHQUAKE.
NO ONE HERE CAN SAY WITH ABSOLUTE CERTAINTY WHEN
SOMETHING'S GOING TO HAPPEN. SO IN FACT THE LIKELIHOOD IS
RARE OR UNLIKELY? IT IS NOT LIKELY IT IS NOT
ALMOST CERTAIN. IT IS SIMPLY UNLIKELY IT MIGHT
HAPPEN BUT NO ONE HERE CAN SAY WHEN.
WHAT IS THE IMPACT? WELL, THE IMPACT CAN'T BE
LOOKED AT IN ISOLATION. THE IMPACT HAS TO BE LOOKED AT
IN THE LARGER SCOPE OF OUR CITY.
WHAT IS CATASTROPHIC IMPACT THAT IS INVOLVES MULTIPLE
FATALITIES, THAT INVOLVES DISASTERS, THAT INVOLVES
LANDSLIDES, THAT INVOLVES EMBARCADERO CENTER CRUMBLING
DOWN UNDER AN EARTHQUAKE THAT IS CATASTROPHIC.
BUT WHAT ARE WE TALKING ABOUT HERE TODAY?
>> WE'RE TALKING ABOUT THINGS THAT PEOPLE EXPERIENCE ON A
REGULAR BASIS THE LEAD IN 90% OF HOMES IN SAN FRANCISCO, THE
ASBESTOS AND 90% OF HOMES IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THE SEISMIC RISK ENCOUNTERED BY HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF SAN
FRANCISCO EVENTS EVERY DAY. AND SO THE IMPACT NECESSARILY
EXISTS. IT IS SERIOUS BUT IT IS NOT
EXTREME OR CATASTROPHIC OR HIGH.
IT IS MODERATE OR LOW. AND SO IF WE LOOK ON THESE TWO
AXIS, THE LIKELIHOOD LOW THE IMPACT LOW THIS IS NOT AN
EMERGENCY. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER ON BEHALF OF THE
APPELLANT, WELCOME. HELLO SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS ANDREA STANISIC. I AM A PRACTICING ARCHITECT
IN SAN FRANCISCO AND THE BAY AREA AND I'VE PERMITTED SEVERAL
PROJECTS THROUGH THE SAN FRANCISCO PLANNING AND BUILDING
DEPARTMENT. >> OFTENTIMES WHEN I'M WORKING
WITH MY CLIENTS I HAVE TO GO BACK TO THEM AND SAY HEY,
THERE'S THIS EXTRA PROCESS OR THIS EXTRA STEP THAT WE HAVE TO
TAKE THAT'S BEING REQUIRED BY THE CITY IN ORDER FOR YOU TO
MOVE FORWARD WITH OBTAINING A BUILDING PERMIT IT'S GOING TO
COST YOU TIME, IT'S GOING TO COST YOU MONEY BUT IT'S
REQUIRED AND ALSO THE RIGHT THING TO DO IN MOST CASES.
AND SO AS A WORKING PROFESSIONAL TO SEE THE CITY
KIND OF BLATANTLY SIDESTEP THE PROCESSES THAT HAVE BEEN
PUTTING IN PLACE FOR THESE KINDS OF PROJECTS, I FIND
EXTREMELY DISCOURAGING AND DISHEARTENING.
>> I'M ALSO A PARENT AND AS A PARENT I FEEL THAT YOU MODEL
THE BEHAVIOR THAT YOU WANT YOUR CHILDREN TO LEARN IN ORDER TO
BECOME DECENT HUMAN BEINGS AND I FEEL LIKE THE CITY
IN THIS CASE IS NOT MODELING THE BEHAVIOR THAT ANYONE
WORKING WITHIN THE BUILT ENVIRONMENT IN SAN FRANCISCO IS
GOING TO NEED TO BE ABLE TO DO IN ORDER TO PERMIT OR GET
ANYTHING BUILT. THANK YOU.
THAT'S IT. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
ARE THERE ANY OTHER SPEAKERS ON BEHALF OF THE APPELLANT PLEASE
PROCEED OVER TO THE LINE NEAR THE CURTAINS.
OTHERWISE THIS MAY BE OUR LAST SPEAKER.
WELCOME. >> I JUST WANT TO SHARE ANY
GAMERS OUT THERE THAT THIS MOUNTAIN IS A SCALABLE SPOT.
>> TONY HAWK RELEASED IN 99. MAY I ASK YOU TO SPEAK DIRECTLY
INTO THE MICROPHONE JUST AS CLOSE AS YOU CAN.
>> THANKS. SO PLEASE SUPERVISORS, FIX IT.
DON'T NIX IT. IT FELL INTO DISREPAIR.
IT WAS A VERY COOL FOUNTAIN WATER FLOWING THROUGH IT.
PEOPLE WOULD TAKE PHOTOS TOURISTS.
EVERYONE LOVED IT. PLEASE FIX IT.
THE ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT OF MOVING TONS OF CONCRETE INTO
STORAGE IT'S SIGNIFICANT. >> IF YOU CAN TRY TO FIX IT SO
THAT WE CAN ENJOY IT ONE LAST TIME.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> RIGHT.
ONE MORE. OH, OKAY.
SO LAST. I DON'T I'M NOT FAMILIAR WITH
THIS FONT AND FOR WHATEVER REASON I HAVEN'T STUDIED IT
THINKING IT WILL BE THERE FOREVER.
NOW WHAT'S THE GOAL? >> WHY DO YOU TAKE THIS THING
DOWN? THAT'S KEY, RIGHT?
SO IF THE GOAL WAS GOOD DON'T WORRY THEY WOULD ASK YOU PUBLIC
OPINION. >> IT'S BECAUSE IT'S NO GOOD.
SO IT MEANS THEY DON'T WANT YOUR OPINION BECAUSE
EVERYBODY'S GOING TO BE AGAINST REMOVING THIS THING IS VERY
EASY TO UNDERSTAND. >> SO YOU FIGHT TO KEEP THIS
THING. >> THAT'S IT.
YOU ARE DESTROYING DUTY HERE. IT'S A SORT OF BEAUTY.
IT'S NOT GOING TO WORK. YOU CAN'T DESTROY BEAUTY.
>> BEAUTY WINS IN THE END NO MATTER WHAT.
>> SO THAT'S MY TAKE ON IT. OKAY.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS, MR. PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. SEEING NO OTHER SPEAKERS PUBLIC
COMMENT AND SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL IS NOW CLOSED.
>> NOW WE'RE GOING TO HAVE A PRESENTATION FROM OF UP TO TEN
MINUTES FROM THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT AND MEMBERS OF THE
BOARD. MY NAME IS KEISUKE.
I'M A SENIOR PLANNER WITH THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT.
JOINING ME TODAY ARE LISA GIBSON, ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW
OFFICER AND TANYA SENIOR PRINCIPAL PLANNER.
ALSO WITH THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT FOLLOWING MY
PRESENTATION STAFF FROM THE RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT
AND ARTS COMMISSION WILL PROVIDE ADDITIONAL INFORMATION
REGARDING THE PROJECT AND BACKGROUND.
THE PROJECT SITE IS THE EMBARCADERO FOUNTAIN LOCATED AT
THE NORTH EAST CORNER OF THE EMBARCADERO PLAZA.
IN THE FINANCIAL DISTRICT THE RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT
ONE OF THE CITY AGENCIES RESPONSIVE FOR MAINTAINING THE
EMBARCADERO FOUNTAIN PROPOSES TO DISASSEMBLE AND REMOVE THE
FOUNTAIN FOR STORAGE AND FURTHER TECHNICAL ANALYSIS.
THE PURPOSE OF THE PROJECT IS TWOFOLD FIRST TO ELIMINATE AN
IMMEDIATE PUBLIC SAFETY RISK. AND SECOND TO FACILITATE
FURTHER INVESTIGATION INTO THE FOUNTAIN'S DETERIORATING
STRUCTURAL INTEGRITY AND AND THE PRESENCE OF HAZARDOUS
MATERIALS USED IN ITS CONSTRUCTION.
>> THE FOUNTAIN CURRENTLY EXHIBITS NUMEROUS SEVERE
STRUCTURAL DEFICIENCIES. THESE INCLUDE CRACKED
AND DETERIORATED DETERIORATED CONCRETE THROUGHOUT THE
FOUNTAIN. ADVANCED CORROSION OF EMBEDDED
STRUCTURAL STEEL AS WELL AS MISSING OR FAILED CRITICAL
STRUCTURAL WEIGHT SUPPORTING ELEMENTS.
PARTIAL STRUCTURAL FAILURE OF ONE OF THE FOUNTAINS
APPROXIMATELY TEN TON CONCRETE ARMS WHICH IS CURRENTLY RESTING
ON ANOTHER CONCRETE ARM. AS BUILT CONDITIONS THAT DO NOT
CONFORM TO THE DESIGN DRAWINGS FOR EXAMPLE PRECAST ELEMENTS
ALONG THE BACK WALL OF THE FOUNTAIN ARE REINFORCED DESPITE
DESPITE THE DESIGN CALLING FOR FOR THEM TO BE ANCHORED TO THE
MAT FORM THE FOUNDATION MISSING OR DISCONTINUOUS REINFORCEMENT
STEEL. NONCOMPLIANCE WITH CURRENT
SEISMIC AND SAFETY HAZARD EXCUSE ME STATE SEISMIC
AND SAFETY STANDARDS. HEIGHTENED STRUCTURAL RISKS DUE
TO THE FOUNTAIN'S LOCATION ON UNCONSOLIDATED FEEL AND BAY
MUD. AND ACCELERATED STRUCTURAL
DETERIORATION CAUSED BY THE PREVIOUS EXPOSURE TO WATER.
COMBINED WITH CONTINUED EXPOSURE TO SAN FRANCISCO'S
HUMID HUMID MARINE ENVIRONMENT, THESE CONDITIONS ARE DOCUMENTED
IN IN A MAY 19TH 2025 REPORT BY ENGINEERING FIRM DCI.
AND OCTOBER 27TH 2025 LETTER FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING
INSPECTION AND THE JUNE 2ND 2025 REPORT FROM PAGE TURNBULL.
THE RECORD ALSO DOCUMENTS BREACHING OF FENCING AND OTHER
SECURITY MEASURES INTENDED TO RESTRICT PUBLIC ACCESS TO THE
STRUCTURE. DESPITE THESE CONTROLS
INDIVIDUALS HAVE ENTERED THE STRUCTURE INCLUDING SLEEPING
WITH THE CONCRETE TUBES. >> AS A RESULT, IF A STRUCTURAL
FEAR FAILURE WERE TO OCCUR AND ONE OF THE TEN TONNE
CONCRETE ARMS WERE TO FALL IT COULD CAUSE SERIOUS INJURY OR
IN THE WORST CASE LOSS OF LIFE. BASED ON THESE CONDITIONS THE
RECREATION PARKS DEPARTMENT DETERMINED THAT THE FOUNTAIN'S
CONDITION CONSTITUTES A SAFETY EMERGENCY.
BASED ON THE SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE IN THE RECORD, THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT DETERMINED THAT THE PRODUCT QUALIFIES FOR
AN EMERGENCY STATUTORY EXEMPTION UNDER SECRET
GUIDELINES SECTION 15269. >> STATUTORY EXEMPTIONS ARE
ESTABLISHED BY THE STATE LEGISLATURE TO EXEMPT CERTAIN
PRODUCTS FROM SEEKING REVIEW TO ADVANCE OTHER IMPORTANT POLICY
GOALS. IN THIS CASE THE EMERGENCY
STATUTORY EXEMPTION WAS ISSUED TO PREVENT OR MITIGATE SAFETY
EMERGENCY. >> THE DEPARTMENT'S KEY
RESPONSES TO THE APPEAL ARE SUMMARIZED ON THIS SLIDE
AND DISCUSSING OUR JANUARY 5TH AND JANUARY 8TH APPEAL
RESPONSES. >> FIRST, APPELLANT DISREGARDS
SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE IN THE RECORD DEMONSTRATING THAT THE
PRODUCT IS REQUIRED TO PREVENT OR MITIGATE A SAFETY EMERGENCY
AND THAT THE STATUTE DOES NOT REQUIRE AN EMERGENCY TO HAVE
OCCURRED. >> NOR DOES IT PROHIBIT THE
ISSUANCE OF STATUTORY EXEMPTION WHEN THE PRODUCT COULD HAVE A
SIGNIFICANT IMPACT ON THE HISTORIC RESOURCE STAFF FROM
THE RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENTS.
DEPARTMENT WILL FURTHER ADDRESS THE NATURE OF THE SAFETY RISKS.
>> THE APPELLANT ALSO ASSERTS THAT THE CITY MANUFACTURED THE
EMERGENCY THROUGH CALCULATED LONG TERM DEFERRED MAINTENANCE
. THIS ASSERTION IS NOT SUPPORTED
BY THE FACTUAL RECORD AND IMMATERIAL TO THE EXEMPTION
ANALYSIS. SEQUA DOES NOT REQUIRE THE LEAD
AGENCY TO EVALUATE THE ORIGIN OR INTENT BEHIND THE HAZARD.
IT REQUIRES A DETERMINATION WHETHER URGENT ACTION IS
NECESSARY TO ADDRESS A CLEAR AND IMMINENT DANGER.
SECOND, CONTRARY TO THE APPELLANT CLAIM THE CITY DID
NOT APPROVE OR COMMIT TO THE PROJECT PRIOR TO COMPLETING THE
ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW. >> SECRET PROHIBITS PUBLIC
AGENCIES FROM APPROVING OR COMMITTING TO A PROJECT BEFORE
COMPLETING ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW.
HERE THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT ISSUED AN EMERGENCY STATUTORY
EXEMPTION ON OCTOBER 31ST, 2025.
THE ARTS COMMISSION SUBSEQUENTLY APPROVED THE
PROJECT ON NOVEMBER 3RD, 2025, RELYING ON THE STATUTORY
EXEMPTION. WHILE PRELIMINARY DISCUSSIONS
PLANNING OCCURRED PRIOR TO THE ARTS COMMISSION APPROVAL, THOSE
ACTIVITIES DID NOT COMMIT THE CITY TO A DEFINITE COURSE OF
ACTION REGARDING THE SCOPE OR NATURE OF THE FOUNDATION
REMOVAL. THEREFORE THE CITY DID NOT
IMPERMISSIBLY COMMIT TO THE PROJECT PRIOR TO COMPLETING
COMPLETING THE ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW.
>> FINALLY THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S ISSUANCE OF THE
EMERGENCY STATUTORY EXEMPTION DOES NOT CONSTITUTE
IMPERMISSIBLE PIECEMEALING UNDER CEQA.
>> SEQUEL ALLOWS ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW FOR DISCRETE COMPONENT
OF A PROJECT WHEN THAT COMPONENT HAS INDEPENDENT
UTILITY EVEN IF IT'S RELATED TO THAT LARGER PROJECT.
>> IN THIS CASE THE FOUNTAIN REMOVAL DOES NOT RELY ON THE
LARGER EMBARCADERO PLAZA IMPROVEMENTS TO IMPLEMENT IT
AND VICE VERSA. ALSO THE FOUNTAIN REMOVAL DOES
NOT LIMIT THE OPTIONS AVAILABLE FOR THE DESIGN OF THE PLAZA.
GIVEN THAT THE FOUNTAIN WILL BE PLACED IN STORAGE THEREFORE THE
TWO PROJECTS HAVE INDEPENDENT UTILITY AND THE FOUNTAIN
REMOVAL DOES NOT CONSTITUTE IMPERMISSIBLE PIECEMEALING.
>> TO CONCLUDE THE DEPARTMENT HAS PROVIDED SUBSTANTIAL
EVIDENCE DEMONSTRATING THAT THE PROJECT IS STATUTORILY EXEMPT
FROM SECURE ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW UNDER SEQUOIA GUIDELINES
SECTION 15269. THE APPELLANT HAS NOT
DEMONSTRATED THAT THE ISSUANCE OF STATUTORY EXEMPTION WAS NOT
SUPPORTED BY SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE IN THE RECORD.
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT THEREFORE RESPECTFULLY
RECOMMENDS THAT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS UPHOLD THE
DEPARTMENT'S DETERMINATION AND DENY THE APPEAL.
THANK YOU. STAFF ARE AVAILABLE TO ANSWER
ANY QUESTIONS YOU MAY HAVE IN ADDITION.
WE HAVE A REPRESENTATIVE HERE FROM DCI, THE FIRM THAT
PREPARED THE CONDITION ASSESSMENT REPORT.
>> >> THANK YOU. I DO NOT SEE ANY COLLEAGUES UP.
SUPERVISOR JAN. THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MAN DOMAIN
. >> I'M JUST TRYING TO
UNDERSTAND WITH SORT OF KIND OF MAKING THE ARGUMENT ABOUT THE
REMOVAL OH, I'M JUST TRYING TO UNDERSTAND WHAT IS THE PROCESS
LIKE FOR THE REMOVAL AND APPROXIMATELY THE CALLS FOR
THE REMOVAL AND SHOULD IT BE REMOVED WHAT WHAT IT'S GOING TO
HAPPEN TO IT LIKE LIKE THIS TO THAT SPACE LIKE WHAT'S GOING TO
GO INTO IT? >> GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT
MALAMAN. I'M LISA GIBSON, ENVIRONMENTAL
REVIEW OFFICER. I'D LIKE TO ASK IF IT'S
POSSIBLE THAT REC PARK COULD ANSWER THAT QUESTION.
>> SURE. >> COME ON UP.
PARK THANK YOU SO MUCH SUPERVISOR, FOR YOUR QUESTION.
>> SO THE QUESTION WAS WHAT'S GOING TO HAPPEN TO THE
FOUNTAIN? WHERE WILL IT OR HOW WILL IT BE
STORED AND WHAT'S THE COST? >> IS THAT CORRECT?
CORRECT. OKAY.
SO THE TENTATIVE PLAN WILL BE THAT THE FOUNTAIN WOULD BE
REMOVED IN ABOUT A MONTH IN MID-FEBRUARY.
THIS IS AFTER THE 90 DAY CAP A REQUIREMENT TO NOTIFY THE
ARTIST OR MAN VAILLANCOURT THE PROCESS WOULD TAKE
APPROXIMATELY TWO MONTHS AND IT WOULD BE STORED OFFSITE FOR UP
TO THREE YEARS. THE COST TO REMOVE TO
DISASSEMBLE AND STORE IT IS APPROXIMATELY $4.4 MILLION.
>> AND WHAT IS THE FUNDING SOURCE FOR THAT 4.4 MILLION.
THAT WOULD BE PROJECT MONDAY. I WOULD BE SORRY.
OH PROJECT FUNDING. >> WHERE'S THE PROJECT FUNDING
SOURCE COMING FROM? >> >> I'M GOING TO DIRECT THIS
QUESTION TO STACIE BRADLEY. >> HI SUPERVISOR.
THANK YOU FOR THE QUESTION. MY NAME IS STACY BRADLEY.
I'M THE DIRECTOR OF OUR CAPITAL AND PLANNING DIVISION AT REC
AND PARK. I'M THE PROJECT FUNDS ARE
DEVELOPED THROUGH THE THERE IS A SEPARATE PROJECT THAT WE ARE
WORKING ON THE EMBARCADERO PLAZA PROJECT THAT HAS
IDENTIFIED IS ABLE TO DEAL WITH THIS EMERGENCY SITUATION.
SO WE ARE USING PROJECT FUNDS FROM THE LARGER EMBARCADERO
PLAZA RENOVATION PROJECT TO DEAL WITH THIS SEPARATE PROJECT
AND THE FUND SOURCE IS THERE'S MULTIPLE SOURCES.
SO WE HAVE 2024 BOND DOLLARS. WE ALSO HAVE A PARTNERSHIP UP
WITH A DOWNTOWN PARTNERSHIP AND B P TO DELIVER PRIVATE
FUNDING. >> SOUNDS LIKE IT'S A IF I
RECALL CORRECTLY I THINK THAT WE RECENTLY DID TO ACCEPT
AND EXPEND GRANT ROUGHLY. SOUNDS LIKE YOU'RE USING THE
ACCEPT AND EXPAND GRANT THAT THE CITY HAS ACCEPTED MOST
RECENTLY TO FOR THE REMOVAL OF THE FOUNTAIN.
>> YES, THAT IS OUR ANTICIPATION.
AND WHAT WILL BE DONE GOING INTO IT?
SHOULD IT BE REMOVE? >> LIKE WHAT WHAT WILL HAPPEN
TO THAT SPACE? WELL, WE DON'T KNOW RIGHT NOW
SO PART THIS PROJECT THE REMOVAL THE THIS PROJECT IS
LOOKING AT THE REMOVAL OF THE FOUNTAIN AND KEEPING IT IN A
SECURE LOCATION AND SECURING THE SPACE AS WE'VE IDENTIFIED
NEXT STEPS. >> SO IT'S IT'S KIND OF LIKE AN
EMPTY JUST LIKE AN EMPTY PLOT LIKE AFTER REMOVAL.
YES. LIKE AFTER FEBRUARY OR AFTER
MARCH. THEN IT WILL BE JUST LIKE AN
EMPTY SPACE THERE. YES.
AND HOW DO YOU PLAN TO SECURE I MEAN ONCE IT'S DEMOLISHED OR
NOT REMOVE YOU TAKING OUR PARK AND HOW DO YOU PLAN TO SECURE
THAT SPACE? >> WE'RE GOING TO USE SIMILAR
TO FENCING TO WHAT IS THERE TODAY THERE'S FENCING
AND PLANTING IN THE AREA AND SO WE WILL CONTINUE TO KEEP THAT
SAME FENCING SOMETHING SIMILAR UNDER.
AND HOW MUCH ROUGHLY WOULD THEN BE FROM THEN AND ON OUT IS
SHOULD IT BE REMOVED? WHAT IS THE MAINTENANCE BUDGET
LOOK LIKE AND WHAT WE WOULD MAINTAIN THE SPACE IN THE SAME
WAY THAT WE MAINTAIN THE WHOLE EMBARCADERO PLAZA.
>> AND HOW MUCH DOES IT COST RIGHT NOW TO MAINTAIN THE
FOUNTAIN OR HOW HAS IT HOW MUCH HAS IT BEEN AS A AS A
MAINTENANCE FUND FOR THE FOUNTAIN?
>> WE WORK JOINTLY WITH THE ARTS COMMISSION TO MAINTAIN THE
SPACE WE BOTH I BELIEVE THE ARTS COMMISSION WHO IS HERE
AND CAN ANSWER AS WELL FROM THEIR PERSPECTIVE.
BUT BOTH OF OUR AGENCIES IDENTIFY MAINTENANCE FUNDING
THROUGHOUT ALL OF OUR PROJECTS RIGHT?
SO WHEN SOMETHING IS NEEDED WE WILL USE IT TO ADDRESS
MAINTENANCE NEEDS. DOES THAT MAKE SENSE?
SO FROM OUR LARGER BUDGET OF MAINTAINING ALL OF OUR PARKS
AND OPEN SPACES AND FROM THE ARTS COMMISSION LARGER BUDGET
OF MAINTAINING THEIR CIVIC ART COLLECTION WE THEN ALLOCATE
NECESSARY FUNDS TO MAIN UP TO MAINTAIN, TO OPERATE
AND MAINTAIN OF COURSE. >> AND DO WE KNOW ROUGHLY HOW
MUCH THAT IS ON AN ANNUAL BASIS?
>> I AM SORRY. >> GO AHEAD.
HI. I CAN ANSWER THAT ONE.
YEAH. WE ASKED OUR DIRECTOR OF
OPERATIONS ABOUT HOW MUCH IT WOULD COST AT SOMEWHERE BETWEEN
50 TO $100,000. IT KIND OF DEPENDED ON THE YEAR
BUT THAT INCLUDED JUST FROM REC PARKSIDE IT WAS, YOU KNOW,
GRAFFITI ABATEMENT WHICH THE ARTS COMMISSION HAS ALSO WAS
ALSO DOING CLEANING OUT THAT ENTIRE FOUNTAIN QUARTERLY
AND REMOVING ALL DEBRIS TO ALLOW FOR REMOVAL OF SEDIMENT
MAINTAINING THE PUMP SO THE LAST PUMP STOPPED WORKING
IN MAY OF 2024 AND IT WAS A NEAR DAILY JOB TO GO OVER THERE
AND CHECK EVERYTHING. >> SO THAT WAS THAT WAS THERE
ESTIMATE IN THE LAST FEW YEARS. >> THANK YOU.
>> I JUST WANTED TO MAKE A STATEMENT ABOUT HOW I VIEW THE
FOUNTAIN, YOU KNOW, AND REALLY ALSO HOW I VIEW THE ENTIRE
SPACE. FIRST, I APPRECIATE THE MOST
RECENT NAME REMOVAL FROM JUSTIN HERMAN PLAZA TWO NOW KNOWN AS
AND BACK OR DARROW PLAZA. I THINK THERE'S A INTERESTING
HISTORY IN THAT SPACE. I GREW UP IN SAN FRANCISCO'S
CHINATOWN AND IN THAT AREA AND AND VISIT THAT AREA OFTEN I
DO NOT HAVE A PERSONAL ATTACHMENT TO SORT OF THIS
BRUTALIST FOUNTAIN AS I AS I VIEW IT.
BUT I DO UNDERSTAND ITS VALUE AND ITS ITS AS A MARK OF OUR
HISTORY AND AS A CITY I DO APPRECIATE ITS EXISTENCE BUT I,
I ALSO CAN UNDERSTAND JUST MOVING FORWARD AS A FUTURE
VISION FOR THAT SPACE. I AM I AM TORN AND IT'S
CONFLICTED. IT'S CERTAINLY IS A CHARACTER
PART OF THE CHARACTERS CHARACTERISTICS OF WHO WE ARE
AS A CITY IN THAT SPACE. BUT I CAN CERTAINLY ALSO SEE
HOW IT'S BEEN DETERIORATING QUITE SOME TIME NOW.
SO THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR ANSWERING THE
QUESTIONS. >> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU
PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN CHURCH AND I APPRECIATE YOUR QUESTIONS
AND CAN PROVIDE SOME INSIGHT FROM GOVERNMENT ON AN OVERSIGHT
COMMITTEE IN MARCH AND ALSO OH IN MARCH WE APPROVED AIBA
HAZARD PAYMENTS WAIVER FOR THE GENERAL MANAGER AND PARK THE
DIRECTOR AND STAFF OF REGEN PARK, THE MAYOR AND SEVERAL
STAFF IN THE MAYOR'S OFFICE TO HAVE A BIG HAZARD PAYMENT
WAIVER AND SOLICIT DONATIONS FOR THE RENOVATION OF THE
EMBARCADERO PLAZA AND SUBURBAN PARKS FROM INDIVIDUALS
AND NONPROFITS. >> WE ALSO PASSED A ANOTHER
RESOLUTION IN IN MARCH WITH BXP EMBARCADERO PLAZA DOWNTOWN
THERE IS SAN FRANCISCO PARTNERSHIP ACCEPTING CASH
AND IN-KIND GRANTS FROM THE APPROXIMATELY 2.5 MILLION FOR
THE DESIGN AND OUR PD AND ADDITIONAL GRANTS OF
APPROXIMATELY 10 MILLION FROM THE DOWNTOWN COMMUNITY BENEFIT
DISTRICT. ALL THAT TO SAY THERE'S A LOT
OF MONEY GOING INTO THIS FROM OUTSIDE OF THE CITY GOVERNMENT.
IT SEEMS AND I JUST YOU KNOW THIS THIS IS A PRETTY UGLY
FOUNTAIN. >> I THINK EVERYONE CAN AGREE
ON THAT. BUT BUT YOU KNOW LET ME FINISH
LET ME FINISH. >> CLEARLY CLEARLY AN IMPORTANT
HISTORICAL PART OF THIS AREA AND SAN FRANCISCO'S HISTORY
WHETHER WHETHER YOU APPRECIATE OR NOT IT EVOKES SOMETHING
IN YOU AND I THINK THAT IS THE POINT OF ART AND ARCHITECTURE
AND I ALSO APPRECIATE OF OH J PLEASE.
>> I ALSO APPRECIATE THAT IT IS AN IMPORTANT PART OF THE
SKATEBOARDING COMMUNITY WHETHER THAT IS RECOGNIZED BY US HERE
AND IN THE ROOM OR NOT THERE'S SOMETHING TO BE SAID ABOUT SAN
FRANCISCO'S HISTORY AND AND WHAT WE ALL LOVE ABOUT IT AND I
JUST IT DOESN'T IT DOESN'T SIT WELL HOW MUCH MONEY IS IS BEING
PUT FROM OUTSIDE ENTITIES AND WHOEVER IS IT'S NOT REALLY
JUST ABOUT THE FOUNTAIN IT'S CLEAR TO ME IT'S NOT JUST ABOUT
THE FOUNTAIN. THERE'S ALSO, YOU KNOW, A
PRIORITIES AND IT SEEMS LIKE THERE IS A LOT OF INTEREST FROM
A LOT OF POWERFUL PEOPLE DOWNTOWN IN THIS PARTICULAR
SPOT. AND I FIND IT VERY INTERESTING
THAT WHEN THAT'S THE CASE I RECKON PARK CAN MOVE MOUNTAINS
IN ORDER TO GET SOMETHING DONE. MEANWHILE I HAVE A LETTER TO
THEM OUTLINING ALL THE WAYS IN WHICH DISTRICT NINE
AND SPECIFICALLY THE MISSION IS STILL IGNORED WHEN IT COMES TO
PROGRAMING, WHEN IT COMES TO THE QUALITY OF OUR FACILITIES
LIKE THE MISSION REC CENTER AND I'M STILL AWAITING A
RESPONSE TO HEAR ANYTHING ABOUT ADDRESSING THOSE AND SO THAT'S
WHERE I AM ON THIS AND THAT'S HOW I'LL BE ASSESSING HOW TO
MOVE FORWARD. >> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU.
THIS IS A GOOD DISCUSSION FOR ME IT'S A LITTLE MORE
STRAIGHTFORWARD IN THAT THIS IS AN APPEAL OF A DETERMINATION OF
EXEMPTION FROM ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW WHETHER OR NOT THE BROOK
PARK DEPARTMENT IN THE PAST NEGLECTED THE MAINTENANCE OF
THE FOUNTAIN. THE FACT IS RIGHT NOW THE
FOUNTAIN IS NOT WORKING AND IT DOES PRESENT A HAZARD EVEN
THOUGH FOLKS SKATE ON IT AND DO ALL KINDS OF THINGS ON IT.
IT DOESN'T MEAN THAT IT'S SAFE. IT'S ACTUALLY QUITE HAZARDOUS.
AND SO FOR ME IT IS YOU KNOW, THIS IS A PRETTY
STRAIGHTFORWARD SECURE ISSUE AND WE SIT IN THIS BODY AS THE
BODY THAT HANDLES APPEALS OF THE DETERMINATIONS THAT HAVE
BEEN MADE BY OUR ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW OFFICER HAVE GONE TO THE
COMMISSION. AND SO IN THAT VEIN IN THAT YOU
KNOW, I WANT TO ASK IF WE WERE TO SUPPORT THE APPEAL WE WOULD
HAVE TO HAVE DIFFERENT FINDINGS IN TERMS OF, YOU KNOW,
SUPPORTING A DENIAL. WHAT WOULD THOSE FINDINGS BE?
WHAT COULD WE POSSIBLY SAY IF IT'S YOU KNOW, THE THE YOU
KNOW, FOUNTAIN IS ACTUALLY UNSAFE.
IT HAS BEEN SURROUNDED BY A FENCE BECAUSE WE WANT TO KEEP
PEOPLE FROM YOU KNOW, GETTING A HEARD ON IT.
WHAT WOULD BE THE FINDINGS? LISA GIBSON ENVIRONMENTAL
REVIEW OFFICER THANK YOU FOR THE QUESTION.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR THAT IS THE PURVIEW OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS THE AS YOU AS YOU CORRECTLY NOTED THE HEARING
TODAY IS ON THE ADEQUACY OF THE DEPARTMENT'S DETERMINATION THAT
THIS PROJECT IS EXEMPT FROM SEQUA AND WE PRESENTED IN OUR
RESPONSES TO THE ARGUMENTS MADE BY THE APPELLANT INTO
SUBMITTALS AND WE ACTUALLY THREE SUBMITTALS AND WE'VE HAD
TWO DETAILED RESPONSES STATING OUR REASONS WHY WE FIND THAT
THAT DETERMINATION THAT WE ISSUED OF THE STATUTORY
EXEMPTION IS APPROPRIATE AND THERE HAS NOT BEEN THE
LEGAL BURDEN OF PROOF MET TO SUCCESSFULLY ARGUE THAT THE
CITY DID NOT HAVE SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE TO SUPPORT SUPPORT OUR
DETERMINATION AND CERTAINLY THAT IS OUR RECOMMENDATION THAT
THE BOARD UPHOLD OUR DETERMINATION AT THE FINDINGS
IF IF THIS BOARD DOES VOTE TO SUPPORT THE APPEAL AND RETURN
THIS PROJECT TO THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT FOR FURTHER
ASSESSMENT, THE BOARD WOULD THEN ADOPT FINDINGS STATING THE
BASIS OF THAT DETERMINATION AND WE WOULD THEN REVIEW THOSE
FINDINGS AND DETERMINE THE APPROPRIATE COURSE OF ACTION.
>> THANK YOU. MS. GIBSON AND SO I HAVE NOT
HEARD ANY ARGUMENTS. YOU KNOW, TODAY THAT WOULD
SUPPORT FINDINGS OTHER THAN TO SUPPORT THE DETERMINATION THAT
YOU HAVE MADE NOTWITHSTANDING THE POTENTIAL FOR, YOU KNOW,
ATTACHMENT THAT PEOPLE HAVE TO THIS WHETHER OR NOT, YOU KNOW,
WE YOU KNOW, WANT TO HONOR THE BRUTALIST ARCHITECTURE OR THE
TIME AND SPACE THAT THIS ART WAS DONE OR WHO IS PAYING FOR
IT. I MEAN THE FACT IS IT IS
UNSAFE. WE HAVE DETERMINED THAT WE CAN
ISSUE A STATUTORY EXEMPTION BECAUSE OF THE CIRCUMSTANCES
AND IF WE WERE NOT TO DO THAT WE WOULD RISK THE LIABILITY
THAT COMES WITH IT AND I HAVE NOT HEARD ANY SUPPORTING
EVIDENCE TO HAVE ME VOTE TO TAKE THAT RISK AS A CITY.
>> THANK YOU. ALTHOUGH APPELLANTS WILL HAVE
THREE MINUTES TO CONVINCE YOU AT THE END.
>> SUPERVISOR SAUDER THANK YOU PRESIDENT BENJAMIN AND THANK
YOU FOR THE CONVERSATION. COLLEAGUES THIS SITS
IN DISTRICT THREE BY JUST A FEW FEET.
I HAVE A QUICK QUESTION. YOU KNOW, IF WE WERE TO GO DOWN
THE ROUTE OF RESTORING THIS FOUNTAIN TO ITS ORIGINAL FORM
AND FUNCTION, DO WE HAVE A SENSE OF THE COST OF SUCH AN
ENDEAVOR? >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR SOUDER. YEAH.
IF WE WENT DOWN THE ROUTE OF RESTORING THE FOUNTAIN WE DID A
COST ESTIMATE AND THAT WOULD BE APPROXIMATELY $29 MILLION $29
MILLION. >> THANK YOU.
THAT IS QUITE A PRICE TAG. >> ALL RIGHT.
I KNOW THERE'S MUCH THERE'S MORE STEPS IN THE HEARING SO
I'LL TURN IT BACK OVER. >> PRESIDENT THANK YOU.
PRESENT HOUR. >> ALL RIGHT.
THAT WAS THE PRESENTATION FROM THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT.
I BELIEVE THERE ARE NOW THERE'S NOW A PRESENTATION FROM THE
PROJECT SPONSOR WHICH IS THE DEPARTMENTS AND THEY HAVE UP TO
TEN MINUTES TO PRESENT. >> GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT
MANDELSON AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
MY NAME IS MARY CHU, DIRECTOR OF PUBLIC ART AND CIVIC ART
COLLECTION FOR THE SAN FRANCISCO ARTS COMMISSION.
I'M JOINED TODAY BY RALPH REMINGTON, DIRECTOR OF CULTURAL
AFFAIRS AND ALISON CUMMINGS, SENIOR REGISTRAR.
>> THE EMBARCADERO FOUNTAIN ALSO KNOWN AS AVALON COURT
FOUND FOUNTAIN WAS DESIGNED BY CANADIAN SCULPTOR ARMAND
VAILLANCOURT AND COMPLETED IN 1971 AS PART OF THE LAWRENCE
HOPKINS DESIGN FOR EMBARCADERO PLAZA AND THE LARGER GOLDEN
GATEWAY REDEVELOPMENT PROJECT MANAGED BY THE FORMER SAN
FRANCISCO REDEVELOPMENT AGENCY. >> THE FOUNTAIN IS PART OF THE
CITY'S CIVIC ART COLLECTION AND UNDER THE JURISDICTION OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO ARTS COMMISSION, THE ARTS COMMISSION
AND THE RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT HAVE MANAGED THE
MAINTENANCE AND CARE OF THE FOUNTAIN INCLUDING GRAFFITI
ABATEMENT AND REPAIRS TO THE FOUNTAINS, PUMPS AND MECHANICS
. >> AS PART OF THE PLANNING
PHASE FOR RENOVATION OF THE PARK AT DARA PLAZA AND SUPERMAN
PARK, THE RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT COMPLETED A
CONDITIONS ASSESSMENT OF THE FOUNTAIN AS PART OF THIS
ASSESSMENT AND STRUCTURAL ANALYSIS IDENTIFIED STRUCTURAL
AND SEISMIC RISKS DUE TO CORROSION AND OTHER
MATERIAL FAILURES. >> ON NOVEMBER 3RD OF 2025 THE
ARTS COMMISSION WAS PRESENTED WITH DOCUMENTATION FROM THE
STRUCTURAL ENGINEER THE RECREATION AND PARK DEPARTMENT,
THE DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING INSPECTION AND THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT AND APPROVED REMOVAL AND STORAGE OF THE FOUNTAIN AS
AN EMERGENCY SAFETY MEASURE. >> THE FOUNTAIN WILL BE
DISASSEMBLED AND PLACED INTO STORAGE TO ALLOW FOR FURTHER
INVESTIGATION TO THE EXTENT OF DETERIORATION TO THE STRUCTURE
AS WELL AS CONSIDERING A POSSIBLE RESTORATION REPAIR
RELOCATION. REPURPOSING OR OTHER FUTURE
ACTIONS RELATED TO THE FOUNTAIN.
>> I WILL NOW TURN IT OVER TO JOHN, A GOODWIN PROJECT MANAGER
AT THE RECREATION A PARK DEPARTMENT TO PROVIDE MORE
DETAILED INFORMATION ABOUT THE CONDITIONS, ASSESSMENT
AND MITIGATION MEASURES. >> THANK YOU MARY.
GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT MANDELSON AND MEMBERS OF THE
BOARD. MY NAME IS JOANNA HARRISON
GOODWIN. I'M A PROJECT MANAGER WITH THE
SAN FRANCISCO RECREATION PARK DEPARTMENT.
>> TODAY'S HEARING CONCERNS THE EMERGENCY RESPONSE TO
DOCUMENTED SAFETY HAZARDS AT THE FOUNTAIN.
THE PROJECT IS SEPARATE FROM THE EMBARCADERO PLAZA
AND HUBERMAN PARK RENOVATION PROJECT.
THAT PROJECT IS IN THE PLANNING PHASE AND IN THE OFFICE OF
COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT. >> I AM HERE AS THE PROJECT
SPONSOR TO PROVIDE BACKGROUND INFORMATION AND SUPPORT OF THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT DETERMINATION THAT REMOVAL OF
THE VAILLANCOURT FOUNTAIN IS NECESSARY TO ADDRESS AN
IMMEDIATE THREAT TO PUBLIC HEALTH AND SAFETY.
>> AND THE PROPOSAL THEREFORE QUALIFIES FOR THE EMERGENCY
EMERGENCY STATUTORY EXEMPTION UNDER SEQUA.
I WILL ADDRESS WHAT WE KNOW ABOUT THE CURRENT LIFE SAFETY
HAZARDS PRESENTED BY THE FOUNTAIN.
>> >> THE VAILLANCOURT FOUNTAIN IS NOT A CONVENTIONAL STRUCTURE
BUT A HIGHLY COMPLEX, FULLY INTEGRATED WORK OF ART
AND INFRASTRUCTURE COMPLETED IN 1971.
OVER 50 YEARS AGO SINCE THE FINAL PUMP FAILED IN MAY 20TH
24, THE FOUNTAIN HAS BEEN DRY AND INOPERABLE.
>> THE FOUNTAIN WAS ORIGINALLY DESIGNED TO BE PHYSICALLY
INTERACTIVE, INVITING MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC TO MOVE THROUGH
IT AND UNDER IT. HOWEVER, BASED ON THE
STRUCTURAL DEGRADATION IDENTIFIED IN THE CONDITIONS
ASSESSMENT THE CITY HAS HAD TO PROHIBIT ALL DIRECT PUBLIC
ACCESS FOR SAFETY REASONS AND THAT RESTRICTION REMAINS
IN PLACE. THE FOUNTAIN WAS DESIGNED TO
PUMP APPROXIMATELY 30,000 GALLONS OF WATER PER MINUTE
THROUGH ITS CONCRETE ARMS. >> THESE CANTILEVERED CONCRETE
ARMS WEIGH ROUGHLY TEN TONS EACH.
>> THE OVERALL STRUCTURE WEIGHS APPROXIMATELY 710 TONS.
STRUCTURAL STEEL CORES, WELDED STEEL PLATES, ELECTRICAL
CONDUITS AND MECHANICAL PUMPING RUN THROUGH THE HOLLOW PRECAST
CONCRETE ARMS. MAKING THESE COMPONENTS
INACCESSIBLE FROM THE EXTERIOR. THE MECHANICAL AND ELECTRICAL
SYSTEMS OF THE FOUNTAIN CONNECT TO AN UNDERGROUND VAULT THAT IS
PRONE TO FLOODING AND DOES NOT MEET CURRENT OSHA SAFETY
STANDARDS. FURTHER LIMITING SAFE ACCESS
FOR INSPECTION AND MAINTENANCE. >> THAT FLOODING IS THE RESULT
OF FAILED WATERPROOFING INCLUDING IN THE MEMBRANE
BENEATH THE FOUNTAIN SPACE BASIN WHICH REQUIRES FULL
REPLACEMENT IN 2025. THE CITY RETAINED PAIGE
AND TURNBULL TO PREPARE CONDITIONS ASSESSMENT OF THE
VAILLANCOURT FOUNTAIN WHICH INCLUDED A STRUCTURAL
OBSERVATION AND EVALUATION BY DCA ENGINEERS.
>> ONE OF THE MOST SIGNIFICANT FINDINGS DOCUMENTED BY THE
STRUCTURAL ENGINEERS INVOLVES A CANTILEVERED CONCRETE ARM
WEIGHING APPROXIMATELY TEN TONS THAT IS RESTING ON AN ADJACENT
ARM. >> ACCORDING TO THE ORIGINAL
DESIGN, THESE ARMS WERE INTENDED TO ACT INDEPENDENTLY
AND WERE NOT DESIGNED TO TRANSFER LOAD TO ONE ANOTHER.
THE FACT THAT ONE ARM IS BEARING ON ANOTHER DEMONSTRATES
THAT THE STRUCTURE IS NOT BEHAVING AS DESIGNED.
THIS CONDITION REFLECTS AN EXISTING STRUCTURAL FAILURE
WITH FORCES BEING TRANSFERRED TO ELEMENTS THAT WERE NEVER
ENGINEERED TO CARRY THEM. >> THE CITY ALSO CONDUCTED
NONDESTRUCTIVE TESTING THROUGH GROUND PENETRATING RADAR TO
BETTER UNDERSTAND THE FOUNTAIN'S AS BUILT CONDITION.
THAT TESTING CONFIRMED THAT THE FOUNTAIN DOES NOT FULLY CONFORM
TO ITS ORIGINAL DESIGN DRAWINGS.
ENGINEERS IDENTIFIED MISSING REINFORCING STEEL IN THE BACK
WALL THAT WAS INTENDED TO BE ANCHORED TO THE FOUNDATION.
IN ADDITION, STRUCTURAL ENGINEERS CONFIRM THAT AT LEAST
ONE POST TENSIONING ROD AN ELEMENT ORIGINALLY INSTALLED AS
PART OF THE FOUNTAIN STRUCTURAL SYSTEM AND CRITICAL TO
MAINTAINING TENSION AND RESISTING BENDING IN THE
CANTILEVERED ARMS IS NOW MISSING THE STRUCTURAL REPORT
INDICATES THAT THE ABSENCE OF THIS ROD REDUCES THE LOAD
CARRYING CAPACITY OF THE AFFECTED ARM BY APPROXIMATELY
25%. >> DCI ENGINEERS FURTHER
CONCLUDED THAT EVEN UNDER IDEAL MATERIAL CONDITIONS MEANING
ASSUMING THAT THE STRUCTURE HAD EXPERIENCED NO CORROSION
AND ALL MATERIALS WERE PERFORMING AS ORIGINALLY
INTENDED, THE FOUNTAIN DOES NOT MEET CURRENT SEISMIC OR SAFETY
STANDARDS. THEIR ANALYSIS INDICATES THAT
UNDER BOTH DESIGN BASIS AND MAXIMUM CONSIDERED
EARTHQUAKE LOADS THE STRUCTURE IS LIKELY TO YIELD OR DEFORM.
THESE CONCLUSIONS ARE BASED ON STRUCTURAL MODELING USING
ORIGINAL DESIGN ASSUMPTIONS AND DO NOT ACCOUNT FOR THE
ADDITIONAL LOSS OF CAPACITY CAUSED BY CORROSION AND MISSING
ELEMENTS. >> THE STRUCTURAL REPORT ALSO
EXPLAINS THAT THESE RISKS ARE EXACERBATED BY THE FAULT
AND LOCATION ON UNCONSOLIDATED FILL AND BAY MUD WHICH IS KNOWN
TO AMPLIFY SEISMIC FORCES AND INCREASE LIQUEFACTION
POTENTIAL AND REDUCE OVERALL SEISMIC PERFORMANCE.
>> THE STRUCTURAL EVALUATION ALSO EXPLAINED THE
DETERIORATION OF THE FOUNTAIN IS ONGOING.
ENGINEERS OBSERVED THAT INTERNAL TUBES ARE HEAVILY
CORRODED LARGELY DUE TO PROLONGED IMMERSION IN WATER
DURING THE FOUNTAINS DECADES OF OPERATION.
COMBINED WITH CONTINUED EXPOSURE TO SAN FRANCISCO'S
HUMID MARINE ENVIRONMENT, THE REPORT STATES THAT THIS
CORROSION LIKELY COMPROMISES THE STRUCTURAL INTEGRITY
AND LOAD BEARING CAPACITY OF THESE STEEL ELEMENTS.
>> IMPORTANTLY, DCA ENGINEERS NOTED THAT ADDITIONAL CORROSION
OF INTERNAL STEEL PLATES AND CONNECTORS IS LIKELY
PRESENT BUT CANNOT BE CONFIRMED WITHOUT DISASSEMBLY BECAUSE
THESE ELEMENTS ARE CONCEALED WITHIN THE CONCRETE.
FOLLOWING ISSUE ISSUANCE OF THE CONDITIONS REPORT STARTING
IN JUNE OF 2025, THE RECREATION AND PARK DEPARTMENT IMPLEMENTED
INTERIM MEASURES TO RESTRICT PUBLIC ACCESS TO THE FOUNTAIN
INCLUDING FENCING, MESH BARRIERS AND WARNING SIGNAGE.
DESPITE THESE EFFORTS, FENCING AND MESH BARRIERS HAVE BEEN
BREACHED AND STAFF HAVE DOCUMENTED EVIDENCE OF PEOPLE
SLEEPING INSIDE THE CONCRETE TUBES.
THE FOUNTAIN IS LOCATED AT ONE OF THE CITY'S MOST HEAVILY
TRAFFICKED CIVIC INTERSECTIONS ADJACENT TO MARKET STREET
AND THE FERRY BUILDING AND IT IS FREQUENTLY THE SIZE OF LARGE
PUBLIC GATHERINGS, DEMONSTRATIONS AND PROTESTS.
GIVEN ITS SIZE, CONFIGURATION AND LOCATION, IT IS EXTREMELY
DIFFICULT TO RELIABLY EXCLUDE THE PUBLIC THROUGH FENCING
ALONE. >> IN OCTOBER 2025 THE
DEPARTMENT OF BUILDING INSPECTION INDEPENDENTLY
REVIEWED THE CONDITIONS ASSESSMENT CONDUCTED A SITE
INSPECTION AND ISSUED A WRITTEN LETTER CONFIRMING CORROSION
AND MATERIAL DEGRADATION AND DIRECTING THAT THE SITE
REMAIN VACATED AND THAT SECURITY BE STRENGTHENED UNTIL
HAZARDOUS CONDITIONS ARE ABATED .
>> BASED ON THESE DOCUMENTED CONDITIONS, THE RECREATION
AND PARK DEPARTMENT DETERMINED THAT THE FOUNTAIN PRESENTS A
PUBLIC HEALTH AND SAFETY HAZARD IN ITS CURRENT CONDITION.
>> THE DEPARTMENT DETERMINED THAT THE SAFEST WAY TO CONDUCT
THE NECESSARY FURTHER INVESTIGATION CONSIDER POSSIBLE
REPAIRS OR POTENTIAL HAZARD ABATEMENT IS TO REMOVE THE
FOUNTAIN FROM THE PUBLIC PLAZA AND CONDUCT THESE
INVESTIGATIONS OFFSITE. >> IN SHORT, THE FOUNTAIN IS A
710 TON CONCRETE STRUCTURE BUILT ON UNCONSOLIDATED FILL
AND BAY MUD AND IS NOT SUPPORTED BY DEEP FOUNDATION OR
PILE SYSTEM. >> ITS TEN TON CANTILEVERED
ARMS ARE HOLLOW TUBES LINED WITH STRUCTURAL STEEL THAT IS
CONSTANTLY EXPOSED TO A CORROSIVE MARINE ENVIRONMENT
AND IS INACCESSIBLE FROM THE EXTERIOR.
THIS IS NOT A SIMPLE MAINTENANCE ISSUE.
INSTEAD INTERNAL DETERIORATION IS ONGOING BECAUSE BECAUSE OF
THE FOUNTAINS LOCATION AND THE MATERIALS USED TO CONSTRUCT IT
DISASSEMBLE AND REMOVAL ARE NECESSARY TO REMOVE THE
IMMEDIATE PUBLIC SAFETY RISK AND TO ALLOW THE CITY TO FULL
AND TO ALLOW THE CITY TO FULLY UNDERSTAND THE EXTENT OF
DETERIORATION CORROSION, HAZARDOUS MATERIALS
AND STRUCTURAL FAILURE OF THE FOUNTAIN.
>> DELAYING ACTION WOULD ALLOW DETERIORATION TO CONTINUE
AND WOULD PROLONG EXPOSURE OF THE PUBLIC TO KNOWN HAZARDS
INCLUDING ASBESTOS AND LEAD PAINT PAINT USED IN THE
FOUNTAIN'S CONSTRUCTION. >> THE SECURE STORAGE ALLOWS
FOR CONSIDERATION OF POSSIBLE FUTURE OPTIONS TO RESTORE,
REPAIR, RELOCATE AND OR REPURPOSE THE FOUNTAIN.
>> TAKEN TOGETHER THE DOCUMENTED STRUCTURAL FAILURES
EXPERT ANALYSIS II CONCURRENCE ONGOING ENVIRONMENTAL
DEGRADATION AND REPEATED PUBLIC INTRUSION CONSTITUTE TO SUDDEN
AND ESCALATING LIFE SAFETY EMERGENCY.
>> WE RESPECTFULLY ASK THE BOARD TO UPHOLD THE SEQUEL
DETERMINATION AND DENY THE APPEAL.
>> AS A REMINDER, JEFF BRINK OF DCI ENGINEERS IS ALSO HERE TO
HELP ANSWER ANY QUESTIONS. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. COLLEAGUES, DO YOU HAVE ANY
QUESTIONS FOR THE DEPARTMENT'S ?
>> LOOKS LIKE WE DO NOT. AND IN THAT CASE WE'LL INVITE
MEMBERS OF PUBLIC WHO WANT TO SPEAK IN OPPOSITION TO THE
APPEAL AND IN SUPPORT OF THE PROJECT TO LINE UP.
YOU WILL HAVE TWO MINUTES EACH. MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL OUR FIRST SPEAKER? >> COME ON UP TO THE PODIUM.
WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES AT FIRST.
YOU YOU WILL HEAR A SOFT BELL THAT WILL TELL YOU THAT YOU GOT
30S TO FINISH UP YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR FIRST SPEAKER.
>> >> GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS DIANNA TAYLOR AND I'M A RESIDENT OF DISTRICT
THREE LIVING VERY CLOSE TO SUPERMAN PARK AND THE
EMBARCADERO PLAZA. TODAY I'M REPRESENTING THE
BARBARY COAST NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION AND THE NEARLY 5000
PEOPLE WHO LIVE AND WORK WITHIN A SHORT WALK OF THE PARK
AND THE PLAZA. OUR NEIGHBORHOOD HAS LIVED
IN THE SHADOW OF THE FREEWAY FOR OVER 40 YEARS AND HAS BEEN
AN ACTIVE PARTICIPANT IN THE IMPROVEMENT OF WHAT WE CONSIDER
OUR BACKYARD. FOR EXAMPLE, WE LED THE
FUNDRAISING FOR A CHILDREN'S PLAYGROUND THAT IS IN CONSTANT
USE. AND RECENTLY WE HAVE
PARTICIPATED IN EXTENSIVE MEETINGS AND OUTREACH TO OUR
NEIGHBORS THROUGH SURVEYS, COMMUNITY MEETINGS, DESIGN
PLANNING THAT BADLY NEEDED NEEDED RENOVATION OF THE
EMBARCADERO PLAZA. AS STATED IN OUR LETTER TO THE
BOARD, BECKNER BELIEVES THAT AMPLE OPPORTUNITY FOR BONA FIDE
COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT ON THIS OVERALL RENOVATION PROJECT
INCLUDING ITS PUBLIC PRIVATE PARTNERSHIP ASPECTS AND ON THE
FATE OF THE FOUNTAIN SPECIFICALLY HAS BEEN PROVIDED
BY BOTH DEPARTMENT OF REC AND PARK AND THE ARTS
COMMISSION. ANY ALLEGATION THAT ADEQUATE
OPPORTUNITY FOR SUCH ENGAGEMENT HAS NOT OCCURRED IS NOT
FACTUALLY SUPPORTED AND SHOULD NOT BE A FACTOR IN YOUR
DECISION ON THIS APPEAL. >> IN CONCLUSION, WHILE WE ARE
SENSITIVE TO THE ISSUES RAISED BY DOKO MOMO TO SAVE OUR
ARTISTIC HISTORY, THE FACT IS THAT FUNDS NECESSARY TO MAKE
THE FOUNTAINS SAFE AND OPERATIONAL PROBABLY DID
NOT EXIST. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HI, I'M ERIN FISHER.
>> I LIVE IN THE GATEWAY APARTMENTS AND BECAUSE OF THAT
I WALK BY THE FOUNTAIN AT LEAST A HALF A DOZEN TIMES A WEEK
PROBABLY MORE. >> I'M ALWAYS STRUCK BY HOW IT
DOESN'T FIT. AND OF COURSE THERE'S A REASON
FOR THAT. IT WAS DESIGNED FOR A
COMPLETELY DIFFERENT ENVIRONMENT.
SO WHEN I BRING PEOPLE FROM OUT OF TOWN AND THEY HAVE THE SAME
REACTION I GO THROUGH THE WHOLE EXPLANATION OF HOW IT CAME
ABOUT. >> PARKING OR FREEWAY WAS TORN
DOWN AND SO ON. I THINK IT NO LONGER MAKES
SENSE TO BE THERE EVEN IF IT'S HISTORICAL.
SO I WOULD ENCOURAGE THE BOARD TO HAVE IT TAKEN AWAY SO WE CAN
PROCEED WITH THE BEAUTIFICATION OF THE PLAZA.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS MICHELLE HENNESSEY AND I LIVE AT THE GATEWAY
APARTMENTS AND THAT'S RIGHT NEXT DOOR TO THE BOURBON POT.
>> AND I'M ALSO ON THE BOARD OF THE BARBARY COAST NEIGHBORHOOD
ASSOCIATION. >> THE FOUNTAIN NEEDS TO BE
REMOVED IN ORDER TO OPEN UP THE AREA FOR THE REDEVELOPMENT OF
THE SUBURBAN PARK. WE NEED TO BRING MORE
ACTIVITIES TO THE AREA FOR OUR RESIDENTS AND VISITORS ALIKE.
THE EAST SIDE OF THE EMBARCADERO WHERE THE FERRY
BUILDING IS OVER THE LAST 20 YEARS HAS TOTALLY REINVENTED
ITSELF AND MORE RESTAURANTS, MORE PEOPLE ARE GOING TO THAT
AREA BUT NOT ON THE WEST SIDE WHICH IS WHERE THE PARK IS
IN ORDER TO BRING MORE ECONOMIC BENEFIT TO THE CITY.
WE REALLY NEED TO IMPROVE THE PARK AND BE ABLE TO BRING MORE
PEOPLE DOWN. >> THAT WILL ALSO BRING IT INTO
THE THE PARK AREA BUT THAT ALSO INTO THE FINANCIAL DISTRICT.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS MARILYN TREMBLAY. I AM THE PRESIDENT OF THE
GATEWAY TENANTS ASSOCIATION. >> IT WAS VERY IMPORTANT FOR US
TO FIGURE OUT AND LET OUR PEOPLE KNOW WHAT THE GATEWAY.
SO AS A REMINDER, WHAT IS THE GATEWAY?
WELL, IT'S A HUGE COMMUNITY. IT'S A VILLAGE.
WE BASICALLY HAVE 1254 UNITS SPREAD OUT BETWEEN FOUR
BUILDINGS AND 58 TOWNHOUSE. WE OCCUPY THE BLOCKS FROM
BATTERY TO DRUM AND WASHINGTON TO JACKSON STREET.
SO WE ARE LITERALLY A VILLAGE. AND IT WAS IMPORTANT TO GET THE
OPINION AND TO LET THE PEOPLE OF OUR VILLAGE KNOW WHAT WAS
GOING ON. ON TOP OF IT WE ARE RENT
CONTROL FOR YOU THAT DO NOT KNOW.
SO WHAT DID WE DO TO SPREAD THE WORD?
WELL WE SENT EMAILS AND WE NOTIFIED FIRED OUR RESIDENTS AS
EARLY AS FEBRUARY 25 OF THE PROJECT.
AND WE ENCOURAGE THEM TO ATTEND ALL MEETINGS.
FILL IN ALL SURVEYS AND EXPRESS THEMSELVES WITHOUT TAKING
POSITION WHETHER WE WERE FOR THE VANCOUVER FOUNTAIN OR NOT.
THE MEETING IN RESPONSE THAT WE GOT WERE A RESOUNDING SUCCESS
ALTHOUGH WE WERE NOT ABLE AND WE ARE NOT ABLE AS THE
GATEWAY TENANTS ASSOCIATION TO REACH ALL OUR RESIDENTS.
WE UTILIZE FLIERS IN THE ELEVATORS SOCIAL MEDIA PLATFORM
SUCH AS FACEBOOK AND NEXT DOOR. >> AND THE PROJECT IS MET WITH
HUGE ENTHUSIASM AND EVERYONE IS LOOKING FORWARD.
WHILE MANY ARE LOOKING FORWARD TO THE OPENING OF THAT AREA.
AGAIN RECOGNIZING HOW IMPORTANT THE FOUNTAIN THE VERY COOL
FOUNTAIN WAS AND SERVED ITS TIME.
>> THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER MR. PRESIDENT MEMBER FOR THE BOARD
CITY STAFF. MY NAME IS ALEC BASH AND VICE
PRESIDENT OF THE GATEWAY TENANTS ASSOCIATION ALSO CHAIR
OF ITS SAFETY SECURITY COMMITTEE AND CO-CHAIR OF THE
BARBARY COAST NEIGHBORHOOD ASSOCIATION SAFETY COMMITTEE.
I'M ONE OF MANY PEOPLE IN OUR AREA WHO HAVE BEEN ACTIVELY
PARTICIPATING IN THE PLANNING FOR THE RENOVATION AND MERGER
OF SUPERMAN PARK AND BACKYARD PLAZA.
AND IN MY EARLIER DAYS I ACTUALLY CREATED THE FOOTAGE
SHOOT COURT PROCESS AND RESEARCH ENVIRONMENTAL
REVIEW OFFICER FOR SIX YEARS. SO I UNDERSTAND THE PROCESS WE
ARE GOING THROUGH NOW. THIS LAST PHASE OF THE VINE
COURT FELT IS ITS MOST TROUBLING.
IT'S CALLED CELEBRITY NATURE HAS LED TO EXTENSIVE EVALUATION
OF ITS PHYSICAL CONDITION AND WE NOW WILL KNOW WHAT THE
HAZARDS ARE ASSOCIATED WITH IT. IT'S AN ATTRACTIVE NUISANCE, A
DANGEROUS CONDITION ON CITY PROPERTY.
ITS UNIQUE NATURE WITH HIGH OVERLOOKS LARGE WATERSPOUT
AND OPEN WALKABLE CONCRETE PADS OVER THE DRY WATER BASINS MAY
PARTICULARLY ATTRACT CHILDREN INTO THE SITE AND POSE A RISK
TO THEIR SAFETY. IF YOU DETERIORATE TO
CONGESTION AND IN MANY PLACES FAILING CONCRETE STEEL
AND STRUCTURE EXACERBATES THESE CONCERNS TO SAY NOTHING THE
KNOWN PRESENCE OF HAZARDOUS MATERIALS THROUGH YOUR ENTRY IS
READILY FORESEEABLE BY THE BY THE CITY AND EMERGENCY
EXCLUSION FROM FREQUENT IS VERY APPROPRIATE.
RENOVATING AND MERGING SUGARMAN PARK AND THE EMBARCADERO PLAZA
ARE TO CREATE A TRULY GRAND WATERFRONT PARK IS SUCH A
WORTHY GOAL FOR THE CITY. THE DARLING COURT FOUND THAT
MANY OF US LOVED WHEN IT WAS SUCH A BRILLIANT CONCEPT
IN CONJUNCTION WITH THE EMBARCADERO FREEWAY IS NOW AN
ANACHRONISM. IT DESERVES A BETTER FATE.
IT FILLS MOST OF THE NARROW NECK BETWEEN THE TWO PARKS.
AND IF IT STAYS IT WOULD PREVENT I BELIEVE, AN
INSURMOUNTABLE HURDLE TO ANY SUCCESSFUL COMBINATION
RENOVATION OF THOSE MERGED PARKS.
>> THANK YOU. AND I URGE YOU TO REJECT THE
APPEAL. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT
MANAGEMENT MEMBERS OF THE BOARD .
>> I'M JOHN LOFTUS AND I WAS BORN AND RAISED HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. FOR THE PAST ROUGHLY 12 YEARS I
WORKED AS A DIRECTOR OF SAFETY AND SECURITY FOR BIXBY,
FORMERLY KNOWN AS BOSTON PROPERTIES AND OWNERS
AND OPERATORS OF THE EMBARCADERO CENTER.
>> PRIOR TO MY EMPLOYMENT WITH THE XP, I SERVED FOUR WITH THE
S.F. P.D. FOR 32 YEARS. >> I THINK I THINK IT'S
IMPORTANT THAT I SHARE WITH YOU MY EXPERIENCE WITH THE
STRUCTURE AS YOUR BOARD CONSIDERS THE ISSUE OF SAFETY
AT VAILLANCOURT FOUNTAIN. >> IN THE PAST 15 YEARS THE
SECURITY TEAM AT XP HAS RESPONDED TO NUMEROUS CALLS FOR
SERVICE. >> VAILLANCOURT.
THESE CALLS HAVE ORIGINATED FROM AN ARRAY OF SOURCES
INCLUDING OUR CLIENTS THE TENANTS THAT EMBARCADERO
VISITORS TO THE PLAZA AND FOUNTAIN TOURISTS AND OUR
JANITORIAL STAFF WHO ARE TASKED WITH CLEANING THE AREA AROUND
THE FOUNTAIN AND PLAZA. >> AS A RESULT OF THESE CALLS
NEARLY 500 INCIDENT REPORTS HAVE BEEN GENERATED.
THESE REPORTS DOCUMENT A WIDE VARIETY OF SAFETY AND SECURITY
ISSUES OCCURRING AT THE FOUNTAIN.
>> AMONG THE REPORTED INCIDENTS CONCERNS RELATED TO THE
UNHOUSED POPULATION ENCAMPMENTS, DISTURBANCES
AND THE LIKE MEDICAL CALLS, VANDALISM, THEFTS, ASSAULT
CASES, ROBBERIES, THEFTS, SUSPICIOUS PERSONS HAZARDS,
SKATEBOARDING AND SLIPS AND FALLS WITH INJURY.
SO ALTHOUGH IT'S UNFORTUNATE THE 55 YEAR OLD FOUNTAIN HAS
BECOME SOMEWHAT OF AN ATTRACTIVE NUISANCE AND DOES
REPRESENT A SAFETY RISK. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER, PLEASE.
IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL AND IN SUPPORT OF THE PROJECT.
>> YES, GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS DAN RABINOWITZ.
I AM A PROUD AND ENGAGED RESIDENT OF DISTRICT THREE.
AND THANK YOU FOR THE OPPORTUNITY TO BE HERE.
>> I WOULD MAKE TWO OBSERVATIONS WHICH I THINK ARE
PERTINENT TO WHAT'S GOING ON IN TODAY'S HEARING.
FIRST IS THAT THE ULTIMATE FATE AND THE ULTIMATE PERHAPS THE
ULTIMATE PLACEMENT OF THE FOUNTAIN IS NOT ACTUALLY WHAT'S
BEFORE THE BOARD TODAY THE DECISION OF THE ARTS COMMISSION
WHICH IS THE BODY HAVING ACTUAL DIRECT JURISDICTION OVER THE
FOUNTAIN AS A PIECE OF PUBLIC ART WAS THAT THE FOUNTAIN
SHOULD BE REMOVED TO STORAGE PENDING FURTHER CONSIDERATION
OF WHAT ITS ULTIMATE DESTINATION MIGHT BE.
GIVEN THE ENORMOUS EXPENSE THAT WOULD BE ENTAILED BY TRYING TO
RECONSTRUCT IT IN PLACE AS A DISTRICT THREE RESIDENT WHO IS
FREQUENTLY IN EMBARCADERO PLAZA AND SUE BEERMAN PARK WHILE I AM
NOT A STRUCTURAL ENGINEER THERE IS NO REASON THAT I CAN SEE
HAVING LOOKED AT THE FOUNTAIN CAREFULLY TO DOUBT THE
THOUGHTFUL DETAILED ENGINEERING ASSESSMENTS FROM MULTIPLE
SOURCES ABOUT THE POTENTIAL STRUCTURAL HAZARDS ABOUT THE
PRESENCE OF HAZARDOUS MATERIALS THERE AND ABOUT THE FALLEN
STATE OF DESOLATE TUDE INTO WHICH THE FOUNTAIN HAS COME
UNDER THESE CIRCUMSTANCES. IT I WOULD RESPECTFULLY URGE
THAT THE ONLY COURSE THAT MAKES SENSE FOR THIS BOARD WOULD BE
TO REJECT THE APPEAL AND TO ALLOW THE REMOVAL OF THE
FOUNTAIN PENDING ITS FURTHER ASSESSMENT AND ULTIMATE
DESTINATION. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS TAD SKY.
I BECAME A STREET ARTIST IN THE EARLY 70S AND STARTED WORKING
AT THE PLAZA IN 1976 SO WE HAD A LOT OF FUN WITH THAT FOUNTAIN
. YOU COULD GO ON TOP OF IT,
SMOKE A JOINT. THE POLICE WOULDN'T SEE YOU
COMING. YOU COULD WALK UNDER IT.
IT WAS IT WAS A GREAT JOY. OVER THE YEARS I DID SEE MANY
TIMES IT WAS TURNED OFF AND AND WHEN THE WATER WASN'T RUNNING
IT REALLY WASN'T THAT PRETTY. >> AND THEN OF COURSE AFTER THE
EARTHQUAKE WHEN THE FREEWAY CAME DOWN, PART OF ITS PURPOSE
WAS GONE. >> IT WAS BIG.
AND NOW IRONICALLY THE HUGE SIZE WHICH MASKED THE FREEWAY
IS NOW PART OF ITS PROBLEM BECAUSE IF YOU WANT TO JOIN
THOSE TWO PARKS TOGETHER WHICH I THINK IS A GREAT IDEA THE
FOUNTAIN JUST DOESN'T FIT IN THERE.
FURTHERMORE OF COURSE IT WOULDN'T BE ADA COMPLIANT
AND THE MATERIALS THERE ARE NOT TOO HEALTHY.
>> BUT IF THIS WERE PROPOSED TODAY FOR YOU FOLKS YOU WOULD
REJECT IT IS NOT SAFE. THOSE PADS THAT YOU HAVE TO
WALK ON UNDERNEATH ARE SLIPPERY WHEN THE WATER IS RUNNING
AND THAT'S A PROBLEM. SO I THINK IT'S TIME FOR IT TO
GO BECAUSE PROGRESS SHOULDN'T BE HALTED OR HELD HOSTAGE TO
NOSTALGIA OR TO HISTORY. I MEAN NORMALLY AS AN ARTIST I
WOULD BE IN FAVOR OF KEEPING IT AND IF IT WERE SMALLER I'D SAY
YEAH, LET'S LET'S FIT IT IN SOMEHOW.
BUT RIGHT NOW IT BLOCKS THE TWO.
THAT AREA OF THE PLAZA IS DEAD. PEOPLE DON'T GO THERE SO PLEASE
DO WHAT YOU HAVE TO DO. IF IF IT CAN BE STORED
SOMEWHERE AND REPURPOSED AND REIMAGINED SOMEWHERE ON THE
SOUTHEAST PART OF THE BAY THERE'S A LOT OF WATERFRONT
THERE. IT WOULD LOOK GREAT.
BUT WHERE IT IS NOW I DON'T THINK IT WORKS TOO WELL.
AND SADLY THE ARTISTS WILL BE DISAPPOINTED BUT MAYBE IT CAN
BE PUT SOMEWHERE ELSE AND HAVE A SECOND LIFE.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> MY NAME IS JACK AND I MAY BE
SPEAKING OUT OF TURN. I APOLOGIZE.
BUT I SUPPORT THE FOUNTAIN. >> AND IS THIS NOT THE RIGHT
TIME TO SPEAK? THIS IS FOR SPEAKERS
IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL AND IN SUPPORT OF THE PROJECT
AND I'M GOING TO COME BACK LATER AS POSSIBLY WAS THAT
ALREADY DONE? WE'VE ALREADY HAD THE PUBLIC
COMMENT. YOU'RE INTERESTED
IN SUPERVISING. PERFECT.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR COMING DOWN
TODAY. WELCOME.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS CHAIRMAN WOMAN JOEL KOPPEL,
DISTRICT FOUR RESIDENT. NOT ONLY DID THESE DOWNTOWN
BUILDINGS KEEP ME EMPLOYED AS AN ELECTRICIAN FOR ABOUT 20
YEARS MY MY CAMPAIGN OF RECENT AS A GOVERNMENTAL AFFAIRS
DIRECTOR FOR OUR ELECTRICAL CONTRACTORS ASSOCIATION IS
DOWNTOWN REVITALIZATION. SPENDING TIME ON THE COMMISSION
WITHIN COMMISSIONER MELGAR VERY FAMILIAR WITH OUR VERY ROCK
SOLID ROBUST ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REVIEW STAFF.
AND WANT TO THANK AGAIN SUPERVISOR MELGAR FOR BRINGING
UP JUST THE SIMPLE FACT FINDINGS.
YOU CANNOT IGNORE THE FACT THAT A REPORT SAYS THAT THIS
FOUNTAIN IS NOT COMPLIANT WITH CURRENT SEISMIC AND SAFETY
STANDARDS. >> OKAY.
AND JUST SPEAKING ABOUT LAND USE, YOU KNOW DOWNTOWN IS A
VERY IMPORTANT PART OF OUR CITY VENICE AND MARKET IS A GATEWAY.
MORE IMPORTANTLY, THE FERRY BUILDING SECTOR IS IS A GATEWAY
WITH TRANSIT WITH PARKS. WE EVEN HAVE, YOU KNOW, FERRIES
COMING OVER FROM THE NORTH AND EAST BAY WATERWAY TO ENTER
OUR CITY. I WAS DOWN THERE THIS WEEKEND,
HAD SOME GLUTEN FREE PASTRIES AT MARIPOSA BAKERY AND THE
FERRY BUILDING WALKS MY WAY TO HILLSDALE AND WATCHED THE 49TH
GAME AND JUST AGAIN SAW WHAT COULD BE A LITTLE MORE PRETTIER
OF A PLAZA TO GREET PEOPLE THAT COME INTO SAN FRANCISCO.
WE HAVE PEOPLE THAT WORK IN OFFICE BUILDINGS TAKING
LUNCH. THEY GO TO COFFEE.
THESE BUILDINGS PUT PEOPLE LIKE ME TO WORK.
THEY BRING PEOPLE INTO THE CITY, GIVE THEM JOBS
AND SUPPORT ALL THE RETAIL, ALL THE BARS, THE RESTAURANTS, THE
HOTELS AND THEY KEEP THIS CITY ALIVE.
SO WE NEED TO PRIORITIZE REVITALIZING DOWNTOWN.
JUST LOOK AT WHAT'S HAPPENED. WE REMODELED ONE SANSOM.
IT'S BECOME A HOTSPOT. IT'S BRINGING PEOPLE DOWN TO
THE SAN FRANCISCO DOWNTOWN. THE STREETS ARE CLEANER.
IT FEELS SAFER DOWN THERE. THIS IS JUST ANOTHER STEP WE
CAN TAKE TO BEAUTIFY A BIG GATEWAY INTO SAN FRANCISCO.
SO DENY THE APPEAL TODAY. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF
THE CHAMBER BEFORE THIS GENTLEMAN BEGINS TO SPEAK WHO
WOULD LIKE TO SPEAK IN OPPOSITION TO AN APPEAL TO
THE APPEAL AND IN SUPPORT OF THE PROJECT?
IF SO, PLEASE COME ON OVER AND STAND ON YOUR RIGHT HAND
SIDE OF THE CHAMBER PLEASE. OTHERWISE THIS MAY BE OUR LAST
SPEAKER. WELCOME, SIR.
THANK YOU. DOWNTOWN DAVE HERE TO OPPOSE
THE FOUNTAIN. IT'S GOING TO COST A LOT OF
MONEY. WE SHOULD GET RID OF ALL THE
FANS IN TOWN. WHO NEEDS THEM?
AND WHILE WE'RE AT IT, LET'S BRING IN MORE BILLBOARDS, MORE
ADVERTISING. CHOP DOWN ALL THE TREES.
THEY'RE DANGEROUS. THEY COST MONEY.
AND I'M HAPPY TO SUPPORT MY FUDDY DUDDY NEIGHBORS.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. ALL RIGHT.
MR. PRESIDENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IN UP IN SUPPORT OF THE PROJECT AND IN
OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL IS CLOSE.
AND THEN I THINK LASTLY WE INVITE THE APPELLANTS UP TO
PRESENT A REBUTTAL ARGUMENT FOR UP TO THREE MINUTES.
>> HELLO. SUSAN BRANDT HOLLEY AGAIN.
IF I COULD HAVE MY OTHER 45 SECONDS THAT WOULD BE GREAT.
>> I DON'T KNOW IF THAT'S POSSIBLE.
ALL THE COMMENTS YOU JUST HEARD IN OPPOSITION I THINK THERE
MIGHT HAVE BEEN ONE THAT TALKED ABOUT THE ISSUE OF SOME KIND OF
DANGER OR PROBLEM WITH THE FOUNTAIN BUT NO ONE TALKED
ABOUT EMERGENCY AND MOST MOST OF THOSE COMMENTS THOSE
THOUGHTFUL COMMENTS WERE OPINIONS ABOUT THE MERITS OF
THE PROJECT ITSELF WHICH IS NOT BEFORE YOU AS YOU KNOW, WE DID
HEAR THE REC AND PARK STAFF ADMIT THAT THE FUNDING TO TO
DISASSEMBLE AND RELOCATE THE FOUNTAIN INTO STORAGE IS PART
OF THE IT'S GOING TO BE FUNDED BY THE PLAZA PROJECT IT'S PART
OF THE PLAZA PROJECT. >> SO STARTING OUT OF THE GATE
HERE, THIS IS NOT A PROJECT SEPARATE FROM THE PLAZA PROJECT
THAT'S SO LOGICAL AND APPARENT AND ADMITTED ONCE AGAIN BY THE
FACT THAT IT'S BEING FUNDED AS PART OF THAT PROJECT.
SO THAT'S A PROBLEM WE'VE WE'VE HEARD ABOUT THERE HAVE BEEN
PROBLEMS FOR 15 YEARS WITH THE WITH THEIR FOUNTAIN.
THAT'S NOT ANYTHING THAT'S NEW. IT'S NOT AN EMERGENCY THAT
WOULD QUALIFY FOR A SECRET EXEMPTION.
WE HEARD ABOUT THE THE THE GOAL OF THIS QUOTE UNQUOTE PROJECT
IS TO ELIMINATE RISK AND FACILITATE INVESTIGATION
FOR THE PROJECT. THAT'S NOT AN EMERGENCY.
>> AND IMPORTANTLY, THERE'S A WAY TO ABATE THE PROBLEM FROM
EVERYTHING WE'VE HEARD. IF THE FOUNTAIN WAS TO BE
REMOVED THERE WOULD STILL NEED TO BE A FENCE AROUND THE SITE
WHERE THE FOUNTAIN WAS TO PROTECT THE PUBLIC.
THE ANY DANGER COULD BE ABATED. AND IT HASN'T BEEN LOOKED AT.
IT SHOULD AND IT SHOULD BE WITH ADEQUATE FENCING AND SECURITY.
WE PUT IN OUR PRESENTATION THAT WE FIGURED OUT AT A FAIR WAGE
SECURITY COULD BE ACCOMPLISHED BY I THINK IT'S $400,000 FOR 18
MONTHS. SO YES, PROTECT THE PUBLIC IF
THERE IS SOME PROBLEM BUT THERE IS NO EMERGENCY THAT'S BEEN
DEMONSTRATED TO YOU TODAY AND THAT'S WHAT'S REQUIRED TO
COMPLETELY AVOID SECURE THE FACT THAT IT WASN'T NOW BUILT
AS IT WAS PLANNED FOR 50 YEARS AGO.
THAT'S NOT AN EMERGENCY EITHER .
THERE WAS MENTION OF THE DCI ENGINEER WHO IT WAS I HEARD SAY
WAS HERE AND HE MADE NO RECOMMENDATION AS TO REMOVAL
AND IN FACT STATED AS WE HAVE ON PAGE 21 OF OUR PRESENTATION
THAT IT'S EXTREMELY HAZARDOUS TO DISASSEMBLE THE PHONE
AND WOULD BE SIGNIFICANT SAFETY HAZARDS IN DOING SO.
SO YOU HAVE $4 MILLION AS OPPOSED TO THE SMALLER AMOUNT
TO DO OTHER ABATEMENT AND THIS IS NOT A SEPARATE PROJECT
AND I'D BE GLAD TO PROVIDE FINDINGS FOR THIS BOARD
IN DRAFT IF YOU WOULD BE INTERESTED TO GRANT THIS
APPEAL. >> THANK YOU.
>> ALL RIGHT. COLLEAGUES, THIS PUBLIC HEARING
HAS BEEN HELD AND IS NOW FILED AND NOW WE WILL CONSIDER
WHETHER TO AFFIRM OR CONDITIONALLY REVERSE THE
APPROVAL OF THE PLANNING COMMISSION.
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU PRESIDENT MELMAN AND THANK YOU
EVERYONE FOR COMING TODAY. APPRECIATE ALL THE CONVERSATION
THAT THIS HAS IGNITED AND THROUGHOUT THIS PROCESS I
HAVE HEARD FROM MANY WHO HAVE SHARED FOND MEMORIES OF
MOUNTAIN SOME FROM DECADES AGO WHEN IT WAS SHROUDED BY THE
FREEWAY ABOVE AND WHEN IT FULLY FUNCTIONED.
BUT BELIEVING THAT IT'S NOW TIME FOR A NEW CHAPTER, I'VE
ALSO HEARD FROM OTHERS WHO BELIEVE WE SHOULD RESTORE THIS
FOUNTAIN AND REALLY CHERISH ITS ROLE AND CONTINUED ROLE IN THE
ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY OF OUR CITY.
THE DECISION BEFORE US TODAY IS NOT TO CHOOSE BETWEEN THESE TWO
ARGUMENTS BUT RATHER IT IS REALLY FOCUSED NARROWLY ON THE
QUESTION OF WHETHER THIS PROJECT IS EXEMPT FROM FURTHER
ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW PURSUANT TO AN EMERGENCY STATUTORY
EXEMPTION DUE TO THE CONDITION OF THE FOUNTAIN.
AFTER REVIEWING THE MATERIALS HEARING THE PRESENTATIONS TODAY
,I DO BELIEVE THAT THIS FOUNTAIN WHICH IS A 710 TON
CONCRETE STRUCTURE POSES A SIGNIFICANT PUBLIC SAFETY
HAZARD. AS SUCH I BELIEVE IT QUALIFIES
FOR THE STATUTORY EXEMPTION CREATED EXACTLY FOR THIS REASON
TO PREVENT DAMAGE TO INDIVIDUALS AND PUBLIC
PROPERTY. WHEN SUCH CONDITIONS EXIST.
SO GIVEN THIS I WOULD RECOMMEND THAT THE BOARD UPHOLD THE
EMERGENCY STATUTORY EXEMPTION DETERMINATION AND DENY THE
APPEAL OF THE SEQUEL DETERMINATION.
AS SUCH I WOULD MAKE A MOTION TO AFFIRM ITEM 21 AND TABLE
ITEMS 22 AND 23 SEVERITY WHEREAS SAUTER HAS MADE A
MOTION. IS THERE A SECOND?
SUPERVISOR CHERYL SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANKS PRESIDENT
GENTLEMEN. SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU TO
EVERYONE FOR COMING OUT. I THINK THEY'RE VALID ARGUMENTS
ALL AROUND. >> I REMAIN DEEPLY CONCERNED
ABOUT HOW RICHMOND PARK HAS REALLY PRIORITIZED THIS
PARTICULAR SPACE AND DOWNTOWN AND OTHER PARK SITES AND THE
DUNES THE PAST COUPLE OF YEARS AND I BELIEVE THAT IS VERY
CONCERNING IN LIGHT OF BUDGET DEFICITS, IN LIGHT OF INCREASED
FARES AND SORRY FEES FOR PARK FACILITIES AND ESPECIALLY IN MY
DISTRICT DISTRICT NINE. IN LIGHT OF THE FACT THAT PARKS
IN MY DISTRICT FOUR OF THE 18 LOWEST SCORING PARKS ARE
SITUATED IN THE MISSION, THERE WAS A REPORT THAT CAME OUT BY
THE COMPTROLLER'S OFFERS OFFICE STIPULATING THIS AND AROUND 45%
OF THE LOWEST SCORING PARKS ARE AN EQUITY ZONES WHICH ARE
REGIONS THAT HAVE HISTORICALLY EXPERIENCED ENVIRONMENTAL
HEALTH RISKS. THIS IS THE SAME PROPORTION AS
THE EQUITY THE EQUITY ZONE PARKS IN THE CITY AND THIS IS
OBVIOUSLY ABOUT THE FOUNTAIN. THIS IS ABOUT SAFETY, THIS IS
ABOUT RENOVATION AND THIS IS ABOUT REDEVELOPMENT AND HAVING
QUALITY OF LIFE FOR THE RESIDENTS AROUND.
>> IT'S ABOUT HISTORY. IT'S ABOUT ARCHITECTURE AND FOR
ME IT IS REALLY PLAINLY FROM MY PERSPECTIVE ALSO ABOUT MONEY
AND POWER AND THIS PARTICULAR TO CITY GOVERNMENT AND ITS
HISTORY AND RESPONDING TO CONSTITUENTS AND POWERS THAT
HAVE BE THE CAPITAL TO BE ABLE TO TO DO WHAT THEY WANT IN THE
CITY. AND SO I WILL BE CASTING MY
VOTE AS SUCH. >> THANK YOU.
>> ALL RIGHT. SINCE NO OTHER NAMES ON THE
ROSTER, MADAM CLERK, WOULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
SUPERVISOR SADR'S MOTION ON THE MOTION TO APPROVE ITEM 21
AND TABLE ITEMS 22 AND 23 SUPERVISOR SAUTER.
SAUTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MENDELSON I AND SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I THERE ARE TEN EYES AND ONE NO WITH SUPERVISOR
FIELDER VOTING NO WITHOUT OBJECTION ITEM 21 IS APPROVED
AND ITEMS 22 AND 23 ARE TABLED. MADAM CLERK THAT CONCLUDES OUR
THREE HOUR FIRST 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER.
LET'S GO TO OUR NEXT 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER PLEASE CALL ITEMS
24 THROUGH 27 TOGETHER ITEMS 24 THROUGH 27 COMPRISE THE PUBLIC
HEARING OF PERSONS INTERESTED IN THE APPROVAL OF A
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION PURSUANT TO PLANNING CODE
SECTION TWO 10.1 AND 303 FOR A PROPOSED PROJECT AT 8 TO 5
SANSOM STREET THAT INVOLVES A CHANGE OF USE FROM THE EXISTING
PUBLIC PARKING GARAGE USE WITH SNYDER SIX PARKING SPACES
AND THE ESTABLISHMENT OF A PRIVATE FLEET CHARGING USE AT
THE UPPER LEVEL A PUBLIC ELECTRIC VEHICLE CHARGING
LOCATION USE AT THE GROUND LEVEL AND A PARKING A PRIVATE
PARKING GARAGE USE AT THE BASEMENT LEVEL AT THESE SUBJECT
PROPERTY AN EXISTING ENCLOSED TWO STORY MULTILEVEL PUBLIC
PARKING GARAGE WITH THE BASEMENT ITEMS 2526 AND 27 ARE
THE MOTIONS MOTIONS ASSOCIATED WITH THAT PUBLIC HEARING.
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU PRESENT GENTLEMEN ON THESE
ITEMS. WE ARE HAVING PRODUCTIVE
CONVERSATIONS WITH THE PARTIES INVOLVED AND WE HAVE AGREEMENT
FROM BOTH BOTH PARTIES TO CONTINUE THIS ITEM CONTINUE TO
FEBRUARY THIRD. SO WITH THAT I'D LIKE TO MOVE
TO CONTINUE THESE ITEMS TO FEBRUARY 3RD.
>> ALL RIGHT. SO AS FAR AS MADE A MOTION TO
CONTINUE THIS ITEM TO FEBRUARY 3RD, 2026, THESE ITEMS THAT HAS
BEEN SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND BEFORE WE VOTE ON
THAT MOTION WE NEED TO TAKE PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE
CONTINUANCE SO IF THERE ARE ANY MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD
LIKE TO SPEAK TO US ABOUT THE THE CONTINUANCE, PLEASE COME
FORWARD AND IF FOLKS CAN TAKE THEIR CONVERSATIONS OUT INTO
THE OUTSIDE THE CHAMBER ARE AT PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE
CONTINUANCE IS CLOSED AND SO SUPERVISES AS IT'S NOT OUR
AGAIN HAS MADE A MOTION TO CONTINUE THESE HEARINGS OPEN TO
THE FEBRUARY THIRD 2026 BOARD OF SUPERVISORS MEETING AND THAT
HAS BEEN SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND COLLEAGUES.
I HOPE WE CAN TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION WITHOUT OBJECTION.
THE APPEAL HEARING AND MOTIONS ARE CONTINUED OPEN TO FEBRUARY
3RD, 2026. ALL RIGHT.
>> AND NOW WE GO BACK. >> MADAM CLERK TWO ITEM 17.
>> ITEM 17 IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE FIRST AMENDMENT TO
THE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY AND A AND A HEALTH SERVICE INC
TO PROVIDE REHABILITATIVE BOARD AND CARE RESIDENTIAL SERVICES
TO EXTEND THE TERM BY THREE YEARS FROM JUNE 30TH 2026 FOR A
TOTAL TERM JULY 1ST 2024 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2029 AND TO
INCREASE THE AMOUNT BY APPROXIMATE 23 MILLION FOR A
NEW TOTAL OF 32.6 MILLION. >> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU CALL
THE ROLL ON THIS ITEM ON ITEM 17?
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYES SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR MANDEL MEN HIGH
MANDEL MEN EYE AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I THERE ARE 11
EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
QUIRK WE HAVE ALREADY TAKEN CARE OF ITEM 18 CAN YOU PLEASE
CALL ITEM 19? ITEM 19 THIS IS A MOTION TO
APPOINT SAKAI BAILEY RESIDENTIAL REQUIREMENT WAIVED
AND TIFFANY BOCHY TO THE INCLUSIONARY HOUSING TECHNICAL
ADVISORY COMMITTEE FOR FOUR UNLIMITED TERMS AND COLLEAGUES
I'M IMAGINING WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITH
A BIG NOD FROM FROM CHAIR MELGAR LANDS CHAIR MELGAR
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
>> AND THEN MADAM CLERK LET US GO TO COMMITTEE REPORTS.
>> YES. ITEM 28 WAS CONSIDERED BY THE
RULES COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY JANUARY 12TH
AND WAS RECOMMENDED AS A COMMITTEE REPORT.
ITEM 28 IS A MOTION TO CONFIRM THE MAYORAL REAPPOINTMENT OF
CARMEN CHIU AS CITY ADMINISTRATOR FOR A FIVE YEAR
TERM AND CITY ADMINISTRATOR CHIU AND HER VERY PATIENT
DAUGHTER ARE IN THE AUDIENCE AND SHE'S WAVING AND I DON'T
THINK SHE WANTS TO TALK TO US BUT SHE IS SHE HAVE A WE ARE
GRATEFUL TO YOU AND WITH THAT COLLEAGUES I THINK WE CAN TAKE
THIS ITEM. SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
>> ALL RIGHT. ALL RIGHT.
>> GOOD MOVE. BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS.
>> SUPERVISOR SOLDER YOUR FIRST UP TO INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS
SUBMIT THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR ARE CHERYL
COLLEAGUES OVER THE PAST YEAR ALONG WITH WITH MANY OF US IF
NOT ALL OF US HAVE BEEN VERY FOCUSED ON UNDERSTANDING
AND SEEING HOW WE COULD BETTER SUPPORT THE CITY'S SMALL
BUSINESS COMMUNITY. >> ONE OF THE ELEMENTS THAT I
TALKED TO SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS AND ADVOCATES ABOUT REGULARLY
IS PERMITTING AND ACROSS ALL OF THOSE CONVERSATIONS INS ONE
PERMIT IS REFERENCED OVER AND OVER AGAIN AND THAT IS THE
PERMIT RELATED TO ADA ACCESS FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC
WORKS. WHEN WE TALK ABOUT OPENING
SMALL BUSINESSES, PROVIDING ACCESS FOR ALL SAN FRANCISCANS,
THE ANSWER HAS TO BE SPEED. AND WHEN ONE THING COMES UP
OVER AND OVER AGAIN, I THINK THAT DEMANDS SOME FOCUS.
SO TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A HEARING REQUEST FOCUSED ON
IMPROVING THE CITY'S ADMINISTRATION OF ADA
ACCESSIBILITY REQUIREMENTS AND PERMITTING SO THAT OUR
ENTREPRENEURS CAN QUICKLY OPEN DOORS AND OPEN ACCESS TO EVERY
SAN FRANCISCAN OF ALL AGE SHAPES SIZE ABILITY EVERYTHING
AS QUICKLY AS POSSIBLE. I THINK WE'VE ALL HEARD HORROR
STORIES THROUGHOUT THE CITY. IT'S NOT JUST IN DISTRICT TWO.
I KNOW I'M VERY FAMILIAR WITH WITH WITH A SITUATION
IN DISTRICT ONE THAT MY KNOW MY COLLEAGUE SUPERVISOR CHAN HAD
TO SUFFER THROUGH WITH THE SALT WATER BAKESHOP A TERRIBLE
SITUATION BOB'S DONUTS A LEGACY BUSINESS ANOTHER TERRIBLE
SITUATION IT'S UNACCEPTABLE I THINK WE ALL SEE THIS AND WHILE
PERMIT S.F. IN RECENT LEGISLATION AT THIS BOARD HAS
MADE GREAT STRIDES TOWARDS STREAMLINING OUR PROCESSES,
MORE NEEDS TO BE DONE AS WE LOOK AT ADMINISTERING ADA
ACCESSIBILITY ARE WE PUTTING ENOUGH RESOURCES TOWARDS
ACCESSIBLE CITY? ARE WE SUPPORTING OUR SENIORS
AND OUR DISABILITY DISABLED COMMUNITY IN THE WAY THAT THEY
DESERVE THIS HEARING IS HERE TO MAKE SURE THAT WE ARE A CITY OF
YES A CITY THAT ENABLES NOT OBSTRUCTS AND IT MAKES IT
EASIER FOR SMALL BUSINESSES TO OPEN TO THRIVE AND TO SERVE ALL
SAN FRANCISCANS. THIS WILL BE A KEY STEP TOWARDS
CREATING A COMPREHENSIVE, CLEAR AND CONCISE PERMITTING PROCESS
AND THAT CONVEYS THAT WE ARE ONE CITY GOVERNMENT WORKING
COHESIVELY TO SUPPORT OUR ENTREPRENEURS.
>> I WANT TO GIVE A SPECIAL THANK YOU TO DIRECTOR DEARMAN
AT THE DEPARTMENT OF DISABILITY AND AGING SERVICES DIRECTOR
TANG AT THE SMALL BUSINESS. A SPECIAL THANK YOU TO HARRY
BREAUX, OUR DISTRICT TWO REPRESENTATIVE ON THE
DISABILITY AND AGING SERVICES COMMITTEE, TIM OMI, THE
PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL OF DISTRICT MERCHANTS ASSOCIATION
AND ALSO DISABILITY ADVOCATES AND SENIOR AT SENIOR
IN DISABILITY ACTION. THEIR PARTNERSHIP IS CRITICAL
TO ENSURING ACCESS FOR ALL SAN FRANCISCANS IN A SPEEDY
AND TIMELY MANNER AS POSSIBLE. TOGETHER WE CAN WORK TO ACHIEVE
A BETTER AND QUICKER PROCESS AND I LOOK FORWARD TO
CONTINUING THIS WORK AS WE STRATEGIZE FOR AN INFORMATIVE
AND CONSTRUCTIVE HEARING. >> THANK YOU AND THE REST I
SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
>> I HAVE NOTHING TO SUBMIT SO I SUBMIT.
OKAY. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. SUPERVISOR WON'T SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU,
MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUE TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION URGING OUR COMPTROLLER TO INCORPORATE
ADDITIONAL METRICS IN THE BI MONTHLY COMPTROLLER STATUS OF
SAN FRANCISCO'S ECONOMY. ECONOMY REPORT MONITORING THE
CITY'S PROGRESS TOWARDS A JUST ECONOMIC RECOVERY ACROSS ALL
COMMUNITIES IS VITAL TO ENABLE POLICYMAKERS AND THE PUBLIC TO
PLAN FOR A MORE INCLUSIVE SAN FRANCISCO IN 2021 THE
COMPTROLLER BEGAN TO PUBLISH A BI MONTHLY REPORT ON THE STATUS
OF THE SAN FRANCISCO ECONOMY TO SHED LIGHT ON THE CITY'S
ECONOMIC RECOVERY FOLLOWING THE COVID PANDEMIC.
>> THIS REPORT TRACKS MEASURES SUCH AS HOTEL RATES
AND OCCUPANCY OFFICE ATTENDANCE, TRANSIT RIDERSHIP,
APARTMENT RENTS, AUTHORIZED HOUSING UNITS AND UNEMPLOYMENT
. >> A COMPREHENSIVE
UNDERSTANDING OF THE HEALTH OF OUR LOCAL ECONOMY REQUIRES A
BROADER SET OF INDICATORS THAT REFLECT THE LIVED EXPERIENCES
OF SAN FRANCISCANS INCLUDING OUR WORKERS, OUR CHILDREN, OUR
RESIDENTS AND SMALL BUSINESS. OTHERWISE IT'S A MEASURE OF
ECONOMIC PROGRESS WITHOUT CONSIDERING SHAPE, SHARE
ECONOMIC INCLUSION AND PROSPERITY A ACHIEVING
SHARE ECONOMIC PROSPERITY REQUIRES MAKING SUSTAINED
PROGRESS ON A BROAD RANGE OF INDICATORS.
>> FOR EXAMPLE WORKFORCE WAGE TRENDS ECONOMIC AND ADD IN IN
EQUALITY, FINANCIAL STABILITY, FINANCIAL STABILITY OF SMALL
BUSINESS, HOUSING AFFORDABILITY, DISPLACEMENT,
SOCIAL HOUSING CHANGES TO SOCIAL SAFETY NET RACIAL AGENDA
AND ALDA EQUITY EQUALITY LABOR UNION PARTICIPATION
AND WORKFORCE PREPAREDNESS AND EDUCATION THE CURRENT
MEASURES OF ECONOMIC PROGRESS IN TO CONTROL THE STATUS OF THE
SAN FRANCISCO ECONOMY REPORT FAILS TO ACCOUNT FOR THIS
ESSENTIAL INDICATORS AND THIS MONTH'S UNDERLYING INEQUITIES
IS IMPACTING EVERYDAY SAN FRANCISCANS.
NUMEROUS STUDIES HAVE SHOWN THAT INEQUITY INEQUALITY IS
DETRIMENTAL TO ECONOMIC HEALTH HINDERING LONG TERM GROWTH,
INCREASING INSTABILITY, REDUCING SOCIAL MOBILITY
AND WORSEN OUTCOMES FOR LOW INCOME RESIDENTS.
I KNOW THAT AS A CITY AND COUNTY WE ARE COMMITTED TO
PRINCIPLES OF SHARED ECONOMIC PROSPERITY, RACIAL EQUALITY
AND JUSTICE, ECONOMIC RECOVERY ACROSS ALL COMMUNITIES.
MY OFFICE HAS BEEN WORKING COLLABORATIVELY WITH CHIEF
ECONOMIST TEGAN WHO HAS BEEN A VERY HELPFUL THOUGHT PARTNER
IN DRAFTING THIS RESOLUTION. THE OFFICE OF THE COMPTROLLER
HAS THE EXPERTISE AND DATA NECESSARY TO COMPLY AND AND
ELLEN AND ANALYZE THIS ESSENTIAL METRICS IN AN
IMPARTIAL AND THOUGHTFUL MANNER.
I WANT TO THANK MY EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP ADVISOR CHEN
MALKA AND LOOK FORWARD TO THE REST OF MY COLLEAGUE FOR THEIR
SUPPORT. >> I ALSO HAVE ANOTHER
RESOLUTION THAT I AM INTRODUCING LAST YEAR MORE THAN
30 PEOPLE DIE WHILE IN ICE CUSTODY MAKING IT TO DEATH THIS
YEAR IN MORE THAN TWO DECADES. >> TWO PEOPLE WERE FATALLY SHOT
BY ICE OFFICERS ELICITING PULL OUT RAGEOUS AND DESPAIR AT THE
INABILITY OF ICE TO PROPERLY OBSERVED DUE PROCESS OR ENGAGE
IN OUR COMMUNITIES WITH DOUBT IN SITTING EXTREME VIOLENCE
INCITING EXTREME VIOLENCE. THIS YEAR LESS THAN A WEEK AGO
A WOMAN WAS FATALLY SHOT BY AN ICE OFFICERS IN MINNEAPOLIS
AND TWO INDIVIDUALS WERE SHOT BY CBP AGENT IN PORTLAND.
TODAY I AM ALSO INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION CONDEMNING ICE FOR
ACTIONS THAT HAVE LED TO LOSS OF LIVES TO OUR COUNTRY
INCLUDING IN OUR HOME STATE. >> MANY OF THESE DEATHS ARE
STILL UNDER INVESTIGATION LEAVING FAMILIES
AND COMMUNITIES WITHOUT ADEQUATE ANSWERS SURROUNDING
THE CIRCUMSTANCE THAT WHAT OCCURRED WHILE IN ICE CUSTODY
AND WITHOUT CLOSURE FURTHER DISTRESS DON'T ACCOUNT FOR THE
WIDESPREAD REPORTS OF DEATHS AFTER DISAPPEARANCE OF
COUNTLESS INDIVIDUALS AND THE DEATHS OF THOSE IMPACTED BY THE
STRESS FROM RAMPANT ESCALATION OF ICE ENFORCEMENT.
>> AN ESCALATION OF ICE ENFORCEMENT.
THIS RESOLUTION SEEKS TO MEMORIZE THOSE WHO HAVE LOST
THEIR LIVES. AND IT CALLS FOR ACCOUNTABILITY
FOR THE ACTION OF OUR FEDERAL ENTITIES THAT CONTRADICT PUBLIC
SAFETY AND DUE PROCESS. >> IT CONDEMNS ICE FOR ACTIONS
THAT HAVE LED TO THOSE LOSS OF LIFE BOTH IN BOTH INSTANCE A
FATAL SHOOTINGS AND IN-CUSTODY DEATH.
I URGE OUR STATE AND FEDERAL PARTNERS TO CALL FOR A THIRD
PARTY INVESTIGATION OF ALL DEATHS THAT HAVE OCCURRED AS A
RESULT OF ACTION TAKEN BY ICE OFFICERS.
>> COSTS FOR A MORATORIUM ON ICE DETENTION UNTIL A THIRD
PARTY INVESTIGATION IS CONDUCTED AND CORRECTIVE ACTION
IS IMPLEMENTED. AND REAFFIRM OUR COMMITMENT AS
SUPPORT WE AND REAFFIRM OUR COMMITMENT AS SUPPORT TO
PROTECTING SANCTUARY CITY POLICIES THAT KEEP OUR
IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES SAFE. I WANT TO THANK MY CO-SPONSOR
SUPERVISOR WALTON FIELDER MOORE SUPERVISOR CHEN AND SUPERVISOR
MALKA FOR THEIR SUPPORT AND I SUBMIT THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR CHEN SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES, I AM TODAY
SUBMITTING A LETTER OF INQUIRY TO REQUEST INFORMATION THROUGH
THE SAN FRANCISCO HEALTH SERVICE SYSTEM AS TO WHETHER
BLUE SHIELD OF CALIFORNIA MAY BE ENGAGING IN A PATTERN OF
DENYING OR DELAYING COVERAGE FOR MEDICALLY NECESSARY CARE TO
SAN FRANCISCO EMPLOYEES AND RETIREES IN CITY SPONSORED
HEALTH PLANS. GIVEN THE STRONG POSSIBILITY
THAT THIS COULD RESULT IN A HEARING BEFORE THE BUDGET
AND FINANCE COMMITTEE, I AM SUBMITTING THIS IN PARTNERSHIP
WITH BUDGET CHAIR CONNIE CHEN. I APPRECIATE HER LEADERSHIP ON
THESE ISSUES AND I KNOW WE ARE 100% ALIGNED IN ENSURING THAT
OUR CITY'S WORKERS AND RETIREES GET THE HEALTH CARE COVERAGE
FOR WHICH THEY ARE ENTITLED. LAST WEEK RETIRED SAN FRANCISCO
FIREFIGHTER KEN JONES RECEIVED NOTICE THAT BLUE SHIELD OF
CALIFORNIA AND DENIED COVERAGE TO HIM FOR A CANCER TREATMENT
REGIMEN THAT WAS RECOMMENDED BY HIS UCSF ONCOLOGIST.
THE FOLLOWING DAY NEWS OF THAT DENIAL WAS PRESENTED DURING
PUBLIC COMMENT TO THE HEALTH SERVICE BOARD ON WHICH I SIT.
THERE WE LEARNED FROM MR. JONES FAMILY MEMBERS AND COLLEAGUES
THAT EVEN AFTER HIS PHYSICIANS DETERMINED THAT THE PROPOSED
TREATMENT WAS MEDICALLY NECESSARY TO SLOW THE
PROGRESSION OF HIS STAGE FOUR LUNG CANCER, HIS INITIAL
REQUEST AND THE SUBSEQUENT INITIAL PHYSICIAN APPEAL WERE
DENIED. ALTHOUGH I AM INFORMED THAT
BLUE SHIELD HAS SINCE APPROVED A MODIFIED TREATMENT PLAN FOR
MR. JONES, WE HAVE NOW BEEN MADE AWARE OF THREE OTHER
FIREFIGHTERS FACING CANCER IN WHICH THEIR TREATMENT WAS
INITIALLY DENIED OR DELAYED BY BLUE SHIELD.
IN TWO OF THOSE CASES. TREATMENT WAS ALSO FINALLY
APPROVED BUT ONLY AFTER EXTRAORDINARY ADVOCACY.
COLLEAGUES MAY RECALL THAT THIS BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IN JUNE
2024 TOGETHER WITH THE HEALTH SERVICE BOARD APPROVED THE
ADDITION OF BLUE SHIELD'S MEDICARE ADVANTAGE PRESCRIPTION
DRUG PLAN TO REPLACE A SIMILAR PLAN BY UNITEDHEALTHCARE.
THAT MOVED SAVED MANY MILLIONS OF DOLLARS YOU MAY RECALL BUT
IT WAS NOT WITHOUT CONTROVERSY OR OUT OPPOSITION.
SPEAKING FOR MY OWN VOTE ON THAT I WAS PERSUADED BY A
COMPETITIVE RFP PROCESS WHICH FOUND BLUE SHIELD TO BE THE
MORE AFFORDABLE OPTION. HOWEVER, I ALSO RELIED ON
ASSURANCES THAT THE TRANSITION TO BLUE SHIELD WOULD BE SMOOTH
AND THAT ITS COVERAGE AND ACCESS TO HIGH QUALITY
MEDICAL PROFESSIONALS WOULD BE AS GOOD AS OR BETTER THAN THE
INCUMBENT IT WAS REPLACING. THESE ASSURANCES APPEAR
INCREASINGLY DIFFICULT TO RECONCILE GIVEN WHAT WE HAVE
SEEN PLAY OUT OVER THE LAST YEAR AND I THINK THAT'S
ESPECIALLY TRUE NOW IN LIGHT OF DID NOT DENIALS THAT I JUST
DESCRIBED THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO PROVIDES
HEALTH CARE COVERAGE THROUGH BLUE SHIELD TO APPROXIMATELY
5000 OF OUR EMPLOYEES AND RETIREES.
MANY OF WHOM SELECTED THE PLAN SPECIFICALLY BECAUSE OF THE
CONTINUITY OF CARE WITH UCSF AND OTHER TRUSTED PROVIDERS.
IN PARTICULAR SAN FRANCISCO FIREFIGHTERS WHO FACE
WELL-DOCUMENTED OCCUPATIONAL CANCER RISKS AND WHO BENEFIT
FROM STATUTORY PRESUMPTIONS THAT CANCER IS LINKED TO THEIR
SERVICE SHOULD NOT BE FORCED TO ENCOUNTER NEEDLESS BARRIERS
WHEN SEEKING MEDICALLY NECESSARY CARE.
ACCORDINGLY, OUR LETTER OF INQUIRY SEEKS RESPONSES TO
ASCERTAIN WHETHER EVIDENCE MAY SUGGEST THAT BLUE SHIELD IS
ENGAGING IN POST CLAIM UNDERWRITING PRACTICES TO DENY
MEDICALLY NECESSARY TREATMENT TO OUR CITY WORKERS
AND RETIREES. I AGAIN THANK BUDGET CHAIR CHAN
AND HER TEAM FOR THEIR PARTNERSHIP ON THIS.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR AND I HAVE SPOKEN ABOUT IT TOO AND I
APPRECIATE HER LEADERSHIP ON IT.
FINALLY, THANKS TO THE CLERK OF THE BOARD AND HER OFFICE
IN ADVANCE FOR THEIR WORK TO FACILITATE THE RESPONSES WE
SEEK AND THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY HAPPY TO DO IT.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD PRESIDENT. MADAM CLERK THANK YOU.
COLLEAGUES TODAY AND ACROSS THE COUNTRY WE CONTINUE TO WITNESS
INCREASED IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT ACROSS OUR COUNTRY.
>> THOUSANDS OF DOLLARS ARE BEING SPENT TO DISSEMINATE
RECRUITMENT ADS PROMISING FIVE FIGURE SIGNING BONUSES TO JOIN
THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELAND SECURITY AS AN AGENT AS A
SANCTUARY CITY. >> SAN FRANCISCO HAS LONG BEING
A LEADER IN MAINTAINING A CLEAR SEPARATION BETWEEN LOCAL LAW
ENFORCEMENT AND FEDERAL IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT
IN ORDER TO PROTECT IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES AND PROMOTE
EFFECTIVE, EQUITABLE PUBLIC SAFETY.
>> AT A TIME WHEN OUR CITY IS EXPERIENCING ONGOING PEACE
OFFICER STAFFING SHORTAGES. >> SWORN OFFICERS MUST FOCUS
THEIR TIME AND EXPERTISE ON ADDRESSING LOCAL PUBLIC SAFETY
NEEDS RATHER THAN BEING DIVERTED TO FEDERAL IMMIGRATION
ENFORCEMENT ACTIVITIES. >> THAT'S WHY TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION IN SUPPORT OF ASSEMBLYMEMBER
ISAAC BRYAN'S ASSEMBLY BILL NUMBER 1537 WHICH PROHIBITS
PEACE OFFICERS FROM BEING EMPLOYED BY CONTRACTING WITH OR
VOLUNTEERING FOR THE UNITED STATES DEPARTMENT OF HOMELAND
SECURITY OR ANY ENTITY THAT ASSISTS WITH IMMIGRATION
ENFORCEMENT. >> I ALSO WANT TO TAKE A MOMENT
TO THANK THE PUBLIC DEFENDER'S OFFICE FOR THEIR LEADERSHIP
AND PARTNERSHIP WITH ASSEMBLYMEMBER BRIAN AND THE
ICE OUT OF CALIFORNIA COALITION AS WELL AS CHINESE FOR
AFFIRMATIVE ACTION FOR THEIR STRONG SUPPORT FOR THIS
RESOLUTION AS WELL. >> HB 1537 WOULD REQUIRE PEACE
OFFICERS TO REPORT ANY OFFER OR ATTEMPT OF SECONDARY EMPLOYMENT
RELATED TO IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT TO THEIR EMPLOYING
LAW ENFORCEMENT AGENCY ENSURING TRANSIT AGENCY
AND ACCOUNTABILITY WITHIN LOCAL DEPARTMENTS.
>> DECADES OF RESEARCH AND LIVED EXPERIENCE HAVE
DEMONSTRATED THAT ENTANGLEMENT BETWEEN LOCAL LAW ENFORCEMENT
AND FEDERAL IMMIGRATION FORESMAN UNDERMINES PUBLIC
SAFETY BY DISCOURAGING IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES FROM
REPORTING CRIMES, COOPERATING WITH INVESTIGATIONS OR SEEKING
EMERGENCY ASSISTANCE BY CLEARLY PROHIBITING POLICE OFFICERS
FROM PARTICIPATING IN IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT.
AB 1537 STRENGTHENS OUR STATE'S COMMITMENT TO CIVIL RIGHTS,
CONSTITUTIONAL PROTECTIONS AND COMMUNITY CENTERED PUBLIC
SAFETY. I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISORS
FIELDER WALTON AND CHEN FOR THEIR EARLY SUPPORT AND MY
LEGISLATIVE DIRECTOR SAM LOGAN AND CHIEF OF STAFF JESSICA
GUTIERREZ GARCIA FOR THEIR WORK ON THIS LEGISLATION AND I HOPE
TO HAVE COLLEAGUES YOUR SUPPORT AS WELL.
>> SECOND COLLEAGUES WANTED TO NOTE THAT ON DECEMBER 12TH OF
LAST YEAR A THREE ALARM FIRE AT 50 GOLDEN GATE AVENUE DISPLACED
NEARLY 142 RESIDENTS INCLUDING FAMILIES WITH YOUNG CHILDREN
AND SENIORS AND MONOLINGUAL TENANTS FORCING THEM FROM THEIR
HOMES AHEAD OF THE HOLIDAY SEASON.
>> THE UNCERTAINTY AND TRAUMA THE RESIDENTS FACED FOLLOWING A
FIRE IS DEEPLY CONCERNING IN CONVERSATIONS WITH RESIDENTS
IMPACTED. >> THEY SHARED WITH ME THAT
THEY HAD LOST PACKAGES WITH CHRISTMAS PRESENTS FOR THEIR
CHILDREN LEFT UNITS THEY HAD CALLED HOME FOR OVER 20 YEARS,
MANY HAVING LEFT WITH NOTHING MORE BUT THE CLOTHES ON THEIR
BACKS. >> THIS IS A REMINDER THAT ANY
ONE OF US IS ONE UNPREDICTABLE EMERGENCY AWAY FROM LOSING IT
ALL AND SITTING ON THE CUSP OF HOMELESSNESS AS A CITY IT IS
OUR RESPONSIBILITY TO PROTECT THE HEALTH, SAFETY AND DIGNITY
OF ALL RESIDENTS ESPECIALLY DURING TIMES OF CRISIS WHEN
FAMILIES ARE DISPLACED, TRAUMATIZED AND AT RISK OF
BECOMING UNHOUSED. >> I'D LIKE TO ACKNOWLEDGE
AND THANK THE WORK OF THE SAN FRANCISCO HUMAN SERVICES AGENCY
IN COORDINATION WITH THE AMERICAN RED CROSS AND OTHER
CITY DEPARTMENTS WHICH RESPONDED BY ESTABLISHING AN
EVACUATION CENTER, COORDINATING EMERGENCY TRANSPORTATION,
PLACING RESIDENTS IN HOTELS AND ADMINISTERING THE TEMPORARY
ASSISTANCE FOR DISPLACED PERSONS PROGRAM FOR RESIDENTS.
>> DESPITE THESE ACTIONS, THE SCALE AND DURATION OF THE
DISPLACEMENT HAS LEFT MANY RESIDENTS FACING CONTINUED
INSTABILITY AS THOSE IMPACTED HAVE VOICED THE ONE WEEK
DURATION OF TEMPORARY ASSISTANCE PROGRAMS.
AS INSUFFICIENT SECURE HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO'S CONSTRAINED
RENTAL MARKET LEAVING HOUSEHOLDS AT RISK WHEN
ASSISTANCE SUNSETS. >> IN EVALUATING THIS RESPONSE
WE'VE HEARD THAT THE EXISTING DISPLACEMENT RESPONSE SYSTEMS
LEAVE MANY DISPLACED RESIDENTS IN THE MISSING MIDDLE.
EXCLUDING HOUSEHOLDS FROM RENTAL ASSISTANCE DUE TO RIGID
ASSET THRESHOLDS THAT RESIDENTS WITH LIMITED ENGLISH
PROFICIENCY FACE SIGNIFICANT BARRIERS NAVIGATE ADDING
DISPLACEMENT SERVICES EVEN WHEN INTERPRETATION WAS AVAILABLE
AND THAT DISPLACED RESIDENTS FELT LOST IN THE PROCESS
RELYING ON RESIDENT LED HOUSING SEARCHES.
WE MUST DO MORE TO SUPPORT OUR NEIGHBORS IN TIME OF NEED.
>> THAT'S WHY TODAY I'M INTRODUCING AN URGENT
RESOLUTION THAT WILL ONE REQUEST THAT WE ADD STAFFING
DEDICATED TO THE CITY'S FIRE DISPLACEMENT RESPONSE INCLUDING
CASE MANAGERS WHO CAN PROVIDE INDIVIDUALIZED AND CONTINUED
SUPPORT TO DISPLACED HOUSEHOLDS TO EXPAND ELIGIBILITY FOR THE
TEMPORARY ASSISTANCE FOR DISPLACED PERSONS PROGRAM BY
RAISING ASSET THRESHOLDS TO ALIGN WITH THE STATE MEDI-CAL
THRESHOLDS FROM 30,000 TO $130,000 FOR SINGLE PERSON
HOUSEHOLDS AND THREE STRENGTHEN LANGUAGE ACCESS SERVICES FOR
FURTHER ALIGNMENT TO THE LANGUAGE ACCESS ORDINANCE TO
FACILITATE THE APPLICATION AND PROCESSES RELATED TO
DISPLACEMENT AND RECOVERY. I'D LIKE TO THANK MY
LEGISLATIVE AIDE WILL MAXEY AND CHIEF OF STAFF JESSICA
GUTIERREZ GARCIA AND MY OFFICE FOR WORKING ON THIS PIECE OF
LEGISLATION. >> ULTIMATELY OUR DISASTER
RESPONSE MUST BE ROOTED IN EQUITY TRANSPORT AGENCY
AND COMPASSION ENSURING THAT NO FAMILY DISPLACED BY A FIRE IS
LEFT WITHOUT SHELTER, SUPPORT OR A CLEAR PATH TO PERMANENT
HOUSING. >> I HOPE TO HAVE YOUR SUPPORT
COLLEAGUES. >> LASTLY, COLLEAGUES TODAY IS
MY DISTINCT PRIVILEGE TO HONOR THE LIFE AND LEGACY OF BOB WEIR
,LEGENDARY MUSICIAN AND CULTURAL ICON AND BELOVED
MEMBER OF SAN FRANCISCO'S RICH ARTISTIC COMMUNITY.
>> BOB WEIR WAS BORN ROBERT HALL WEIR IN OCTOBER 1947
PASSED AWAY ON JANUARY 10TH AT THE AGE OF 7878, SURROUNDED BY
FAMILY AND LOVED ONES AFTER COURAGEOUSLY BATTLING ILLNESS.
>> AS A FOUNDING MEMBER AND RHYTHM GUITARIST A PALO
ALTO GRATEFUL DEAD WHERE I WAS BORN, BOB HELPED CREATE A SOUND
THAT BECAME THE SOUNDTRACK OF A GENERATION.
>> HIS INNOVATIVE GUITAR WORK, SOULFUL VOCALS AND RESTLESS
CREATIVE SPIRIT WERE CENTRAL TO THE BAND'S EVOLUTION FROM A
LOCAL SAN FRANCISCO ACT INTO A GLOBAL PHENOMENON THAT
CONTINUES TO INFLUENCE MUSIC AND CULTURE AND INSPIRE
COMMUNITIES THROUGHOUT THE WORLD.
>> FOR MORE THAN 60 YEARS, BOB BROUGHT JOY AND INSPIRATION
THROUGH MUSIC BY BLENDING ROCK, BLUES, FOLK AND IMPROVISE
IMPROVIZATIONAL EXPLORATION IN WAYS THAT CHALLENGED GENRE
AND UNITED FANS ACROSS CULTURES AND GENERATIONS.
>> HIS CONTRIBUTIONS TO SONGS LIKE SUGAR MAGNOLIA PLAYING
IN THE BAND AND TRUCKIN HOLD A PERMANENT PLACE IN THE AMERICAN
MUSIC CANON. >> BOB'S INFLUENCE STRETCHED
FAR BEYOND PERFORMANCE. HE EMBODIED THE SPIRIT OF
COMMUNITY THAT DEFINES OUR CITY .
THROUGHOUT HIS LIFE BOB FOSTERED CONNECTION, CREATIVITY
AND A SENSE OF SHARED EXPERIENCE.
THROUGH GRATEFUL DEAD'S LEGENDARY TOURS, BENEFIT
CONCERTS AND OUTREACH EFFORTS, BOB HELPED BUILD A WORLDWIDE
COMMUNITY CALLED DEADHEADS. >> THE DEADHEAD COMMUNITY IS A
COMMUNITY THAT IS ROOTED IN MUSIC, COMPASSION
AND FREEDOM. >> HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO, BOB
WEIR'S PRESENCE WAS NEVER SOLELY MUSICAL.
IT WAS CULTURAL AND CIVIC. >> FROM THE EARLY DAYS AT THE
FILLMORE AND AVALON BALLROOM THROUGH HISTORIC PERFORMANCES
IN GOLDEN GATE PARK CELEBRATING 60 YEARS OF MUSIC, BOB'S
ARTISTRY WAS WOVEN TIGHTLY INTO THE FABRIC OF OUR CITY'S
IDENTITY. >> NOWHERE IS THAT CONNECTION
TO THE CITY FELT MORE STRONGLY THAN HAIGHT-ASHBURY, WHICH CAME
ALIVE WITH TRIBUTES TO BOB AND THE DEAD.
>> OVER THE WEEKEND. >> TODAY WE EXTEND OUR DEEPEST
CONDOLENCES TO BOB'S WIFE NATASHA, HIS DAUGHTERS SHARLA
AND CHLOE AND ALL WHO LOVED HIM.
>> HIS PASSING IS FELT BY A GLOBAL COMMUNITY OF FANS
AND FRIENDS WHOSE LIVES WERE TOUCHED BY HIS SOUND.
HIS SPIRIT AND GENEROSITY. >> BOB WEIR ONE SPOKE OF MUSIC
AS A JOURNEY WITHOUT A FINAL CURTAIN.
HE DESCRIBED MUSIC AS A REFLECTION OF HIS VISION THAT
THE SONG AND THE HEART OF THE COMMUNITY LIVES ON.
>> IN THAT SPIRIT WE REMEMBER HIM NOT JUST FOR WHAT HE
CREATED BUT FOR HOW HE SHARED IT WITH OTHERS WITH AN OPEN
HEART. >> MAY BOB WEIR'S LEGACY
CONTINUE TO RESONATE IN EVERY CORNER OF SAN FRANCISCO
AND BEYOND AS A LASTING TRIBUTE TO A LIFE LIVED BOLDLY WITH
LOVE AND MUSIC AS HIS GUIDING FORCES.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
>> BEFORE WE GO THERE, IF SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD HAS NO
OBJECTION I'D LIKE TO HAVE THAT COME FROM THE ENTIRE BOARD AS
WELL. SO WITHOUT OBJECTION WE'LL DO
THAT IN MEMORIAM FROM SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD ON BEHALF OF
THE ENTIRE BOARD. >> SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU
BOARD PRESIDENT. I BUT WHERE AND THE GRATEFUL
DEAD IS ALSO AN IMPORTANT ASSET IN THE SHOW 11 I JUST WANT TO
THANK SUPERVISOR MEMO FOR DOING THAT AND THANK YOU FOR DOING IT
AS A FULL BOY. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN SUPERVISOR
MILKER. >> SUBMIT THANK YOU OR MR.
PRESIDENT SEEING NO OTHER NAMES ON THE ROSTER THAT CONCLUDES
THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS EXCEPT FOR THE
PRESIDENT. >> OH, SO SAD, MADAM CLERK.
>> FIRST, MR. PRESIDENT. I MEAN DO HAVE A FEW
INTRODUCTIONS. ALL RIGHT, COLLEAGUES, FIRST I
AM INTRODUCING LEGISLATION TO ESTABLISH AN ENTERTAINMENT ZONE
IN AND AROUND DOWNTOWN GLEN PARK.
THIS ENTERTAINMENT ZONE WILL ALLOW RESTAURANTS AND BARS ON
DIAMOND STREET, HENRY STREET AND MONTEREY BOULEVARD TO SELL
ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGES TO GO FOR OUTDOOR CONSUMPTION DURING
EVENTS AND ACTIVATIONS SUCH AS THE GLEN PARK NIGHT MARKETS
ALREADY ESTABLISHED ENTERTAINMENT ZONES HAVE HELPED
SUPPORT SUCH EVENTS IN COAL VALLEY IN THE CASTRO AND IN
LIGHT OF THOSE SUCCESSES THE GLEN PARK MERCHANTS ARE
INTERESTED IN BRINGING AN EASY TO THEIR NEIGHBORHOOD.
I WANT TO THANK THE GLEN PARK ASSOCIATION FOR WORKING WITH
GPM TO COME UP WITH A MAP AND A PROPOSAL THAT WAS ACCEPTABLE TO
BOTH ORGANIZATIONS. >> I ALSO WANT TO THANK BEN VAN
HOUTEN AND KELLY VARIAN FROM THE OFFICE OF ECONOMIC
AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT, VICKI WONG FROM THE CITY
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE AND CALVIN FROM MY OFFICE FOR ALL OF THEIR
WORK ON THIS LEGISLATION. >> I I'M ALSO TODAY INTRODUCING
RESOLUTIONS TO INITIATE THE PROCESS OF LANDMARKING 28
HISTORIC PROPERTIES IN DISTRICT EIGHT.
THIS BATCH IS ANOTHER INSTALLMENT IN OUR ONGOING
EFFORTS TO ENSURE THE PRESERVATION OF SOME OF THE
MOST HISTORICALLY SIGNIFICANT PROPERTIES IN DISTRICT EIGHTH
NEIGHBORHOODS. EVEN AS THE BOARD HAS ACTED
MOST RECENTLY THROUGH THE PASSAGE OF THE FAMILY ZONING
PLAN TO ENCOURAGE THE DEVELOPMENT OF MORE HOUSING
IN THOSE NEIGHBORHOODS. OF COURSE I BELIEVE WE CAN
PURSUE BOTH GOALS IN PARALLEL AT THE SAME TIME AND I WANT TO
THANK RICH SU GRAY AND ALEX WESTHOFF FROM THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT'S HISTORIC PRESERVATION TEAM AND CALVIN
IN MY OFFICE FOR THEIR WORK ON THESE RESOLUTIONS I BELIEVE
CALVIN HAS HAD TO DO 28 RESOLUTIONS TODAY SO IT'S A
BUSY DAY. >> AND FINALLY I DO WANT TO
THANK SUPERVISOR CHAN ESPECIALLY FOR HER RESOLUTION.
I THINK AND WE WILL CONSIDER THAT AND I'M SURE IT WILL PASS
EVENTUALLY. BUT I THOUGHT THAT FOR TODAY IT
WOULD MAKE SENSE THAT WE ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING
IN MEMORY OF RENE GOOD WHO WAS KILLED ON JANUARY 7TH, 2026 AT
AGE 37 BY A FEDERAL IMMIGRATION AGENT AND MINNEAPOLIS,
MINNESOTA. RENE WAS BORN IN COLORADO
AND WAS A DEVOTED CHRISTIAN WHO WOULD TRAVEL TO NORTHERN
IRELAND FOR MISSION TRIPS WHILE GROWING UP SHE LOVED TO SING
AND STUDIED VOCAL PERFORMANCE IN COLLEGE SHE HAD THREE
CHILDREN AGED 15, 12 AND SIX AND SHE DESCRIBED HERSELF AS A
POET AND WRITER AND WIFE AND MOM.
SHE GRADUATED FROM OLD DOMINION UNIVERSITY IN VIRGINIA WITH AN
ENGLISH DEGREE. IN 2020 SHE WON AN ACADEMY OF
AMERICAN POETS AWARD IN THAT YEAR FOR HER POEM ON LEARNING
TO DISSECT FETAL PIGS. RENEE HAD RECENTLY MOVED TO
MINNEAPOLIS WITH HER SIX YEAR OLD SON, NOW AN ORPHAN AND HER
WIFE. HER WIFE DESCRIBED RENEE AS
MADE OF SUNSHINE AND HER MOTHER REMEMBERED HER AS ONE OF THE
KINDEST PEOPLE I'VE EVER KNOWN LOVING, FORGIVING
AND AFFECTIONATE NEIGHBORS AND FRIENDS RECALL RENEE AS
KIND, GENTLE AND OPEN HEARTED AND SOMEONE WHO CARED DEEPLY
FOR HER FAMILY AND THE COMMUNITY AROUND HER.
THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO MOURNS THE LOSS OF
RENEE GOODE AND EXTENDS OUR DEEPEST CONDOLENCES TO HER
FAMILY AND LOVED ONES AS WELL AS THE PEOPLE OF THE CITY OF
MINNEAPOLIS. REST IN PEACE AND POWER RENEE.
GOOD MAY YOUR MEMORY BE FOR A BLESSING AND IF COLLEAGUES ARE
ALL RIGHT, I LIKE TO HAVE THAT COME FROM THE FULL BOARD.
>> ALL RIGHT. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
THANK YOU. GOT THROUGH THE PRESIDENT THANK
YOU KINDLY, MR. PRESIDENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
SO I THINK WE GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT AT THIS POINT.
YES. ALL RIGHT.
LET'S DO THAT. PLEASE LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT
HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER. YOU'RE ABLE TO SPEAK TO THE
MAYORAL APPEARANCE FOR TODAY'S MEETING.
THE MINUTES IS PRESENTED ITEMS 31 THROUGH 32 ON THE ADOPTION
WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE CALENDAR AND OTHER GENERAL
MATTERS NOT ON TODAY'S AGENDA BUT ARE WITHIN THE BOARD'S
SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION. WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO
MINUTES. >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR FIRST
SPEAKER. WELCOME.
YES THIS CONTENT IS ACTUALLY ACTUALLY I FORGET I MISSED THE
MAYOR'S APPEARANCE TOO. I SAW YOU IS TALKING ABOUT
HUMAN TRAFFICKING IN OUR GREAT SURE SO FIRST STEP AT FIRST I
WAS LIKE YEAH FIRST STEP NOW IT'S IN ESPECIALLY IN SPORTS
ORGANIZATIONS SO IT BASICALLY IS TO ENFORCE SURVEILLANCE SO
IT IS NOT ABOUT HUMAN TRAFFICKING STUFF ONLY IT'S
SPECIFICALLY AGAINST INSTITUTIONALIZED CHILDREN
TRAFFICKING THEREFORE BY THE GOVERNMENT ITSELF.
>> SO WE KNOW IS WE NEED TO TARGET WE WON'T FORGET WE WON'T
FORGET NOBODY ALL THE SHENANIGANS GOING ON NOW IT'S
INCREDIBLE OBVIOUSLY. >> SO WE NEED TO STAY I MEAN I
WILL STAY FOCUSED ON WE ARE WORKING TO STOP INSTITUTIONS
ANALYZED CHILD TRAFFICKING ALL IN THE END OF THE GOVERNMENTS
AND THE MEDIA. SO WHATEVER THEY TRY TO NOW
IT'S NOT GOING TO WORK BECAUSE THEY ARE GUILTY.
THERE IS NO IN THE NAME OF SCIENCE HERE CHILD TRAFFICKING
IS NOT IN THE NAME OF SCIENCE. SO YOU FORGET A I WITH THEIR
MANIPULATION FAKE WHATEVER THOSE BIG PHARMA YOU NAME IT
THAT'S THE ALWAYS IN THE NAME OF SCIENCE.
NO, NO CHILD TRAFFICKING IS NOT IN THE NAME OF SCIENCE.
YOU ARE SECRET. YOU DON'T YOU CANNOT BE IN ANY
POSITION OF A GOVERNMENT BARRIER AND WE'RE GOING TO TAKE
CARE OF YOU. >> IT'S COMING.
WE ARE IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> WE START WITH SAN FRANCISCO
THEN WE'LL SEE HOW IT SPREADS ALL OVER THE STATES, COUNTRY
AND WORLD. >> SO YOU GUYS I DON'T KNOW
HAVE A GOOD DAY. I WON'T BE BACK EVERY WEEK.
NO ANY MORE. THAT'S ENOUGH.
ALMOST THREE YEARS. I'M TRYING TO INJECT YOU BEAUTY
IN YOUR MINDS ALL THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENT.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> HEY, GOOD AFTERNOON
PRESIDENT ADELMAN AND BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS RICHARD SD PETERSON AND I TYPICALLY TALK ON PARCEL
TAXES WHICH I'LL GET TO. >> I'VE BEEN APPROACHED BY SOME
PEOPLE IN MY DISTRICT DISTRICT THAT I SHOULD RUN AS A
SUPERVISOR AND I SAID WELL WHAT'S A NICE CONCEPT A
STRAIGHT IN DISTRICT IN MY LIFETIME?
>> BUT I SAID NO, I'M TOO OLD. WHAT WE REALLY NEED IN DISTRICT
EIGHT IS A COUPLE A COUPLE THAT CAN BE STRAIGHT GAY OR WHATEVER
THAT HAVE CHILDREN IN THE PUBLIC SCHOOL.
>> THAT'S THE REPRESENTATION WE NEED IN DISTRICT EIGHT THEY CAN
BE GAY. THEY CAN BE STRAIGHT, THEY CAN
BE BINARY ARE X Y, Z THAT'S FINE BUT GETTING A DO THE
PARCEL TAXES I NOTICE THAT OUR NEW SUPERVISOR IS BRINGING UP A
A POTENTIALLY A POTENTIAL PETITION OR TWO TO REOPEN THE
THE HIGHWAY. >> THAT'S REALLY A DEAD ISSUE.
I MEAN COME ON WHAT IS IT GOING TO HAPPEN THAT'S ALL SMOKE
AND MIRRORS. YOU'RE GOING TO BRING IT UP
PEOPLE THAT THERE'S GOING TO BE A CITYWIDE ELECTION ARE GOING
TO VOTE IT DOWN AND THEN YOU'RE LEFT IN THE SAME POSITION YOU
ARE TODAY BETTER TO FOCUS ON THINGS LIKE PARCEL TAXES,
PARCEL TAXES BRING US TO THE WEST SIDE VERSUS THE DOWNTOWN.
>> ALL I WANT IS FAIR PARCEL TAXES.
I NOTICE THAT IN THE LATEST 11TH JANUARY 8TH EDITION OF THE
CHRONICLE THEY HAD ANOTHER ARTICLE ON THE ONE THING THAT
WAS AB ABSENT FROM THE ARTICLE WAS THE THE STAKE HOLDERS WHO
ARE HOMEOWNERS. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> ALL RIGHT.
LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> WHEN PEOPLE SAY I SHOULD BE GRATEFUL THAT MAYOR LURIE STOPS
TRUMP SIEGE IN SAN FRANCISCO, I SAY IMMIGRANTS HAVE BEEN UNDER
SIEGE. >> IMMIGRATION COURTS IN SAN
FRANCISCO DID YOU CARE ABOUT THIS?
>> ABOUT THAT THIS PAST YEAR IMMIGRATION AND CIVIL RIGHTS
LAWYERS SUING THE GOVERNMENT AND PROTESTERS ARE THE MAIN
REASONS THE ABDUCTIONS WENT DOWN NOT THE MAYOR.
A MAJORITY OF THE IMMIGRATION JUDGES GOT FIRED BY TRUMP
AND WELL SUPPOSEDLY HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO WILL SUPPOSEDLY BE
REPLACED BY DEPORTATION. >> JUDGES HEAR ANY PROTEST
ABOUT THAT FROM OUR MAYOR? ARE YOU HAPPY YOU DON'T HAVE TO
SEE THE SIEGE ON YOUR STREETS BECAUSE IT REMAINS HIDDEN
IN DOORS. >> JUST ABOUT EVERY PERSON
ABDUCTED BY ICE IN THE BAY AREA COMES HERE FOR INHUMANE ILLEGAL
IMPRISONMENT. ONE OF THE LAWSUITS IS ABOUT
STOPPING THAT AND OUR MAYOR AND MOST OF THE BOARD IS OFTEN
SILENT ABOUT IT ALL. >> SORRY THAT'S NOT GOOD ENOUGH
FOR ME. >> ANY IMMIGRANT IN SAN
FRANCISCO IS AT RISK OF ABDUCTION IN SAN FRANCISCO'S
COURTS AND ICE CHECK INS OR PUBLIC ABDUCTION OUTSIDE OF SAN
FRANCISCO. THE OCTOBER COMPROMISE SEEMS TO
BE KEEP THIS VIOLENCE OUT OF SIGHT AND KEEP OUT OF PEOPLE'S
MINDS HERE SO TOURISTS AREN'T SCARED AWAY AND BUSINESSES CAN
KEEP ON BANKING. I DON'T KNOW THOUGH.
RELEASE THE FILES MAYOR LURIE NOT TO MENTION ALL THE
INCREASED POLICE AND SURVEILLANCE A PERSON CAN
BE TRACKED IN SAN FRANCISCO ABDUCTED OUTSIDE SAN FRANCISCO
WITH SAID SURVEILLANCE LIKE FLOC THAT IS COLLABORATION NOT
PROTECTION ON CONSERVATORSHIP LEGISLATION THAT WAS INTRODUCED
BY STATE ASSEMBLY MEMBER CATHERINE STEPHANY SUPPORTED BY
OUR BOARD PRESIDENT STATE SENATOR SCOTT WIENER, ASSEMBLY
MEMBER MATT HANEY, CITY ATTORNEY DAVID CHIU AND THE
CHIEF OF HEALTH AND HUMAN SERVICES MODY I WOULD READ UP
ON THE SHAMEFUL HISTORY OF THE UGLY LAWS THAT'S WHAT THIS
CONSERVATORSHIP REMINDS ME OF AND THE THE LAWS ABOUT IT
AND THE DSM FIVE TRANS PEOPLE CAN BE DIAGNOSED WITH GENDER
DYSPHORIA. IT IS COMMON FOR INSURANCE TO
REQUIRE THIS DIAGNOSIS TO ACCESS CARE LIKE HORMONE
REPLACEMENT THERAPY BEING THAT THIS FEDERAL ADMINISTRATION
DEEMS TRANS PEOPLE AS MENTALLY ILL.
I DO FEAR LAWS LIKE THIS BEING USED TO TARGET AND IMPRISON
TRANS PEOPLE AS WELL. TODAY THE SUPREME COURT IS
DEBATING TRANS PEOPLE'S HUMANITY AGAIN.
DISTURBINGLY THE PETITIONERS ARE ARGUING FOR CONSTITUTIONAL
RIGHTS TO BE DETERMINED BY POPULATION SIZE AND ASKING FOR
A CONSTITUTIONAL DEFINITION OF WHAT DEFINES BIOLOGICAL SEX.
>> DO YOU CARE? >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> ALL RIGHT.
MY NAME IS SCARLETT SWAN. IT'S CONNIE.
YOU ALREADY HAVE A CAN YOU GRAB YOUR MICROPHONE, SIR?
WE CAN BARELY HEAR YOU. HOLD ON ONE SECOND, SIR.
DON'T ADDRESS MEMBERS DIRECTLY. ADDRESS YOUR COMMENTS TO THE
BOARD AS A WHOLE. >> I'LL START YOUR TIME NOW.
THANK YOU. HELLO.
MY NAME IS CARLOS MUNIZ. I HAVE BEEN HAVING A LOT OF
PROBLEMS WITH THE HOUSING ISSUE.
I FEEL THAT I'M THE VICTIM OF THE SHALLOW THINKING OF THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. I'M GOING TO LEAVE A COUPLE OF
PIECES OF PAPER HERE FOR YOU TO FOLLOW UP ON.
>> WE WILL COME COLLECT THAT FROM YOU.
AND ANYWAY, IT ALL STARTED WHEN I BOUGHT MY HOUSE HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO 2627 YEARS AGO. AND WHEN IT WAS FINISHED OF AN
IMMIGRANT FAMILY FROM CHINA CAME TO US SAYING THAT THEY
WERE IN DESPERATE NEED OF HOUSING.
OUR HOUSE WAS NOT SET UP FOR THAT.
HOWEVER, I LET THEM STAY THERE SINCE MY DOWNSTAIRS WAS SET UP
FOR MY OWN LITTLE WORKSHOP AND I GAVE THAT UP.
THEY ENDED UP STAYING THERE SOME FEW YEARS AGO.
>> THEY DECIDED THAT OH THEY CAN TAP INTO THE POLICIES OF
THE CITY IN ORDER TO EXTORT MONEY FROM ME.
SO THEY CALLED IN AN ANONYMOUS TIP SAYING THAT THEY WERE
LIVING IN AN ILLEGAL ADU. >> AND EVER SINCE THE BUILDING
DEPARTMENT HAS BEEN COMING AFTER ME THEY DEMOLISHED ONE
STAIRCASE BECAUSE THEY SAID IT WAS NOT UP TO CODE.
AND THEY PUT ONE IN AND IT'S NOT UP TO CODE.
AND THEY PUT IT IN 100%. I'VE BEEN COMPLAINING THEY
DON'T CARE. THEY JUST IGNORE ME.
>> AND NOW I WANT THEM EVICTED .
>> I HAVE TO PAY THEM NEARLY $50,000 TO MOVE OUT.
THAT'S EXTORTION, ISN'T IT? ISN'T THAT UNCONSCIOUS?
>> SITUATIONAL. THIRD FOURTH AMENDMENT THAT THE
CONSTITUTION THIS THIS IS THE WAY YOU GUYS ARE THINKING.
>> YOU KNOW I'M NOT THE ONLY ONE.
THERE ARE A LOT OF OTHER PEOPLE.
I'D LIKE TO INVITE EVERYBODY HERE TO COME TO MY HOUSE
AND SEE FOR YOURSELVES. OKAY.
THANK YOU. MY INFORMATION, SIR, PLEASE GO.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS OR WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. >> GOOD EVENING, SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS EDGAR RYAN SILVA. I'M A RECENT USF GRADUATE
AND THE SON OF FILIPINO IMMIGRANTS.
THE HORRIFIC EXCUSE ME THE HORRIFIC KILLING OF RENE GOOD
DURING A FEDERAL ICE OPERATION SHOOK PEOPLE ACROSS THE
COUNTRY. >> BUT IT HITS ESPECIALLY HARD
IN PLACES LIKE SAN FRANCISCO, A CITY BUILT BY IMMIGRANTS
SUSTAINED BY IMMIGRANTS AND DEFINED BY THE BELIEF THAT
WHERE YOU WERE BORN SHOULD NEVER DETERMINE HOW MUCH
DIGNITY YOU DESERVE. >> WE HAVE TO ASK WHAT KIND OF
SYSTEM WE ARE WILLING TO ACCEPT ONE THAT PROTECTS PEOPLE
AND KEEPS THE COMMUNITIES WHOLE.
OR ONE THAT PUSHES FAMILIES INTO THE SHADOWS.
>> AND CALLS THAT ENFORCEMENT. IMMIGRANTS CONTRIBUTE
ENORMOUSLY TO THIS CITY'S ECONOMY.
>> THEY PAY SALES TAXES. >> THEY PAY PROPERTY TAXES
THROUGH RENT. THEY CONTRIBUTE BILLIONS INTO
SOCIAL SECURITY AND MEDICARE EVEN THOUGH MANY WILL NEVER BE
ABLE TO COLLECT THOSE BENEFITS. THEY BUILD OUR HOUSING.
>> THEY HARVEST OUR FOOD. THEY CARE FOR OUR ELDERS.
AND THEY KEEP THIS CITY RUNNING.
>> THEY ARE NOT OUTSIDERS. >> THEY ARE PART OF OUR
FOUNDATION. WHEN WE LOOK AT HOW BROKEN
AND SLOW THE LEGAL IMMIGRATION SYSTEM IS WHERE IMMIGRANT
FAMILIES LIKE MINE HAVE TO WAIT YEARS OR EVEN DECADES JUST TO
GET STATUS, DOES IT NOT MAKE MORE SENSE TO HELP PEOPLE
BECOME LEGALIZED AND STABLE THAN TO CRIMINALIZE THEM FOR
SURVIVING INSIDE A SYSTEM THAT BARELY WORKS?
MORAL RIGHTEOUSNESS IN ADDRESSING POLICY DOES NOT
DO ANYTHING UNLESS WE CONSIDER THE ECONOMIC CONSEQUENCES OF
OUR ACTIONS. >> AND THE ECONOMIC TRUTH IS
SIMPLE. TEARING APART A WORKFORCE THAT
GIVES SO MUCH WEAKENS ALL OF US.
>> I URGE THIS BOARD TO KEEP STRENGTHENING IMMIGRANT
PROTECTIONS AND LEGAL DEFENSE PROGRAMS SO THIS CITY TREATS
PEOPLE NOT AS PAPERWORK BUT AS HUMAN BEINGS IN SEARCH OF LIFE,
LIBERTY AND THE PURSUIT OF HAPPINESS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
>> GOOD AFTERNOON. BOARD GRIFFIN LEE HERE
REPRESENTING SUNSET UNITED NEIGHBORS AND STAFF CONNECT TO
THAT STAFF WHERE I'M HERE TODAY TO ASK FOR SUPERVISORS IN THE
ROOM TO SUPPORT SUPERVISOR WONG'S UPPER GREAT HIGHWAY
COMPROMISE BALLOT MEASURE. >> LET'S START LET'S START WITH
THE FACTS. >> CURRENTLY UP UNTIL OR UP
UNTIL SEPTEMBER 2025 REPORTING AND PUBLIC RECORDS SHOW
RECREATION AND PARKS HAS SPENT APPROXIMATELY $1.98 MILLION ON
THE PARK THUS FAR NEARING 2 MILLION MISSION LOCAL REPORTED
80% OF THAT PUBLIC FUNDING. >> I THINK I MAY HAVE.
OH NO. LET'S TALK ABOUT THE CONGESTION
THAT THE CLOSURE HAS LED TO WHICH THE SUNSET AND DISTRICT
FOUR HAS BEEN HURTING ON SINCE THE CLOSURE.
>> SINCE MID-MARCH 2025 SUNSET BOULEVARD TRAFFIC IS UP 31%.
LINCOLN WAY 49%. AND NOOK DRIVE IN GOLDEN GATE
PARK WESTBOUND 20%. >> WE NEED TO RESTORE THE
COMPROMISE. >> THIS IS WHAT'S BEST FOR THE
INTERESTS OF SAN FRANCISCO AND MORE SPECIFICALLY THE WEST
SIDE NOT JUST DISTRICT FOUR BUT DISTRICT SEVEN AND DISTRICT ONE
AND ALL OF THE WEST SIDE. >> PLEASE FOUR SUPERVISOR STEP
UP AND DO YOUR DUTY. >> THANKS SO MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> GOOD EVENING AND HAPPY NEW YEAR.
THIS IS THE FIRST TIME I'VE BEEN HERE THIS YEAR SO HELLO.
>> AND I AM HERE TO ASK THREE SUPERVISORS TO SIGN ON TO
SUPERVISOR WONG'S BALLOT MEASURE.
I BELIEVE THE TIME HAS PROBABLY CLOSED FOR THE JUNE BALLOT.
>> IF IT HASN'T. PLEASE STEP UP NOW.
>> I KNOW THERE'S THREE THAT ARE ALREADY SIGNED ON.
I THINK THERE'S ONE MORE THAT'S NEEDED SO PLEASE STEP UP IF
THERE'S STILL TIME. IF THERE'S NOT I URGE YOU TO
WORK ON THIS FOR THE NOVEMBER BALLOT.
>> IT IS THE RIGHT THING TO RETURN THE GREAT HIGHWAY TWO TO
THE COMPROMISE. AND IF YOU'RE WONDERING HOW
PEOPLE ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO FEEL ABOUT IT NOW THAT THEY
REALIZED THAT THEY WERE SOLD A BILL OF GOODS, THAT THIS WASN'T
THE BUCOLIC PARK IN THE PICTURE THAT WAS SENT TO EVERYBODY THAT
IT'S ACTUALLY JUST A CLOSED ROAD PEOPLE AND THE IMPACT THAT
IT HAS HAD ON D4 AND D1 RESIDENTS PEOPLE ACROSS SAN
FRANCISCO ARE WISHING THAT THEY HAD KNOWN THE TRUTH BEFORE THEY
VOTED. NOW THAT THEY'VE SEEN THE
ACTUAL REALITY THEY WOULD LIKE TO VOTE ON REALITY.
>> AND IF YOU HAVE ANY QUESTION KTVU RUN RAN A POLL TODAY
AND THE LAST I SAW 77% OF SAN FRANCISCANS SAID THEY WANTED IT
OPEN EITHER ON JUST ON WEEKDAYS OR ENTIRELY OPEN.
THERE WAS I THINK 23% THAT THEY WERE SAYING THEY WANTED IT
CLOSED. SO YOU KNOW, UPDATED
INFORMATION IF PEOPLE HAD HAD FACTS AND NOT LIES DURING THE
DURING THE THE PRIOR ELECTION PERIOD, THIS WOULD HAVE GONE
VERY DIFFERENTLY. >> SEVERAL MEMBERS OF THIS
BOARD OPPOSED CLOSING THE GREAT HIGHWAY.
>> SO I HOPE YOU'LL STEP UP AND DO THE RIGHT THING.
THIS IS WHAT'S NEEDED FOR WORKING FAMILIES IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THEIR OFFICE OF SAN CISCO.
THE TITLE OF THIS SPEECH IS ANIMAL CARE.
I WORK IN SIX FLAGS DISCOVERY KINGDOM AND FOR FOUR YEARS FROM
JUNE OF 2007 TO YEAR, END OF YEAR 2012 I'M A THIRD YEAR.
MY SUPERVISOR CAME TO ME, WARNED ME ABOUT THE PROTESTERS
OUTSIDE THE PARK ENTRANCE TO ANIMALS KNOW OUR ENTRANCE.
I WAS TOLD TO IGNORE THEM WHEN GUESTS ASKED ABOUT HOW TO KEEP
QUIET AND DIVERT ANY VERBAL EXCHANGE OF PUBLIC RELATIONS
DEPARTMENT. EVENTUALLY ANIMAL RIGHTS WON A
COURT RULING IN 2019. SINCE THEN I DEVELOPED A SENSE
OF PRIDE. I STAND IN KNOWLEDGE OF ANIMAL
CARE AFTER DAYS MY DAYS AND SIX FLAGS OUR ADVERTISING FROM
GIANT UBER FOR TEN YEARS. USUALLY WHEN I GO OUT AN AGED
ENGAGEMENT MY BEST FRIEND MAGGIE WANG WHO HAPPENS TO BE
MISS CHINATOWN OR SAM CISCO AND MISS POPULARITY I MISS
CHINESE INTERNATIONAL TOLD ME I OVER TALK I TALK TOO MUCH.
>> DEREK PLEASE STOP TALKING AND JUST HELP ME SHOOT
PICTURES. MAGGIE WOULD INSIST.
AND THAT'S WHY I REACH A CYCLE AT YOUR BREAKING POINT.
I CAN TEACH MYSELF TO BE INTERESTED BECAUSE I AM
INTERESTING. >> I CAN TALK ALL ABOUT THE
ANIMALS IN THE DISCOVERY KINGDOM AND THAT'S ONLY A TINY
FACET ABOUT ME. >> I KNOW FOR US THAT COUGARS
OR MOUNTAIN LIONS ARE SAME THING TO NAME.
I ALSO KNOW THAT YOU'RE NOT SUPPOSED TO LOOK AT DOLPHINS OR
SEALS AND SEA LIONS DIRECTLY BECAUSE JUST LIKE BIRDS TO GO
CRAZY ALLIGATORS HAVE SHARP SNOUTS AND CROCODILES ARE BLUNT
ONES. I ALSO VISIT A CLASS THAT I'VE
BEEN OUT THERE CIVIL QUACK WAS A TACO DIVORCE AND A MOVIE FEED
THE FIRST DAY STARRING ANNA SANDLER AND DREW BARRYMORE WHO
PASSED AWAY IN 2015 OR 3 YEARS AFTER I LEFT.
SO FAR SO IN ALL I APPRECIATE ANIMAL CONSERVATION
AND CONSERVATION IS NOT AN ANIMAL ACTIVIST.
I APPRECIATE THE DEEP UNDERSTANDING OF HUMANITY
AND HOW LIFE COULD COEXIST WITH EACH OTHER.
>> A BUNCH OF SMART PHONES AND GET AROUND US.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. YES, WE WILL COME OH AS OF GOV
TV PLEASE. UH, HI SUPERVISORS.
UM DAVID IS GOOD WITH RINCON POINT NEIGHBORS.
UM, I'VE HAD SOMETHING OF A CHANGE OF HEART.
WE WANT TO ENCOURAGE YOU TO OPPOSE OR AMEND THE MAYOR'S
PROPOSED ORDINANCE THAT WOULD ALLOW DEVELOPERS TO NOT PLANT
TREES. IT WOULD ALSO PROHIBIT SOME
APPEALS. WE SENT YOU ALL EMAILS AT 3:15
P.M. TODAY ABOUT AN APPEAL WE ARE WE CURRENTLY HAVE IN THE
WORKS THAT DEMONSTRATES THE NEED FOR APPEALS.
PLEASE ASK YOUR STAFF MEMBERS TO PROVIDE YOU WITH OUR EMAIL
BEFORE YOU VOTE ON THAT MATTER. AGAIN IT WAS SENT TO YOU AT
3:15 P.M. TODAY TO YOUR PRIMARY ADDRESSES.
UM OUR APPEAL IS GOING FORWARD BECAUSE DPW WANTS TO KILL SEVEN
TREES SOME SIGNIFICANT ON THE EASTERN HOWARD STREET.
WELL THEY KEEP SAYING THESE SEVEN TREES WOULD INTERFERE
WITH THE HOWARD STREETSCAPE PROJECT.
THEY PROVIDE NO SERIOUS EVIDENCE OF THAT.
>> ALMOST ALL THE REASONS GIVEN IN A HEARING IN THE EMAIL
COMMUNICATIONS ARE COSMETIC IN NATURE.
THE EMAIL INCLUDES DPW AS STREETSCAPE PLANS WHICH SHOW
THE TREES OR REPLACEMENTS ALL IN THE SAME PLACE AND ALSO HAS
PHOTOS OF THE TREES. THE EMAIL I REFERENCED IN A
ZOOM LINK TO THE DPW HEARING ABOUT THE PROJECT DPW STAFF
STATED FIVE TREES ARE SLATED FOR REMOVAL BECAUSE THEY'RE NOT
GROWING FAST ENOUGH. IS THAT A FIRST?
ANOTHER TREE IS SIMPLY GROWING INTO ITS METAL GRATE.
ANOTHER TREE IS SLATED FOR REMOVAL BECAUSE THE BRICKS
COVERING THE SOIL AROUND IT ARE LOOSE.
AGAIN THERE'S ALMOST NOTHING ABOUT THE TREES INTERFERING
WITH THE STREETSCAPE PROJECT. THESE BAD DECISIONS NEED TO BE
APPEALED. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU DAVID OSGOOD FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> MY NAME IS HERB DUFFY. I'M A SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENT.
SOME SOME TIME I'VE LIVED HERE LONGER THAN THE NEW POLICE
CHIEF JUST 5252 YEARS. SOMETIMES I THINK THERE ARE
ISSUES THAT COME UP THAT WHETHER THE ONE I'M THINKING
ABOUT RIGHT NOW IS WHETHER THERE SHOULD BE A PARK AT THE
GREAT HIGHWAY OR NOT. AND SOMETIMES I THINK THE
THINGS GET KIND OF MISSED OR MAYBE THERE'S A BIGGER VISION.
>> AND THAT IS THAT VERY FEW PEOPLE KNOW THAT THERE'S A
SUBSURFACE SEAWALL FROM RIVIERA TO TERRIBLE STREET AND IT WORKS
VERY EFFECTIVELY AND NOBODY EVEN KNOWS IT'S THERE MOST OF
THE TIME. YOU KNOW THE SAND COMES IN AND
THEN IT GOES OUT AGAIN. IT'S ONLY IN TIMES OF EXTREME
EROSION THAT YOU SEE THIS SEAWALL.
IT'S ACTUALLY QUITE A BIT OUT INTO THE BEACH.
AND I THINK THAT THAT SPEAKS TO A YOU KNOW, A STRATEGY BY WHICH
WE COULD REBUILD NOT WE'VE DONE VERY GOOD WITH REBUILDING THAT
THE THE SAND DUNES ON IT ON THE NORTHERN PART OF THE GREAT
HIGHWAY BUT WE COULD EXTEND THOSE STANDARDS ALL THE WAY
DOWN TO BOULEVARD. WITH THAT TECHNIQUE AND I THINK
YOU KNOW IT'S SOME OF THE MOST VALUABLE PROPERTY IN THE WORLD
AND I THINK WE SHOULD TRY TO PRESERVE IT.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED.
MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR FOR ADOPTION ABOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 31 AND 32 YES ITEMS 31 AND 32 WERE
INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION BUT WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE.
A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON
FIRST APPEARANCE TODAY. ALTERNATIVELY, A MEMBER MAY
REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS 31 AND 32 ON ITEMS 31
AND 32. SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I.
SUPERVISOR WANG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I. SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER. FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANAGEMENT I AND SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I THERE ARE 11 EYES.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
>> THERE ARE NONE TO REPORT. >> MR. PRESIDENT, COULD YOU
PLEASE READ THE IN MEMORIAM? YES.
TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE
FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS. ON A MOTION MADE BY PRESIDENT
RANDLEMAN TO BE ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
FOR THE LATE RENE NICOLE GOOD. ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR MAHMUD
AND SUPERVISOR CHANTE CHEN JOINED IN ON THAT MADE A MOTION
THAT THIS IN MEMORIAM BE ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS FOR A LEGENDARY MEMBER OF THE GRATEFUL DEAD
PLAYING RHYTHM GUITAR AND SINGING VOCALS, A ROCK
AND ROLL HALL OF FAMER AND DEDICATED SAN FRANCISCAN
BOB WHERE THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
I THINK THAT BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA.
>> DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY.
>> THEN WE ARE ADJOURNED. 20